STEPHANIE WEIRICH: Hello, my name
is Stephanie Weirich
and I'm the General
Chair of ICFP, 2020.
And I'd like to welcome
you to Session 4 of ICFP.
Our first talk comes from
one of my favorite
categories of ICFP papers,
Functional Pearls.
The emphasis of papers
in this category
is on the clarity of exposition
and I'm sure that you'll agree that
this paper is a beautiful read.
This paper will be presented
by Lionel Parreaux
and he will tell us about
The Simple Essence of
Algebraic Subtyping,
Principal Type with Principal
Subtyping Made Easy.
LIONEL PARREAUX: Hi, I'm Lionel Parreaux
and I will present
my functional pearl
on the simple essence of
algebraic subtyping.
But first, what exactly
do we mean by subtyping?
Subtyping is a type
system feature used to
model the relative
specificity of types.
For instance, the type
nat of natural numbers
is strictly more specific than int
because all nat values
are also int values.
But the converse is not true.
In this work, we focus
on inclusive subtyping,
in which the types in
a subtyping relationship
share compatible runtime
representations,
meaning that no runtime
coercions are needed.
Inclusive subtyping
is useful
because it can express relationships
between data types
based on their variance.
For instance, since the list
data type is covariant,
nat list is a subtype of int list.
So that a list of natural
numbers can be used in place
where a list of
integers is expected.
Moreover, we focus on
implicit subtyping,
which means that expressions
of a certain type
do not need to be annotated,
in order to be used at
a less specific type.
So when we write 1+2,
we don't need to explicitly annotate
1 as being of type int, although
it's also of type nat.
Now let us see a few
examples of subtyping.
Singleton types are types
which represent single values.
For instance, the type written 0
is the singleton type
of the value 0.
Union types are used
to type expressions,
which can be either one
of two given types.
Intersection types are
used to type expressions,
which are of both given types.
As an example, subtyping
relationship between these,
the type 0 is a subtype
of the union of 0 and 1,
which is itself a subtype of nat.
In fact, subtyping naturally
lets us design types,
which are as close as desired to
corresponding operations and values.
For instance, we can define
the singleton type of empty lists
as well as the type of
prepending a value to a lists.
This allows us to use
the same list syntax
in representation to
express things like
tuple types, non-empty lists
and everything in between.
Subtyping is not just for
object-oriented programming.
In fact, it has found
a host of applications
in functional programming.
It can, for example, be used
for predicate refinement types,
first-class modules, XML
transformations and much more.
Now some may be under the impression
that functional languages,
usually try to avoid subtyping.
But, in fact, subtyping is present
in many of those languages
including OCaml, Haskell and Rust.
In Rust, subtyping is used to
relate the location lifetimes.
In Ocaml, where
subtyping is explicit,
it is used in many places such
as polymorphic variants,
first-class modules
and the object system.
In Haskell, subtyping is
used in the context of
first-class polymorphism to check
inferred types against signatures.
Yet all these languages
use type inference engines
based on unification, which
does not
handle subtyping well
and limits its applicability.
What we'd really like is
a way of integrating subtyping
in ML style type inference, more
consistently and reliably.
So first, let's review
the way ML languages
have traditionally inferred
types based on unification,
the Hindley-Milner type
inference algorithm relies
and introducing type variables
when the types of expressions
are not yet known,
and type variables are later
unified with concrete types
or with other type variables,
based on the way these
expressions are used.
As an example, consider
the following term,
which takes two parameters, X and Y,
compares them and returns
the smaller of the two.
We start from a context gamma,
including only the comparison
operation defined
to operate an integer values.
First, we can see that
the outer lambda binding X,
we assign X to
type variable alpha,
and place it in the context,
then we look at
the inner lambda binding Y
and similarly extend the context
with a new type variable, beta.
Then, we consider
the if-then-else expression,
in particular, the condition,
variable X has type alpha
and it's used on the left hand side
of the less than operation,
so we unify alpha with int.
Variable Y has type beta
and it's used on the right hand side
of the comparison operation,
so we unify beta with int.
Then we consider the branches
of the if statement,
the first branch has type alpha,
the second branch
has type beta,
and since the if-then-else
must return a single type,
we unify alpha and beta,
which is the same as unifying
int with int and is trivial.
The result type of
the if-then-else is alpha,
so the result type is int
because we have unified
int with alpha.
The result of the inner
lambda is beta to int,
which is int to int,
and the final result type
is alpha to int to int,
which is int to int to int.
Now let's review how to adapt
this algorithm to subtyping,
instead of tracking
equalities between types,
we now track inequalities
between types.
We do not unify type variables,
but instead we keep track
of their assumed subtypes
and super types, that is we
keep track of their bounds.
We base our approach
on the previous
algorithm called ML-sub,
which was the first to
infer most specific types
in the presence of subtyping,
but whose presentation was complex
and difficult to understand.
In the paper,
the new synthesis
algorithm is introduced,
which is closer to the traditional
type inference algorithm
we have just seen,
and it's easier to
specify and implement.
Going back to our example,
we look at the outer lambda again,
we extend the context with
a new type variable as before,
same for the second
lambda abstruction,
we extend the context with
the new type variable beta.
Then we'll look at
the condition again,
the variable X has type
alpha, but this time,
instead of unifying alpha with int,
we simply specify that alpha
should be a subtype of int,
so we register int as one of
the upper bounds of alpha,
we do the same for beta,
and then we look at the branches.
The first branch has type alpha,
second  branch has type beta,
but this time we introduced
a new type variable
to represent the union
of the two branches.
We constraint this type
variable to be a super type
of the types of both
branches, alpha and beta.
The resulting type of
the inner lambda is beta to gamma,
and the final resulting type
is alpha to beta to gamma,
together with
the inferred constraints.
So we have inferred the type
alpha to beta to gamma,
where alpha is less than
int, beta is less than int,
and alpha union beta
is less than gamma,
which means that
gamma is a super type
of both alpha and beta.
Now the call F of zero and one
is more precisely typed
as nat instead of int,
but is this really a type
we want to show users?
It looks much more confusing
than the type we had before,
we introduced
subtyping into the mix.
In fact, we can inline so to say,
the bounds of each type
variable into the result type
to use the simpler type, this
is called bounds coalescing.
We replace each type
variable occurrence
with the composition of
the variable's bounds.
For occurrences in output position
or in positive position,
we use a union of the type
variable with its lower bounds.
Conversely, for occurrences in
input or negative positions,
we use an intersection
of the type variable
with its upper bounds.
We can actually simplify
these type further
by removing gamma,
which is useless
and merging alpha and beta
using a type expression,
which is much more
compact and easy to read.
Both of these simplifications,
leave us with a type that is
equivalent to the original
unsimplified type,
despite not featuring the same
number of type variables.
To understand why that is correct,
let us first consider
the first simplification.
The main insight here is
that type intersections
can act like upper bounds
to type variables
as long as they are added to
all the negative occurrences
of that variable.
Indeed, using the resulting
function in our case
requires an argument
whose type is a subtype
of the said intersection,
which is to say that
it must be a subtype
of the type variable and each
of its intersected bounds.
In our case,
the bound is just int.
In particular where users
of the function are free
to instantiate alpha to
whatever type they like,
the function will not be callable
if alpha is taken to be a type
whose intersection with
int contains no values.
Next, let us look at
the second simplification.
Here, the insight is
that alpha and beta
are indistinguishable
from each other
since they always occur together
in positive positions,
which is to say here in
the result type of the function.
Formally, the subsumption relation
between two polymorphic types
can be used to reason
about the equivalence
of simplified
and unsimplified types.
To show that one type
subsumes another,
that is tau zero less
than for all tau one,
it is sufficient to
pick an assignment
of tau zero's type variables,
which satisfies tau zero
less than tau one.
For the first subsumption direction,
which is to show that
the original type
subsumes the simplified type,
we can pick the following
variable assignments.
Alpha is left as alpha,
and beta is taken to be alpha.
This makes both types identical,
which trivially means
that the former subsumes the latter.
For the other subsumption direction,
we pick alpha to be
the union of alpha and beta.
Indeed, this instantiation
is sufficient to show
that the simplified type is
a subtype of the original type.
Let us once again go back to
the type inference example,
but this time consider
the same term applied
to the value zero.
We go back to the state of
type inference as we left it.
And now consider
the application of argument zero
of type nat.
This generates a constraint
that nat should be
a subtype of alpha,
which is the argument
type of the function.
So we register nat as
a lower bound of alpha.
But we are not done yet.
We also have to propagate
the constraint,
and check that nat is
also a subtype of int,
which works out.
This gives us the result
type beta to gamma,
with these new constraints,
which yields the following
simplified type.
Alpha intersection int,
to alpha union nat.
But what happens if we
have a type error?
For example, if we tried
to apply the function
with the Boolean literal false?
In this case, we use bool
as a lower bound of alpha,
but while propagating
the constraint,
we are left constraining bool
to be a subtype of int,
which obviously leads to an error.
As you can imagine, there's
a lot more to talk about.
You can read the paper to
learn about let-polymorphism,
which complicates
the picture quite a bit,
the handling of recursive constraints,
different approaches to
type simplification.
The soundness and completeness
of type inference,
and how subtyping
enables typing terms,
which were not typable before.
Finally, I'd like to correct
some common misunderstandings
about algebraic subtyping.
First union and intersection types,
are not truly first-class.
As we have seen, they simply
result from the printing
of compact type representations.
In fact, they cannot be used
directly by programmers
as is done in languages like
TypeScript or Scala 3,
because in our approach,
there are syntactic restrictions
on the places where unions
and intersections are
allowed to occur.
Supporting first-class
unions and intersections
would be difficult when maintaining
the principle type property.
That is the ability to always
infer a most specific type.
Moreover, it would
make simplification
and other algorithms difficult.
So the expressiveness of
the language studied in the paper
is in fact, similar to
a structurally typed Java,
which includes its F-bounded
quantification features.
Another aspect of
algebraic subtyping,
which I would like to clarify
is its relation with invariance.
As a typical example of invariance
consider the ref data type,
which is the type of
mutable variable references
and which is invariant
in its type argument.
When constraining one ref type
to be a subtype of another,
it is sufficient to constrain
the type arguments, both ways.
However, we can no longer
coalesce the type arguments
of invariant types easily,
since coalescing relies on
the polarity of types to work.
Thankfully, there are several ways
to work around the problem.
We can simply avoid coalescing types
in invariant position,
or we could introduce new notation
to express ranges
overload type arguments
in invariant position.
In conclusion, contrary to
what many people believe,
complete type inference
with subtyping
is not actually that hard.
As long as we restrict
the usage of unions, intersections,
accept a little more verbosity
around variance,
and support recursive types.
Simple Sub is available online
and is less than 500 lines of code,
including parsing, type
inference, simplification,
and pretty printing.
That's it from our presentation.
Thanks for watching.
(AUDIENCE CLAPS)
STEPHANIE: Thank you Lionel.
If you're watching this talk as
live as an ICFP participant,
please look to see if there is
a Q&A session available
with the author in
your time band now.
Our next talk addresses
the challenges
of reasoning about resource usage
at compile time.
This talk will be
presented by Di Wang
and is entitled Liquid
Resource Types.
It is based on work developed
by a team of researchers
at university of
California at San Diego
and at Carnegie Mellon University.
The other authors of
this paper include
Tristan Knoth, Adam
Reynolds, Nadia Polikarpova,
and Jan Hoffman.
DI WANG: Hello, ICFP and
the future viewers of this video.
My name is Di,
a PhD student at
the Carnegie Mellon University.
And today I'm going
to present our work
on liquid resource types,
a technique for
automatically verifying
the resource consumption
of functional programs.
This is a joint work with
Tristan, Adam, Nadia,
from the university of San Diego,
and Jan from Carnegie Mellon.
Resource analysis studies
the consumption of various kinds
of resources in a program,
such as time, memory,
power, et cetera.
One classic scenario
for resource analysis
to find out the time
complexity of algorithms.
Resource analysis can also
be applied to measure
gas usage of smart
contract via blockchains
or detect side-channel
vulnerabilities,
in cryptographic codes.
In this talk, let's
focus on a scenario
about the time complexity
of sorting algorithms.
Consider a situation
where we want to
compare the performance of
Quick sort and Insertion sorts.
These algorithms are
functionally equivalent
and both of them run in
quadratic time in the worst case.
However, if we already know
the input is nearly sorted,
which means that most
of the elements
are in the correct place,
which algorithm will have
a better performance?
In fact, insertion sorts can
achieve linear time complexity
on nearly sorted data.
So instead of
a quadratic upper band,
how can we express
the fine grain complexity
of insertion sorts?
Look at the animation that
might help you recall
how insertion sort works.
It goes through the elements
in the list iteratively,
and tries to move them to
correct places per swaps.
Indeed, we can have
a better estimation
than the quadratic worst case band.
The amount of swaps is proportional
to the number of out of
order pairs in the list.
Now, here comes a challenge that
our work wants to address.
How can a resource analysis
formally describe
and also automatically
verify such complex,
value-dependent resource bounds?
To achieve this, our work follows
a (INAUDIBLE) on liquid types,
which support automatic verification
of functional properties.
For example, a function
returns the absolute value
of its input. Recent augments
of existing liquid type system.
with a simple construct,
types can be annotated
with potentials.
For example, a list where
each element carries
one unit of potential.
Potentials can be used to pay
for the costs in the program.
(INAUDIBLE) function
consumes all the potential
in the list.
The cost bound is linear in
the length of the list.
A major limitation of
recent type system
is that it only
supports linear bounds.
In our work, we propose
liquid resource types,
with the ability to express
a lot more nontrivial
resource bounds.
A key idea is that
the potential can be inductively
specified from the formation
of data structure themselves,
which allows us to express
the time complexity
of insertion sorts.
In general, liquid resource
types provide a mechanism
for expressing
and verifying super-linear,
value-dependent resource bounds.
We formalize and prove
the type soundness
with respect to our cost semantics.
We also implement
an automatic type checker
for liquid resource types.
And we validate on a suite
of challenging examples.
Now I have talked about
motivations for resource analysis
and the main contribution
of our work.
Before diving into
the technical details,
I want to first introduce
two important concepts
that our system is built upon:
Liquid types and
the potential methods.
Liquid types can be seen as
a refinement type system
where types are annotated
with logical predicates
that can constrain the values.
A refined type can be
written as a subset.
B is a base type of the value
and psi is the logical predicate.
For example,
natural numbers can be defined
as a refined type with integers.
The predicate can measure
special variable v,
which reflects the value
of its inhabitants.
In addition, arrow types
can be dependent
and result type can be annotated
with the predicate that
references the arguments.
For example, the type
shown on the slide,
specifies that function
that returns a list
whose length is one plus
the length of the input list.
The potential method
for amortized analysis
is a classic approach
for algorithm analysis,
which can be dated back to 1985.
The highlight idea is to
treat a program execution
as a transition graph
on program states.
And each edge
of the graph
contains the actual
transition cost
between two states. To analyze
the resource consumption,
we devise a potential
function phi
that maps program state
to a non-negative number,
such that the potential
of the state
is enough to pay
for the extra cost
of the current transition
and the potential
of the next state
in this way,
the potential of the initial state
provide an upper bound
or the actual
resource consumption.
A prior work, RESYN,
has combined liquid types
with the potential methods
to automatically
verify resource bonds
of functional programs.
The idea is to annotate
types with potentials.
The potential annotation
and the logical
predicates are in
thre same refinement language.
The difference is that
potentials are numeric
while predicates are Boolean.
The potential annotations
then defines a potential function
or the value of the annotated type.
For example, the type on the slide
describes a natural number,
countering potential
equal to five times of its value.
Potential annotations
can also be conditional.
The type gesture on the slide
describes a list of numbers
where each non-negative element
carries one unit of potential.
With this construct,
RESYN is able to express
and verify value dependent
linear resource bounds.
Take a look at
the functional program on the slide.
The insertion function
as a subroutine of insertion sort
inserting element X
to a proper place
in the list Xs.
We use tick expressions,
marked in blue to
specify a resource metric.
In this program,
we use ticks to count the number
of recursive calls.
RESYN can verify
a value dependent
linear resource bound
showed on this list,
however, they can
not express a type
for insertion sort
because it can only distribute
potential uniformly within a list.
But insertion sorts
request a mechanism
to describe pairs
of elements in the list.
OK, now I have introduced
two important
building blocks of our work
liquid types as the potential method.
Now, we have show
how our work extends prior work,
which two powerful mechanisms
and how to reduce
type verification
to constraint solving
Our first mechanism
is inductive potentials.
Rather than only put
potential to elements
in a data structure.
We can specify potentials
inductively from the formation
of the data structure itself.
The code on the slide
shows that definition of Q list
a variant of list types
with quadratic potentials.
Here, the QCons constructor
maintains that the tail of the list
carries one more unit of potential
in each element than the head
and the tail itself is
again a Q list.
How does such a simple
constant potential annotation
leads to an overall
quadratic potential function?
Well, let's do a calculation,
supposed a list of elements
v1, v2, through Vn
is of type Q list T
While the value of type T
has P units of potential
Then for every element
of BI in your list,
it carries P units of potential
and by definition of QCons.
It also indicates extra potential
equal to the number of elements
to the right of Vi.
Therefore, the
potential function is quadratic
in the length of the list.
More interestingly,
we can use a value
dependent inductive potential
to express fine grained bounds.
The type of ISList
showed on the slide
is almost identical
to the type QList
except that extra potential required by
the ISCons constructor
is not the constant one,
but a conditioner expression
that evaluates to one.
if and only if the element
in the tail is less than
the head element,
In other words,
the potential specified
by ISList is exactly the number
of out of order pairs in the list.
In this way, we formally express
the fine-grained
time complexity of insertion sort
in our type system.
However, inductive potentials
on their own, are difficult to use.
The potential annotations are built
into the data type definitions.
So any slight change
in the analysis
or the resource metric,
requires defining
a new data type.
To address this issues,
We have proposed
a second mechanism,
abstract potentials
in liquid resource types.
We allow data types
to be parameterized
by a numeric potential extractor.
Thus both QList and ISList
can be seen as an extension
of a more general list type.
The list type is parameterized
by numerical function Q,
which takes two
elements as arguments.
Then the Cons constructor
will use the function Q
to define the amount
of extra potential
added to the tail.
What's this abstract type?
QList can be defined
as List with Q
instantiated with
a constant one function
while ISList can be defined as List
with Q instantiated
with the conditional expression
that compares two elements.
Now you may wonder
with this new construct,
how can type checking
your type system
be automated?
Let's use the insertion
sort program as an example,
to illustrate a reduction
from type checking
to constraint solving.
The program uses insert to itertatively
add elements to the right place.
Our system does not infer types.
So assume that
we have a type signature
for recursive functions
insert and sort.
Our type checker
goes through the program,
in a top down manner
and generates
constraints on the fly.
For a sort function
initially, the constraint
only contains
the argument Xs.
After the pattern match
if Xs is an empty list,
then it carries zero potential.
But because it is also free
to create a new empty list,
the nil case is verified.
Otherwise, if Xs is not empty,
then the potential of Xs
is transferred
to the variables,
head and tail.
The component of Cons constructor.
Using the definition of Cons,
we can unfold the type signature
and obtain the potential
stored in head and in tail.
Then there is the rest
of the program.
There are two function calls.
At this point, we need
to split the potential
in the context into two parts.
And each part is used
to pay for the cost
of one function call.
In the top down phase
we don't really know
how to split the potential.
So it creates
symbolic potential,
annotations, and generates
constraints among the symbols.
(INAUDIBLE) for the call to sort,
it's wrapped by a tick expression.
So it needs to use the potential
to pay for the tick.
For simplicity,
let's assume that
the type checker
uses the potential
stored in head to pay for the tick,
stored in the context
for type checking
the call to sort,
the annotation of head
becomes P2 minus one.
Now let's take a look
at the constraints
generated by our type checker.
These constraints (INAUDIBLE)
(INAUDIBLE) P1, P2, Q1, Q2.
First of all, there are constraints
specifying the potential split.
The potential in different parts
should sum up to the original potential
in the context, then for the tick,
we need to ensure
that the potential
is enough to pay
for the cost,
which means that
the potential after the tick
is still non-negative.
Finally the type checker
generates the constraints
for function calls
for the call to sort
which assume that
the type parameter a
is instantiated away
with some unknown potential
annotation S
which is used
to (INAUDIBLE) on potential
to be used by the later
call to insert.
Similarly, we use
the signature of insert
to generate that constraint on S.
Now, after the type checker
generates all its constraints,
it tries to solve
the constraints by finding
proper instances
of P1, P2 and Q1, Q2.
These (INAUDIBLE)
Second-Order Conditional
Linear Arithmetic constraints.
And solving such constraints
automatically is
a well-studied problem.
So in this way,
we built an automatic type checker
for the liquid resource types.
As for theoretical aspects,
we've formalized
and proved the soundness of
liquid resource types,
with respect to a cost-
aware small step
operational semantics.
Our soundness theorem
ensures that a well-typed
closed program
will never run out of resources
if it starts with
the amount of resources
equal to the initial potential
specified by the types.
Details of the theoretical results
can be found in our paper,
and the technical reports.
As I explained
how our type system
formally expresses
and automatically
verifies resource bounds
with liquid resource types.
You may wonder whether the system
is effective in practice or not.
Let's first take a look at some
reusable support resource
annotated data types,
which we'll use to specify
the type signature
for benchmark programs.
The first one for
quadratic potential over lists.
We have already shown
during the presentation.
The second, one for
exponential potential over list,
by doubling the potential
in each element of the tail
in the ECons constructor.
The third one defines
binary trees, to capture
tree height in the potential.
The node constructor
adds Q more units of potential
to the element in the subtree.
So basically an element
at a leaf carries Q times H,
units of potential
where H is the depth of the leaf.
In this way, we can express
our resource bound
like O(n log n).
when the binary tree
is balanced.
The fourth one
also defines binary trees.
(INAUDIBLE)
specific root to
leaf pass on a tree.
This is achieved
by parameterizing
the type
by  logical predicate,
as a guide to a specific leaf.
With these data types
we are able to extract
and verify the time complexities
of 12 challenging
benchmark programs.
As the table shows
the resource bounds
can be polynomial
non-polynomial or value dependent,
our prototype implementation
is reasonably globally efficient,
and (INAUDIBLE)
resource analysis system
can verify all
of our benchmarks,
details of the benchmark programs
can be found in our paper
and the technical reports.
In summary we propose
liquid resource types
as an extension
of liquid types to express
and automatically
verify value-dependent
super-linear resource bounds
of functional programs.
We formally prove
the soundness of our
type system and implement
a prototype type checker
that is shown to be
effective in our experiments.
Our work still has
a bunch of limitations.
For example, our system
only supports
inductively defined potentials.
Does not allow multi-variant
bounds like n times m.
And we don't have
type inference algorithms yet.
These limitations
are interesting research directions.
And we hope
to explore some of them
in the future.
Thanks for your attention.
(APPLAUSE)
STEPHANIE Thank you Dee,
at this point,
if you're watching this stream
live as an ICP participant,
please remember
to look to see if
there's a Q&A session
available in your time band
so that you can discuss
this work with the author.
Our next talk
will be presented
by Glenn Mevel,
who will be presenting
a concurrent separation logic
for multi-core OCaml.
GLEN MEVEL: So welcome to this talk,
I'm Glen Mevel, with
Jacques-Henri Jourdan
and Francois Pottier,
we've been working on
a concurrent separation logic,
Multicore OCaml
What does that mean
our aim is to verify,
fine-grained concurrent programs
in the setting
of the multicore
OCaml memory model,
which is a weak memory model.
In this talk,
I present a concurrence
separation logic
with a notion of views.
So if you (INAUDIBLE)
Multicore Ocaml
as the name suggests
it is an extension
of the OCaml
programming language
with support
for Multicore programming,
it comes with a weak memory model
which has been formalized
in the paper PLDI '18,
and it features
two flavours of locations
which are atomic and non-atomic.
By the way if you're interested
in the garbage collector
of Multicore OCaml,
please have a look
at this other ICFP paper, whose title is
"Retrofitting
Parallelism onto OCaml."
So what is the challenge here?
Essentially, the challenge
is dealing with
the weak memory
and sequential consistency,
traditional concurrent
separation logic
gives you a (INAUDIBLE),
x points to V
which expresses your
unique ownership
of the memory location X
and which also
says which value
we started with.
Then you have the usual
Hoare style resolving rules.
And this assertion
gives you ownership of X
but you may
want to share
this ownership
and goals, right..
To do so, And use assertion,
is to put the assertion,
in an invariant,
intuitively an invariant
holds at all times,
and it contains
contents can be accessed equally
by all threads.
Here, we can put
X points to something
in an invariant
which we denote
by boxing the assertion,
then any thread
that can access X as long as
it presents the invariants.
Now, what breaks
in the weak memory model
is that each thread
now has a different
view of memory.
This notion of view
is crucial, because it means
that some assertions
like the points-to assertion
are only valid
with respect
to the current view of a thread.
We call these kinds
of assertions
subjective assertions.
But on the other hand,
invariants hold
equality for all threads,
so they can only contain
objective assertions
where by objective
we mean non-subjective.
Then the challenge
is to give a program logic,
which felt simple
and natural enough
that at the same time
is able to deal
with subjectivity
on the laws
subject assertions
to be shared, between threads.
I just spoke about the view
of a thread on how it is
central to the challenge
of weak memory,
but I haven't defined
this concept yet.
So let me do that now,
because of weak memory
each thread only know
the subset of all writes
that have happened
to the shared memory.
This affects how the threads
how the thread reads
or writes the memory,
for example
once it has learned
about the writes,
it cannot read
from earlier writes anymore.
This is an example
of what a weak
memory model would say U,
and this subset of write events,
we will call it a view,
so the view of a thread
of the view of a thread
is the set of
of the write events
it knows about.
Now, we want to manipulate
these views from logic.
For that, we have new
kinds of assertions.
The first new kind
of assertions is
this upper view where
U is a view,
we pronounce it
as we have seen U,
but it means that
the current thread
knows all writes
and U is an assertion
about the current view
of the thread.
And the second
new session is P at U,
were P
in anassertion,
and U is a view
it means that P holds in the eyes
of any thread
which has seen U.
For example, let's say
that P relies
on knowing
a given write event.
Then it requires the current view
to contain that write event.
(INAUDIBLE) subjective.
But instead we're going to
(INAUDIBLE)
the current view is,
if it contains
that write event,
then P holds.
And I say these, we do not
depend anymore on the current view.
So saying this is objective,
even though P
maybe subjective.
And that's what
the @U means when
U contains the given write events.
So we can make
a subjective assertions objective
by specifying the view
at which we see it.
On the way
U is interesting
because these new
assertions, complementary,
or precisely in a logic
an assertion P
is equivalent
to an objective,
assertion, any assertion
is equivalent
to an objective assertion
of the form P at U
and a assertion of the form,
upper U,
for some view U.
This shows in particular
that your assertions
of the form upper U.
Capture all the
subjectivity of the,
all the subjectivity
of the weak memory.
And this decomposition, will allow us
to share subjective assertions,
but in Threads, by using
a different mechanism for each part.
The first part P@U,
is objective
so it can be shared by an invariant,
via an invariant,
just as in usual
concurrent separation logic.
Regarding the second parts,
sharing upper U,
means exchanging information
about write events into threads.
So in other words,
it means synchronising.
So we will rely on some form
of thread synchronisation,
that is provided by the memory model.
That was the main idea of this talk.
Now I show you what is
in our programme logic,
to reason about programmes and memory,
and I'll start with the simplest thing,
which are atomic locations.
For atomic locations,
we have a neutral looking
points-to assertion,
atomic x points to v,
which means that (INAUDIBLE)
atomic location x,
and x stores the value v.
We are able to say such a thing,
because atomic locations behave
in a sequentially consistent way.
At any given time,
all threads see the same value for x.
In particular,
this assertion is subjective,
they should come as no surprise,
that atomic x's are by the usual,
Hoare triples both reads and writes.
Where things become interesting,
is for non-atomic locations.
The non-atomic locations of particular
OCaml have relaxed behaviour.
In a logic we still have
an assertion x points to v,
with its meaning differ slightly.
It still asserts the (INAUDIBLE) of x,
but instead of saying that,
the value of x is v,
it says that we have seen
the (INAUDIBLE) to x,
and this write bears the value v.
And this is the typical
subjective assertion.
There is no such a thing as
the global value of x,
because different threads
do not necessarily know
about the same writes to x.
What is really nice with
this points to assertion ,
is that it also objeys the standard rules.
So we have a simple looking assertion,
that behaves in a natural way,
and the price for it
is that the assertion,
hides more (INAUDIBLE) it is subjective.
So we cannot share it,
only by using an invariant.
So let's see how we can share it none
the less and for that,
let's consider the typical lock pattern,
which is called a spin lock.
Let's say we have several threads,
that want to access the same resource,
such as a single monotone location.
Then we can use an atomic
flag to guard a resource,
when the flag is true,
the resource is taken,
and if you want to acquire it,
you need to wait for
it to become available.
Now from a logical point of view,
the lock can be seen as
guarding an assertion P,
which means subjective,
for example,
it may be another
points to assertion,
as we've seen before.
The first thread has P,
before releasing the lock.
The second thread will get P
after it has acquired the lock.
So we want P to be transferred,
from the first thread to the second one.
To see how that works,
let's consider,
I'll need a comprehensive
operation that exists,
because that's when the transfer happens.
As we've seen we decompose
P to an objective part,
and a subjective part,
so that we can transfer each part.
The first part P@U is objective.
So it can be transferred
using an invariant as before.
So we get rid of it.
So now we are down to the problem
of transferring up U assertion.
As I said before,
we need some form of
synchronisation on here.
What OCaml gives us,
is a happens-before relationship,
from the realeasing write
to the acquired read.
So instead of adding
new primitives to the language,
multicore OCaml made the choice
of performing release-aquire
synchronization on atomic access.
And we need to reflect
this in our programme logic,
and we do so,
by extending the atomic
points to predicate.
So recall that atomic points to v,
means that x stores the value of v.
We know what's done this assertion.
So that atomic locations stores the pair
of the value and a view,
so accesses still behave the same,
with respect to the view value,
but they also perform a
release acquire synchronisation
on the view.
So when writing,
we push into the shared location,
any information we have in the local view.
So that's a release write.
And conversely,
when reading we pull into a local view,
any information stored
in a shared location.
So that's an acquire read.
And with this in mind,
let's come back to our spin lock.
As we have seen before,
the spin lock has two operations,
release and acquire,
in the interface (INAUDIBLE) assertion P,
we give the spin lock a specification,
which holds under some invariant,
and now,
to put this specification in
the usual separation logic,
with sequential consistency,
we state an invariant like this.
We are either locked or unlocked,
in the latter case
the invariant itself holds the assertion P.
Now in our programme
logic with weak memory,
P is subjective,
but everything in the
ivariant has to be objective.
So the ivariant we
state instead is that one.
In fact,
it is the same as in your
old separation logic,
but we add views.
To remain objective,
we make it explicit,
at which view we have P,
and we say that if it is the same view,
as is stored in our case.
In other words,
P holds in the eyes of whoever,
last released the lock.
So that P@U in the invariants,
obviously allows to transfer,
the objective part of P,
where the atomic location itself,
allows to transfer the
subjective part of P.
So that was the proof of the spin lock.
And in addition to this example,
we did more case studies with
different kinds of locks.
Like algorithms for mutual exclusion,
and in all of these examples,
we have been experiencing the same pattern
of sprinkling views over our invariants.
So our general method
for proving correctness,
of a concurrent data structure,
is to start by reasoning
as if we had a sequentially
consistent model,
expressing the invariant in the usual
concurrent sequential logic.
Then identifying where
synchronisation happens,
and make it explicit by adding views.
To sum up I have presented
a programme logic,
for OCaml,
based on isolating
subjectivity into views.
I argued that this logic enables concise
and natural reasoning of
how threads synchronise.
There is more in the paper,
namely how the logic is realised,
by building on top of a lower-level logic.
And we also have more case studies.
This entire work is mechanised
in the Coq proof assistant,
using the Iris logic framework.
So we have a verified proof of soundness,
and an entire language with
which we can write programmes
and prove them correct using
Hoare logic.
And in the future,
we would like to verify
even more data structures.
Thus so we would like to
investigate data races,
because data races are currently
not supported in logic.
Even though the underlying memory model,
gives a few guarantees about them.
Thank you for your attention.
And if you have seen on previous slides,
you hold the right to
ask questions though.
(clapping)
STEPHANIE: Thank you Glenn.
If you are watching this talk live,
as an ICFP participant,
please look to see if there
is a Q&A session available,
so that you may discuss this work
with the authors of this paper.
The fourth talk of this session,
is entitled Composing and
Decomposing Op-Based CRDTs
with Semidirect Products.
This paper has been
written by Matthew Weidner,
Christopher Meiklejohn, Heather Miller,
all from Carnegie Mellon University.
Matthew will be presenting the talk.
MATTHEW WEIDNER: Hello, I'm Matthew.
And I'm going to be
talking about our paper,
Composing and Decomposing Op-Based
CRDTs
with Semidirect Products.
And this was worked with Heather Miller,
and Christopher Meiklejohn.
So you'll start off,
let's say you're building a web app,
where you have some kind of storage state,
that can be shared
between different users.
So this is basically any website nowadays,
and some specific examples I have in mind
are things like Slack or Facebook groups,
maybe a conference management website.
So the usual way you'd build this,
is you have a server.
And when a client wants
to change their state,
they send a message to the server.
The server responds,
and then the client updates
their own view of the state.
Okay.
But we know that actually the server
is probably not a single machine,
but a bunch of machines
working together in the cloud
using message passing.
Now a lot of work has gone
into making these systems efficient
and easier to use,
but it still can get pretty complicated.
It's easy to introduce subtle bugs,
and you need a lot of
specialised knowledge
to write the server-side code.
So CRDTs is provide an alternative way
to build applications
that use shared state.
CRDTs stand for Conflict-free
Replicated Data Types.
And basically they're
like ordinary datatypes,
except that they're shared
between a group of users,
and they intelligently sync up
with each other in the background.
So as an example of how you might use this
on the client side,
you can use this snippet
from the Legion CRDT library.
So the first two lines here
set up the group state basically,
and connect to each other.
And then after that,
if you want to have a shared set,
like maybe a shopping list,
all you do is instead of
making an ordinary set,
you make a legion set,
and then you can just use this
like an ordinary data type.
So for instance,
you're can say shopping.addmilk
to add milk to the set.
And what this will do under the hood
is it updates to some
local state immediately.
And it also loosely
broadcasts the operation
to other users and replicas,
who will then apply the operation
to their own copy of the state.
And CRDTs are neat
because they're programming languages
way of solving a systems problem
of how to build these
applications with shared state.
And in particular,
the way you design them is
principled and mathematical.
So at least in theory,
it should be hard to introduce
bugs when you use it.
So some pros.
You have this simple
client-side programming model,
like I described,
where you basically just switch out your
ordinary data types for CRDTs.
And then they run on
top of a generic server.
They have minimal latency.
They work offline,
can support end-to-end encryption.
Some cons is that they're targeted
for data that's shared
in small groups only,
it's because everyone
has to share the state
with each other and sync up.
So you don't want the group to be too big.
Also they have automatic
conflict resolution,
but this algorithm will
make some specific choices,
which won't be appropriate for every app.
They're not for data that needs locking.
But the biggest thing
that I want to talk about,
is the fact that you have to design
the conflict resolution
algorithm for each data type.
Which is a difficult and ad hoc process.
So in practise,
what this means is that you're restricted
to using a few common data types
with restricted interfaces.
Basically whatever CRDT researchers
have figured out within the past 10 years.
In this work,
we present a compositional
design technique
for op-based CRDTs,
which we call a semidirect product.
It is supposed to address the difficulty
of designing CRDTs.
What it lets you do,
is you take two inputs CRDTs,
here's C1 and C2,
oh and they have to operate
on the same state type.
You take a bit of extra information
in the form of this function
that we call the action.
And then what you get out,
is this CRDT that supports the operations
of both of your inputs CRDTs,
and also resolves conflicts
between them in a natural way.
You can use this for a
composition of CRDTs directly.
This is where you take two existing CRDTs
and you combine them to get a CRDT
with both of the operations.
In practise usually,
you can use this to add
operations to an existing CRDT.
So for instance,
we show how to take an
integer counter CRDT
and add multiplication operations.
or take a list CRDT
add a reverse operation,
or take a dictionary CRDT
that maps keys to values
and add a functional mapping operation,
which applies some operation
to every value in the dictionary.
You can also use our semidirect
product for decomposition,
by which I mean taking
the existing CRDT design,
and exhibiting it as a semidirect product,
of two simpler CRDTs.
Often, commutative data types,
just sort of the simplest type of CRDTs.
So for instance,
if you have a set CRDT,
we show how to decompose it
into two simpler commutative data types.
One that only has add operations,
and one the only has removes.
Likewise with some generic
resettable CRDT designs,
we decompose them into the non-resettable,
and the resettable parts.
So to explain our construction,
I first want to give
a bit more background,
on how CRDTs work.
So recall our system model,
when one user updates the state,
they update their local state immediately,
and also broadcast the operation
to other users in the background.
So the problem can come if you
have conflicting operations,
for instance,
let's say Alice and Bob share an integer,
and Alice sets the value to three,
while at the same time Bob
sets the value to five.
So then later they'll
sync up with each other,
and they see that they have a conflict.
So they have to decide what to do,
in order to get the same answer.
So one main conflict resolution technique,
that's used in CRDT design,
is to make operations commute.
So for instance,
in Alice and Bob example,
let's say that they're
actually counting something,
like the number of clicks on an ad.
In that case, when Alice
sets the value to three,
what she actually wants to do
is add three to the current value.
Likewise when Bob sets the value to five,
he actually wants to add five.
But these addition operations
will both get answered eight
once they exchange operations.
So that's fine.
We avoided the conflict.
You can also use commutatively
to design a clever sequence types
that don't have conflicts.
Another thing you can do is
to reason about causality.
So I'll go into more detail
about what I mean by
causality on the next slide.
But a simple example,
is if Alice and Bob share a shopping list,
say Alice adds milk to the shopping list,
later Bob sees this operation,
but he's already bought milk at the store.
So he's going to remove
milk from the shopping list.
And what a CRDT will do,
is it'll send out a message
to the other users saying,
remove milk from the shopping list,
but only after applying Alice's operation.
So we notice that anyone else will apply,
add then milk, in that order.
So they'll end up in the state
where they don't have
milk on the shopping list.
Thus everyone will end
up in the same state,
there's no conflict anymore.
So in general,
when I say reasoning about causality,
I mean,
reasoning about the causal
order on operations.
This is the partial order defined
according to three rules,
which I'll illustrate using this diagram.
So here time goes to the right,
and I add more arrows to
indicate message sending.
Okay.
So the first rule is that,
if some user like Alice sends
two operations in a row,
and the first operation is
less than the second one,
we have a partial order,
for instance here adding milk
is less than adding bread.
The second rule is that if say Alice.
The message,
Bob receives it,
indicated by the first
diagonal orange arrow.
And then, Bob sends
his own operation,
like "Remove milk," here.
Then, the first one
is less than the second one.
So, here, "Add milk" is
less than "Remove milk,"
in the causal order.
And the third rule is transitivity.
So, by what I just said,
"Add milk" is less
than "Remove milk,"
and by the first rule, again,
"Remove milk" is less
than "Add eggs."
So then, we detect  that, also,
"Add milk" is less than "Add eggs."
A transitivity. OK?
So, note that this
is a partial order,
and it's possible to have
a situation like this,
where these two "Add
milk" operations
are neither less than, nor
greater than each other.
In this case, we say that
they're concurrent.
And the good thing about causality
is that CRDTs can query
the causal order.
Basically, you can attach
metadata to operations,
when you send them over the network,
so that everyone agrees on
what the causal order is.
And then, this lets
you make definitions,
like, for a set CRDT,
you could say X is in the set,
if there is an add x operation
that is not less than
any remove X operation. OK?
Because this will respect
the reasoning about causality,
there's no possibility of conflict.
Even if people get operations
in different orders,
they'll come with the same result.
And you can see, in
the example I have here,
milk is going to stay
on the shopping list,
according to this rule,
because Charlie's
"Add milk" operation
is not constantly less than
any "Remove milk" operation. OK.
So, again, here are
the conflict resolution techniques
for building CRDTs:
commutativity
and reasoning about causality.
There's- then, what
direct product does
is it provides a uniform
and reasonable way
of reasoning about causality,
so that CRDT designers
don't have to do it from
scratch, each time.
This is a good rule for
coming up with rules,
like this rule that I've
specified here, for a set,
and it's also good for
implementing them.
So, if you just look
at this definition,
it's not entirely clear
how you would implement
this efficiently,
without just looping over
the full history of operations,
every time you get a new one. OK?
So, what our semi-direct
product enables
is a new CRDT-designed workflow.
So, starting from
an ordinary data type
that you want to turn into a CRDT,
you first design
commutative data types,
for simple subsets of operations,
and then, you glue
together those subsets,
the semi-direct products,
and it'll handle conflicts
between the operations
that don't commute
in the natural way.
In our experience,
this design workflow
works for most existing CRDT design,
for existing CRDT types,
plus novel ones.
OK. Now, for the rest of the talk,
I want to give an example
of how our semi-direct
product works,
particularly, a simple example.
We're going to just start with
two commutative data types,
an integer register that
has add operations,
and an integer register that
has multiplication operations.
And we went to compose them
into an integer register
that supports both kinds
of operations at once. OK?
So, an example of something
you can do with this data type
is, you start in state one,
multiply by three, and add one.
But, of course, the tricky
part is that multiple users
might be making these
operations concurrently,
and we have to resolve
conflict between them.
So, add operations are
alone, are easy.
They already commute,
so there's no conflicts.
Similarly, for
multiplication operations,
but they conflict with each other.
For instance, if Dave
and Mary are sharing a counter,
and then, Dave says to
multiply his state by three,
while concurrently- so,
without coordination,
Mary says to add one to her state.
Then, after they
exchanged these messages,
if we just apply them literally,
they'll end up different States.
Mary's going to be six
and David's going to get four.
So, this is a conflict. OK.
So now to resolve this conflict,
you're going to make the choice that,
in the face of a conflict,
add should go before mult.
So basically here,
Mary is in the right
and Dave is in the wrong.
We want to get the answer six.
And our observation is
that to make this happen,
if you're like Dave here,
and you get the add and
the mult in the wrong order,
you can fix it up by
acting on the addition
with the multiplication. OK.
So here, what we say is when Dave
receives Mary's add one message,
instead of applying it literally,
he's going to act on it
with this multiply by three message
and add three instead,
'cause then he gets in
the state six as well,
and we've solved the conflict.
And this works by
the Distributive Law
of multiplication over addition. OK.
So more generally, we have
a more complicated situation
like this one,
we make the rule that when
you receive an add operation,
before applying it,
you first act on it
by all concurrent
multiplication operations
that you've already received. OK.
So in this example,
Dave has multiplied his state
by two, and then added one,
while concurrently,
so without coordination,
Mary multiplied by three
and then added four. OK.
And now they sync up.
So, they exchange these operations.
So Dave gets the multiply by
three operation for Mary.
We'll just apply that literally
And then, when he gets
this add four operation,
he first looks in
his history and sees that
he's already applied
the multiply by two operation
that is concurrent to the add four.
He's going to use that
as a transformation
and add two times four
instead to get 17.
Likewise, Mary receives the multiply
by two operation from Dave.
She applies it literally.
And then, when she receives
the add one operation,
she's going to transform it
by her mult three operation
because that's
the concurrent message
that she's already applied.
So she adds three instead of one,
And then, they both
end up in stage 17.
So the fact that they both
end up in the same state,
was again, just the consequences
of distributivity.
Well, I know a way of
stating this rule
is that if you receive an add
N message from another user,
then you turn it into
add of N one times N K,
et cetera, times M,
or mult N long through mult N K,
or all the multiply operations
that you've previously received
that are concurrent
to the one you've just received, OK?
And this rule is
the same general rule
that we use in the full
semiproduct construction.
Basically, you give some action,
which says, "If
I receive one operation
"after a concurrent
operation of another one,
"I'm going to act on it
with this action."
And this works in general,
subject to algebraic
constraints on the input CUDT
and on the action.
OK, so that's all I wanted to
say about our constructions.
Just a quick recap.
CRDTs are a neat
programming languages,
way of building systems that act
on a shared state, like web apps.
The way you use them is that
program will just replaced
ordinary data types
with CRDT versions
on the client side,
then server is just
a messaging server.
You want more
information about these,
I encourage you to check
out the website, CRDT.tech,
which has a collection
of nice resources.
So our work present
the semidirect product,
which is a compositional
design technique for CRDTs.
These resove conflicts between operations by
reasoning about causality,
in a uniform way,
so that you don't have to.
And it enables a new
CRDT design workflow,
where you start with a data type
that you want to replicate,
you design communicative data types,
for subsets of operations,
and then you group these together
with semidirect products.
OK, that's all I have to say,
so thanks for watching,
and I hope there'll
be some questions.
(APPLAUSE)
STEPHANIE: Thank you, Matthew.
If you are watching this talk live,
as an ICFP participant,
please remember to
join the Q&A session,
if it is available
in your time zone.
Our next talk is a new approach to
impredicative polymorphism,
in the Glasgow Haskell Compiler.
This work has been developed by
Alejandro Serrano, Jurean Hawk,
Simon Payton-Jones,
and Dimitrios Vitinyadas.
Alejandro Serrano will be
giving the presentation.
ALEJANDRO SERRANO: Hi.
I'm Alejandro.
I'm going to talk to you about
a bit how we brought
impredicativity into GHC.
But, first of all, what
is impredicativity?
Take a function like map.
It has two type arguments,
and it takes a function, a list,
and returns a list.
Because, this function
is polymorphic,
we can use map with
a wide range of types,
we can use map even,
and then get a function
from list of ints
to list of bools,
or we can have map, of greater than,
and then we have a list of
ints to a list of functions.
But, if now we want to use map
with this function, which takes
an argument which itself
has a polymorphic type,
in many cases we cannot
really use this.
Polymorphic types, those
types headed with for all,
are not first-class in
many programming languages.
Impredicativity is
exactly the feature
that allows you to
instantiate a type variable,
like A or B in map,
with a polymorphic type.
A type which has a for all in front.
System F, which is
the basis for GHC Core,
is itself impredicative.
You can always instantiate
with a for all type.
But, you have to be very
explicit about it.
You need to annotate.
In fact, in System F,
you need to annotate
every time you instantiate
with a type application,
like I am doing here
with at for all A A to A,
and you also have to annotate
every time you generalize,
every time you need to
have a for all in a type,
with a big lambda,
like I am doing here,
in the big lambda for
the first argument.
So the problem actually
is not impredicativity,
but impredicative inference.
We want to write
something like here,
where we cons,
an identity function to id,
which is itself a list
of for all A A to As,
and we want the inference
and to be able to add
anything we need.
But there are several questions.
First of all, how do we
instantiate the cones?
Hindley-Damas-Milner
for example,
which is one of the best known
inference algorithms,
that's not allowed polymorphic
instantiation at all.
The second question is how
do we choose to generalize?
How do we know that we have
to have a big Lambda
at the point we need it
and not somewhere else?
There's been a lot of work about
impredicative inference.
There are so many related work.
Here I want to present Quick
Look which is a new idea
in which what we do is
we introduce a new
Quick Look phase through
an instantiation which discovers
impredicative activity
as much as possible.
And then there is a type checking
just remains as it was.
Let me show you an example.
For example, I have here cons ID
where instead of using ID directly,
I'm putting this into
a local binding,
but here you can see all the types.
If you do inference with
Hindley-Damas-Milner,
what will happen is
that you instantiate
the type of cons
and you're introducing cons
applied to one type
variable, you don't know
I'm going to call it
alpha here,
and then you have
the argument ID and ISs.
The type of the arguments are then
alpha and list of alphas.
The question now is what
is alpha of course,
and if you have a declarative spec,
maybe you guess the instantiation,
or if you have a type
inference engine
that inference will do unification
and try to figure this
out, but the thing is
no instantiation without
for all type works,
so this example is prohibited
by Hindley-Damas-Milner.
How does it work with Quick Look?
Well you start with the same step,
you instantiate the type of cons,
and at this point you have
a quick look at the arguments.
You try to get as many
information about
the impredicativity
you need by looking
at having a peek at the arguments.
In this case we're
going to learn nothing
from the first argument IDs,
and from the second arguments
we're going to learn
that alpha has to be
exactly for all A to A.
At this point, what we
know is that
the type of these arguments are
not just any alpha,
they are exactly for all Aa to A
and list of for all Aa to A.
And there is nothing else to guess
and type checking can succeed.
Now I've said that we
learn nothing from ID,
but from IDs we learn
that alpha must be
for all A A to A, so you
might be wondering
what's difference between
these two arguments?
Let me try to explain this.
Here are the types we are
push, the types that went
from the instantiation,
and the types that are obtained
from looking at
the type of the variables.
In the case of ID,
the type which is push
is this single type
variable alpha
we get from
the variable is for all A A to A
and from IDs it's
the same,
but everything
is wrapped in a list construct.
So actually in the case of IDs
we have only one possibility.
In order for the list of alpha
and the list of for all
A A to B to be equal,
just alpha has to be
for all A, A to A.
Now for the second case, we
actually have two possibilities.
It could be that alpha
is for all A, A to A,
but we have another option.
At this point, we could instantiate,
so the for all A, A to
A becomes beta to beta,
and then we make alpha
equal to this beta to beta.
The difference here is that
alpha in the second case
is what we call guarded,
which means it appears
under a type construct.
And the key idea is that
the instantiation relation
becomes simple equality
when you have
a type constructor on top.
So in the second case, you
have nothing to decide.
There is only one
choice, so you take it.
If you have a single type
variable lying around,
like in a type of IDs, you
don't know what to do,
so we just say, "Well, at this
point we learn nothing."
And actually, it can be the case
that quick look gets
us no information.
That's, for example, cons
ID with an empty list.
In this list, we will
instantiate the type of cons,
have a quick look at the arguments,
and we will learn nothing from ID,
and we will learn nothing
from the empty list,
so we need to fall back to
monomorphic instantiation.
And the result will be
that the inferred type
is the most useful
list of tau to tau,
where these taus are
monomorphic types.
We can also take some other
information into account.
Imagine, for example, we
have this go to single ID.
Well, we have a pretty similar
story with the arguments.
The type of ID is going to be
alpha when we push it,
and then we have
a for all A, A to A.
So we have two choices here, again:
we can make alpha equal
to for all A, A to A,
or we could instantiate.
So quick look gives you
no information here.
But if we have a better look,
we can also take into consideration
the type of the result,
and in that case, we
can play the same trick
as we did for
the cons of ID with IDs.
The type we get pushed
is for all A, A to A,
that's from the annotation,
and the type we get from
the instantiation is list of alpha.
So we can make alpha equal
to for all A, A to A.
So by knowing
the special result type,
we can get even more
impredicative information,
and this will actually inform us
to get a bidirectional type system
instead of a single-directional one,
as Hindley-Milner is, for example.
But the question is when
to stop with looking.
Up to now, we've only
dealt with variables.
So everything was one application,
and this application had arguments,
but those arguments
were all variables.
We can actually go deeper
and inspect nested applications,
and if you think, for example,
into this goal cons
ID to cons ID IDs,
in order for the top-most cons
to be correctly instantiated,
you need to go up to
the IDs so that you learn that,
well, this should
have a type of list
of for all A, A to A, and this
will inform both constants.
So you gain something by
inspecting nested applications.
But we don't know more.
We really want to keep this simple.
We don't want to go
into environmental changes.
So we don't inspect Lambdas.
We don't inspect
let's because this introduce
new things into the environment.
And we don't try
to inspect them
with multiple branches,
like ifs or pattern matching
because it's (INAUDIBLE)
that we need to not only
unify things in a simple way
we also need
to consider the case
in which these two branches
don't have a similar type.
So we just really want
to keep it simple.
And we want, we found that
nested applications
seems to be a sweet spot.
So you really gain
a lot of information
by looking at nested applications
and for the rest
of the cases you,
well, you often get
information pushed
by bidirectional
typing mechanisms.
So this is the sweet spot.
So it will say,
so our goal actually
has always been
to have a predictable
inference for which
I mean a simple mental
model that the
developer can have.
One thing will succeed.
And also when things
break where the annotations
should be placed,
we also want obvious
programs to be typable
without annotations.
And of course, what obvious are,
is objective in the paper.
We have a big list of example,
would we need,
should we think
we should be typeable
without annotations.
And many of the examples
I've shown here
are also typeable
without annotations
so we really want to push
for getting as much
impredicatively
information as we can,
so that developers don't have
to annotate all the time.
The other goal we have
is to be a conservative extension
of existing features.
So we want this thing
to be compatible
with type classes,
type families, everything
which is already in GHC
and also to be localized
in specification and
implementation.
Because as I was saying,
we want to implement
this in GHC without
massive changes.
So let me talk a bit more
about the fact that
quick look is very localized.
And as I said,
this only affects instantiation.
The rest of the type
check-in has no changes.
So we've integrated
this into GHC,
which has type classes,
type families, data type promotion,
levity polymorphism,
you name it.
And we were able
to implement this
and there is a merge request
for doing so.
And we only had to add
450 lines out of roughly
90,000 lines which make up
the type checker in GHC.
So I think we succeeded
in making thing,
really localized.
Of course, I encourage
you to read the paper.
There is more there
you have the full formalization.
And actually we think
it's the first time
that bidirectional
type inference and constraint
have been written
down in a paper.
This is what was inside GHC,
but there was no nothing written
about how you integrate
all of this together.
And on top of that,
we built QuickLook
impredicativity.
Of course we have,
we talk about
metatheoretical properties.
Also we talk about
how we integrate quick look
with visible type application.
And the reason is that when,
when quick look fails,
the easiest way to override
this is a way to tell
the compiler
what this instantiation
should be is to use
visible type application.
So we think it's really
important that does
these two things
play together.
Well, we also talk
a bit about how qualified type
and GADTs is integrated
with quick look
and also lots of related work,
because as I shown
at the beginning,
a lot of people
have been struggling
with this problem
and trying to solve it
for a long time.
In summary, quck look
impredicativity
is a simple approach
to impredicative inference
which tries to be predictable,
but yet type
as many obvious program
as possible without annotation.
And it's also
a conservative extension
to what it's already there
and very localized
in the specification
and implementation.
That's what the whole,
I love to hear you
any new ideas,
any questions in the,
in the ICFP channel for this,
and thanks for watching
(APPLAUSE)
STEPHANIE: Thank you Alejandro.
If you are watching
this talk live,
please don't forget
about the Q & A session
that may be available
in your time now.
We will now pause here
to sync up with
the talk schedule.
Our next talk presents
a general mechanism
and type system design
inspired by modal logic.
This work is called
'A unified view
of modalities
in type systems',
and it is a paper
by Andreas Abel
and Jean-Phillipe Bernardy,
both from Gothenburg.
Jean-Phillipe Bernardy
will be giving the talk.
JEAN-PHILLIPE BERNARDY: Hello
and welcome to
A unified view of Modalities
in type systems.
My name is Jean-Phillipe Bernardy
and this is joint work
with Andreas Abel.
Modalities are qualifiers,
that modify types or propositions.
For example, in the sentence,
it may rain today.
The rain today
proposition is qualified
with the possibility modality.
Another possible example
is the qualification of propositions
by the agent who believe it
as in John thinks
that it rains today
in programming languages,
it can be useful
to qualify your type,
but in amount in presenting,
how much is available.
For example 5.543mm of rain.
Another useful kind of qualifier
is whether information
is public or secret
in this work.
I will go this to describe
the system which unifies
all such instances
of modalities.
We also want the system
to have a useful meta theory,
which all instances
can inherit.
Our work is set
in the framework
of the system F
also known as
the Polymorphic Lambda Calculus.
I am going to assume
familiarity with it.
Also, I assume
you know that
they are isomorphic.
If you watch the video offline,
feel free to pause,
and we decide
that you won't face,
or we can consult the paper
and come back later here,
as suggested
by the examples
that I've shown above.
We add a new type form
of P, which I will just read
out PA in the future.
This means A
qualifying by modality P.
To support modal types.
The key idea is to
annotate every type variable
or every variable
with a modality
in addition to its type. Again.
To support modal types
the key idea is to annotate
every variable
with the modality
in addition to its type.
Formally what we do
is to change the judgment.
So that includes
this little gamma here.
It is a map
from variable names to modalities
and important thing
to note is that
the reason we have
type A in the judgment
has a unit in gamma.
This unit modality
will be interpreted differently
depending on the application.
But I can only say that
it acts as a default
to produce a modality, say P(A),
here we need to multiply
the modality context by P
that is we multiply every modality
in the context by P.
In the same vein.
If we want the product
of A and B, then we
build the sum of their
respective modality contexts.
To see how this plays out
let us first look
at the fragment of system F,
without modalities.
Then we can see
how modality annotations
get added.
Let's look first
at the variable
rule, what it says
is that a is used exactly once.
And so A is annotated
with a unit modality
in the context also
that the rest of the context
is not used at all.
And so it is annotated
with the zero modality
for consistency,
We also annotate domain
of the arrow type
with the modality.
You can see how this
plays out in the ABS
and APP rules
abstruction applications.
In particular, in the application rule
to be able to fit qA
to the function.
We need q times delta.
In passing we know quickly
that the application
does nothing useful
with the modality context.
Let's now look
at the introduction
and elimination rules
for qualified types.
Introduction rule works
as we said before,
namely, we multiplied
the context by P.
Elimination rule
is a bit more involved.
Note first that we assume
that little gamma
produces P(A).
Now we want to use this A
to put to produce
C in continuation.
We could think that
we'd have PA
in the context
of the continuation,
but instead we are allowed
to multiply by the annotation of an arbitrary Q.
This is because
to produce 1C,
unit C,
we may need another modality.
Exactly P for A,
and thus this version
gives more flexibility
to the programmer.
On top of this, we also have
an order of modalities
and it is generated
by this lattice.
This order drives
the weakening rule
as shown here.
We can also see the converse,
and, this is
a conversion rule from P to Q.
If P is less than Q.
The exact structure
of modalities is
as shown here.
Pause the video, or you can
check out the paper.
But the interesting bit
is the last line,
namely, that addition
distribute over meet,
This property also implies
addition is monotonous.
We can instantiate
the structure to various
various special cases
and obtain several
useful systems in this way.
First, we can do
zero and one,
as you'd expect,
we just need to add
the modality Omega to support
unrestricted usage
That's the bang
modality in linear (INAUDIBLE) .
The rest of the structure
is at you expect.
And Omega is acting
as a catch-all value.
A useful generalization
of linear types is the system
which tracks
the exact number of times
that a variable is used.
However, one must
allow for sets
of possible usages.
We implemented meet, et cetera.
The rest of the structure
falls out from this choice.
An interesting property
of all such models,
Modal systems
is that zero annotated parameter
is guaranteed not to be used
this is capture by
the irrelevance theorem,
which is stated
as shown here
and proven in the paper,
the lattice, which as you'll recall,
corresponds to the order
of modalities can be used
for various purposes.
It can be used
for security purposes,
with more secret levels
towards the top.
It can be used to represent
the necessity modalities
with more necessary
propositions towards
the bottom.
It can represent
levels of beliefs.
More credulous agents
are at the top.
We can represent
computational relevance
with more relevant types
toward the bottom.
Remember that convertibility
is from bottom to top.
And so at the meet of P and Q
all data which is available
for either P or Q is
also available there.
We can now take
a moment to ponder
what happens when one
does not care about quantities.
And so modalities
are only used to
represent levels in areas
such as shown previously
in this case,
the meet becomes
the addition and the join
becomes multiplication.
Additionally, zero
is also the top of the lattice.
The consequence is that
to produce zero A
or really top A,
the modality context
can be ignored.
And so we can use all variables,
even those
that are available
with modality zero, in data.
It has the application
where precise quantities
are tracked,
in sensitivity analysis,
which you can read
about in the paper.
Let's now turn
to the metatheory.
We consider our first
operational semantics,
whose cornerstone
is the substitution Lemma,
the proof follows
the issue of structure.
We have additionally
to express how modalities
are transformed by substitution.
It turns out that the modality
transformation applied by
your substitution here, Sigma
is a linear operator, here.
So, the proof
is straightforward,
but it is interesting
to note that the requirements,
this is a well-formed modality
is correspond exactly
to the modality structure,
which we have shown previously.
We also have a modality
preserving abstract machine.
This is a call by name machine
where every state is well typed
and well-qualified.
The main point
of showing this machine
is to show that
dynamic execution steps
will never over-consume
under consume,
see private information,
et cetera.
So the modalities annotations
can be realized
at run time time as such.
Finally, we have
a relation now
Kripke case style semantics.
We interpret types by relations
and these relations
are indexed by worlds.
The main novelty here
is that we can interpret
the PA type by
a notion of division
or more precisely
a galois connection.
For quantitative systems
w is a multiset
of resources to consume.
P is then interpreted
as a natural number
and to interpret P(A) at a world w,
we interpret A
at a world w divided by P.
For non quantitative systems,
w is a set of capabilities.
Types are indistinguishable
if the associated capability
is not in w.
We can take
advantage of the fact
that every modality
can be represented
by a set of capabilities.
So to interpret P(A) at w
we interpret A at the world,
which is the difference
of the sets w and P
combining the two views
is somewhat curious,
but it is shown in the paper.
A perhaps controversial choice
is that we have a constraint
on which modalities...
can take to be scrutinized
by a case expression.
We demand that they must
be convertible
to the unit modality.
This constraint is
necessary for irrelevance.
Otherwise we will be able to see
if we are on the left
or on the right
of the sum
for every modality, and then
everything becomes observable
at every level,
even zero,
but the operational semantics
do not in fact rely...
this constraint, rely
on this constraint.
And so there are other choices.
There is an extended discussion
of this topic in the paper.
Additionally in the paper, we deal
with the whole of system F of course
with sum and products.
And we have quantification
over modalities
which means that we have
higher-order modal types.
We also show more applications
of free theorems.
And we also give
a wealth of nice details.
So feel free to check these out.
In conclusion we
declare victory because
many useful system can be
captured by our framework.
And (INAUDIBLE) rich metatheory.
As usual, it can be useful
to describe an application
which exhibits a non
commutative multiplication
or (INAUDIBLE)
Another useful development would be
to have a representation theorem
for the modality structure.
Thanks for watching.
(APPLAUSE)
STEPHANIE: Thank you Jean-Philippe.
At this point please make
sure to join a Q&A session
if it is available in your time map.
We will now pause to sync up with
the rest of the talk schedule.
(ROCK MUSIC PLAYING)
(MUSIC ENDS)
Our next talk discusses
pattern matching
in the Glasgow Haskell compiler.
It is based on work by Sebastian
Graf, Simon Peyton Jones
and Ryan Scott.
The talk will be
presented by Sebastian.
SEBASTIAN GRAF: Hi, I'm Sebastian
and I'm here to talk to you about
pattern match coverage checking.
In case you are wondering how
this problem hasn't been solved
like 40 years ago,
well lower your guard
and hold back on your jet
just for a few more minutes.
Let's start with a quick recap
of our pattern match warnings.
This incomplete definition
of isJust in Haskell here
will crush when called with nothing
because it lucks a covering clause.
Now run time crushes are
annoying especially such
an obvious oversight.
So the compiler should end
indeed in the case of GHC
it does warn about it.
I'll talk about how GHC
figures out this missing cases
apart from such missing
equations like nothing here,
compilers can also find
redundant equations
like the third one here.
In fact compilers have
been able to produce
these kinds of warnings
for a long time.
So you might think there is
nothing new to find here.
And I thought so to for
I picked up maintenance
of GHC's pattern match checker as
a side project about a year ago.
As of recently there are
over 28 open tickets
for the pattern match checker
most of them related to
performance and incorrect handling
of some subtle interaction
of source syntax features.
So how exactly can something
that looks so simple
give us so many headaches.
Let's start with a little
warm up exercise.
Is this function exhaustive?
Well that's a pretty
suggestive question
and since this isn't a live talk,
I won't be waiting for you.
The answer is no and these are
values that it failed to cover.
There are only four pattern matches
but 16 different combinations
of arguments to consider.
Clearly a scalable automated
checker needs to know when
and how to bail out of this
exponential behaviour.
Now Haskell is
lazy but not total.
That also reflects in it's
pattern matching semantics.
Take this function
here as an example.
It might be tempting to think that
the second equation is redundant
but in fact it isn't.
Deleting equation two would
alter the semantics of function
from crushing to return
three in this call here.
So not redundant.
But on the other end we
can never return two
which definitely smells like
a bug worth reporting to the user.
We say that the equation has
an inaccessible right handside.
Of course when we call
a clause redundant
that always implies it's right
hand side it's inaccessible.
Lazy but not total also means
that we have bottom
inhabiting every data type.
That includes the data type void
which doesn't have any
data constructors.
So bottom is only inhabitant.
These examples here introduce
bindings of type void
by resorting to divergence
and runtime errors.
F here matches on them in
a lazy wild card match
and it's just regular exhaustive
function definition.
Now that we have void, we can
combine it with strict fields.
Here is a strict maybe
data type as you can tell
by the strictness annotation
of Sjust field here.
Whenever SJust is constructed
its field needs to
be evaluated first.
The function F here
matches on SMaybe of Void.
Question, is the second clause
of F redundant or not.
We can answer this systematically
by enumerating
the inhabitants of SMaybe Void
and see which equations
of F match them.
The only two inhabitants
are bottom and SNothing.
SJust of bottom is
just an inhabitant
because of the strict field.
The first equation of
F diverges on bottom
and matches on nothing.
So yes redundant.
There is no value possibly
reaching the second equation.
Guards are another very basic
pattern language feature of Haskell
Does sign have any
redundant clauses,
in general it's hard to tell
without knowing the definition
of less than EQ and so on.
Also would quickly become undecidable
if we just reasoned about
every function we know
the definition of.
So apparently guards are quite
rich semantically speaking.
Here you can see how it's even
possible to pattern matching
with pattern guards.
And get here, even mixes both
structural pattern matching
and pattern guards.
This definition is exhaustive
and the compiler should not flag it
as non exhaustive.
I hope it has become clearer that
there are a lot of
surface language features
that the pattern match checker
has to cope with efficiently.
Also many of these features
interact with each other.
I won't have time to talk
about the ones in parenthesis
like long distance information.
So please do ask
questions afterwards
and read the paper
if you are interested.
The status quo in GHC was
based on a 2015 ICFP paper
that handles most of the language
features in the previous list
including GADTs and type level
information in particular.
But having been battle tested
over the last couple of years
the implementation revealed shortcomings
in being too buggy and slow.
Also it was pretty complicated. In
trying to improve on what we had,
we iterated a couple of times
and came out with the new approach
we called lower your guards.
As the name suggests,
we abandoned all structural
pattern matching like if f here
and Desugar function
definitions into guard trees.
Then we do coverage checking
on these guard trees
which is split in two
simple functions A and U.
A returns an annotated tree
decorated with refinement types
that capture redundancies
and inaccessibility information.
If you want to know about these part
I encourage you to read the paper.
U computes the set of values that
weren't covered by any clause
as a refinement type theta.
And then all we have to do is
report the inhabitants of theta
as uncovered patterns
of the definition.
Let's Desugar this
fancy example function.
Green indicates source syntax.
You can see that fancy makes
use of constructor patterns
and even to language extensions
a bang pattern that
forces the match thing
and a view pattern that
applies the match thing to g
and matches
the results against True.
In yellow you see fancy
Desugaring to guard trees.
Here is the syntax
definition for reference.
Let's focus on tree syntax first.
There is one branch
in the guard tree
for each clause in
the function definition
modelling fall through semantics.
There is also a bunch of
guards on each branch
and each branch ends in
an ordinal that identifies
a particular clause in
the original program.
Looking at guards, we can see
that nested pattern matching
was completely decomposed into
multiple flat pattern guards
like unjust here.
Pattern guards are considered lazy
and evaluation is forced by
bang guards such as x1 here
which stands for the first argument.
Pattern guards can only
match on variables
and only one level deep at a time.
We give names to more
complex expressions
like this function application
with a let binding
which also allows us Desugar
the view pattern here for example.
Desugaring also introduces
a few administrative lets
that fix up naming differences
like the one binding Xs to
the temporary t2 here.
We found similar Desugaring for
all the pattern match syntax
of modern Haskell.
Also note that desugaring is
for coverage checking only.
There is no code
generation involved.
Alright, next up characterizing
the set of uncovered values
that we can report
uncovered patterns for.
We compute the set by gradually
refining the set of possible values
as a fraction of them fall through
from one clause to the next.
How do we represent such a set with
possibly infinitely many values?
We pick refinement
types for the job.
Here are a few example
refinement types in blue
as well as the sets
they denote in orange.
Cross is the unsatisfiable
refinement predicate.
So there are no inhabitants.
Check mark is the trivial
satisfiable refinement predicate
which means we have all
the inhabitants of bool.
This is the type of
unlifted Booleans
and this one also rules out false.
This last one here shows what's
unusual about our refinement types.
It has a pattern guard on mx
that brings Just field X into scope
which then scopes over the conjunct
to the right of the pattern guard.
For some reasonably simple
end to end example,
consider this source program.
It will desugar to this guard tree
which in turn we can compute
the uncovered set for.
Note that the resulting
refinement type
as a disjunction in it's predicate
because we can fall through
from this clause here
in two different ways.
First the match on Just
could have failed
and even if the match
on Just succeeded,
the match on true could have failed.
Question, how do we
do this in general?
With a function like this,
you compute the subset of theta
whose values do not
match the guard tree t.
When we reach the right hand side,
every incoming value is covered.
So we return
the empty refinement type.
Branches model fall
through semantics.
Only values that fall
through the first branch
and fall through the second branch.
A bang guard on x adds
the constraint that x can't be bottom
to the incoming values
of the subtree
likewise for let bindings.
The pattern guard matching
against constructor k
will fall through when x is not k.
Also everything not covered
by the subtree is uncovered
so we adjoin the two refinement types.
And that is all there is
to coverage checking.
The next step is to generate
inhabitants of the refinement types
falling out at the bottom.
These are the uncovered clauses
which we want to report to the user.
If it's empty, then
the pattern match was exhaustive.
For our particular running example
the inhabitants are easy
to find, just true and
just false which are
already in a suitable form
to be presented to the user.
Algorithmically, we could use
Liquid Haskell's embedding
of refinement types,
or an SMT solver directly
to generate inhabitants.
But we didn't do that, because
reflecting GHC's type
constraint solver into SMT logic,
it's quite an undertaking.
And we think that FFI calls
and serialization affects
induce too much overhead.
So, we bit the bullet,
and just wrote our own ad
hoc generator function.
You can read more about
its implementation
and its completeness
properties in the paper.
Now, for an uncovered
set coming from
an obviously exhaustive
definition, like H here,
we find that we can
produce any inhabitants.
So, no values to represent,
hence no warnings to emit.
H is found to be exhaustive.
In conclusion, we came up
with what we find to be
quite a nice solution to
pattern-match coverage checking.
It took us many
iterations to get there,
but, in the end, it paid off.
The end result is, at the same
time, simpler to think about;
simpler to implement;
and executes much faster.
The fact that we invented
it for a lazy language
shouldn't stop you from
lowering your guards
in strict or even mostly
imperative languages.
Just write your own
de-sugaring function.
And if you're in the process
of writing a coverage checker
and don't want to make
the same mistakes,
I can only encourage
you to read the paper.
Lots of more stories to be told
about language extensions
and efficiency concerns.
Alright, that's it.
Thank you for listening.
(APPLAUSE)
STEPHANIE: Thank you, Sebastian.
If you are watching this talk live,
be sure to join the Q&A
session with the author,
if it is available in your time zone.
We will now pause to sync up
with the rest of the schedule.
STEPHANIE: The last talk
of this session is
signature restriction for
polymorphic algebraic effects.
This paper is by Taro Sekiyama,
Takeshi Tsukada and Atsushi Igarashi.
The talk will be presented
by Taro Sekiyama.
TARO SEKIYAMA: Hello,
I'm Taro Sekiyama.
This talk is about our ICFP paper,
signature restriction for
polymorphic algebraic effect.
In this work, we consider
our new type-safe approach
to combining two
programming features,
algebraic effects handlers
and polymorphism.
Algebraic effect handlers is
an approach to user-defined effects.
And they can also structure effectful
programs in a modular way.
Thanks to the separation of interface
and implementation of effect.
Using algebraic effect handlers,
we can define various effects,
such as an exception backtracking
state, and interactions by user.
Another feature we consider in
this work is polymorphism.
In particular, we consider
implicit polymorphism
as in let-polymorphism.
And by combining these
two programming features,
we can make not only expressions,
but also effects polymorphic.
So, let's show one
example of using your
algebraic effect handlers
and polymorphism.
Algebraic effects handlers
provide us three constructs
to implement our effect.
The first construct is
effect declarations
which is used in the first
line of the running example.
Here, the operation 'choose' is declared
with this polymorphic type.
So, this type means that the 'choose'
operation takes two arguments,
and returns either of them.
Here, polymorphism allows
the type of 'choose'
to abstract over
the type of argument.
The second construct
is operation calls,
which is used in these expressions.
Here, the arguments to choose
operation calls are passed
on the second function for peers.
So, both of these functions can
be of this polymorphic type.
So, the result of this
operation calls is also
assigned the same polymorphic type.
The third construct is
for 'define' effect.
and which is achieved by
the use of effects handlers.
So, if you have handlers, a key
component in defining effects,
but in this talk, I omit
the details of them.
So, the problem we consider
in this talk is (INAUDIBLE)
combining algebraic library;
combining algebraic effect handlers
and implicit polymorphism.
So, this is a problem because
the right combination
of these programming features
makes a statically
typed language unsafe.
This is because algebraic effect
handles have the ability
to manipulate delimited
continuations.
But the combination
of the use of continuations
and implicit polymorphism
is known to be unsafe.
So, this is a problem we attack
in this program, in this work.
But this is a classic problem.
There are many approaches
to solving this one.
So, the existing approaches can be
classified into two categories.
The first category is considered
restricting operation calls
in polymorphic expressions.
For the running examples,
the approaches in this category
restrict these expressions,
because this is an operation call
in a polymorphic expression.
For example, value restriction,
weak polymorphism, closure typing
belong to this category.
An advantage of using
these approaches is that
they can address any effect
including ML-style reference
under control operators.
However, the disadvantage
of these approaches is that
they impose a restriction
on any effect code.
Because, for example,
even if the operation call
doesn't need restriction.
For example, we found
in the previous work,
exceptions on the backtracking
don't need a restriction.
But the approaches in this category
don't distinguish effect
that need
a restriction from the effects,
that don't
need a restriction.
So, they impose
a restriction for all effects.
As a complimentary approach
in the previous work,
we provided our new approach to
restricting effect handlers
instead of operation calls.
So, in the running example,
this approach illustrates
this part, effect handlers.
A good point over this
approach is that
it allows operation calls
of safe effects anywhere;
and it rejects unsafe
effects safely.
But the problem of
this approach is that
it is not clear how to mix
safe and unsafe effects
in a single program.
So, this could be a problem
in a general purpose program,
because we may want to use
a safe and unsafe effect
in a single program.
To solve this problem, we
propose a new approach
which restricts the types
of effect operations.
So, in this running examples,
this new approach restricts
effect declarations.
We can determine whether
any usable effects are safe
only by examining how this is like.
OK, so, let me summarize our work.
We propose a signature restriction
which can ensure safety
of effects with polymorphism.
And the signature restriction
accepts only effects that can
be safely used anywhere, even
in polymorphic expressions
without any other restriction.
Now, the signature
restriction examines
the typed signatures of effects.
So, it is very simple criteria.
But how it is still
permissive, in the sense that
it can accept a many useful
effects and it is also scalable.
It means that their signature
restriction can easily support
basic programming constructs
including products, sums and lists.
And to shows the correctness
of this signature restriction.
We provided a simple type system
for algebraic effect
handlers and polymorphism.
We show soundness of
the simple type system
by assuming all effects satisfy
the signature restriction.
So, this demonstrates the correctness
of the signature restriction.
But the problem with this
simple type system is that
we cannot use both effects
that satisfy and don't satisfy
the signature restriction.
So, to solve this situation,
we propose an effect system
where both safe effects
and unsafe effects can be used.
And more precisely, in
this effect system,
effects that satisfy
the signature restriction can be used
anywhere without a restriction.
But if effects don't satisfy
the signature restriction,
then they can be used only
in monomorphic expressions.
We also provide
an artefact that implements
a tiny small ML-like functional
programming language,
where all effects are supposed to
satisfy the signature restriction.
And this implementation does not
cover the effect system part.
OK, so this is a quick
summary of our work.
On the next, I will present a brief
overview of signature restriction.
As I said, signature
restriction is an approach
to determining safety of effects
with the signature of effects.
So, let's suppose we
consider these operations
with this polymorphic type
Here, the signature restriction
determines the safety of effect
only by examining
the polarities of alpha
in argument type tau one
and return type tau two.
But formally, we can say operation
satisfy the signature restriction,
if and only if alpha
occurs only negatively,
or strictly positively
in argument type tau one.
And alpha occurs only
positively in return type tau two.
Here, let me remember what that
means by strictly positively.
So, in this simple function type,
the occurrences of alpha one
and alpha three are positive,
but only the occurrence of alpha
three is strictly positive.
This is because the occurrence
of alpha three is reached
by going through only
the positive part of function phi,
but the occurrence of
alpha one is reached by
going through a negative part
of functional type constructor.
So, this is the difference of
the polarities of alpha
one and alpha three.
And by using this
definitions, we check
our three operation calls
satisfy the signature restriction.
The first example is 'choose'.
So, we can easily find this type.
This type of 'choose' satisfies
the signature restriction
because, for the argument type,
the bound type variables occurs
only strictly positively.
And for return type, it also
occurs only positively.
So, all these operations satisfy
the signature restriction;
and we can apply similar discussion
to the 'fail' operation.
For the satisfied operations,
this whole function or
this argument type
may seem complicated,
but their priority
checking is very easy.
We can easily find that this type,
the bound type variable alpha
occurs only strictly positively.
So, 'satisfy' operation also
follows the signature restriction.
And, as a result,
all of these three operations
satisfy the signature restriction.
OK. So, this is our work.
But our work does not
cover all useful features
in functional programming language.
For example, this work does
not cover type inference
and general algebraic data types.
So, the support for these
features is left as future work.
And we also consider studying
a CPS transformation
for this restriction method
and applying the signature
restriction to other user defined,
or user defined effect
handler mechanisms such as the monads.
It should be interesting
because you know.
OK, let me summarize this talk.
The problem we attack
in this work is that,
naive combinations of
algebraic effect handlers,
and polymorphism may be problematic.
To solve these problems,
we propose a signature restriction
which is a new approach to determine
safety of effect in
a polymorphic setting.
The signature restriction
rests only on
the properties of
bound type variables.
So, it is very simple,
it just examines
the signature of effect.
And it is still
permissive and scalable.
We provide a simple type system
and prove its soundness
by assuming all effects satisfy
the signature restriction
and which demonstrates qualities
of signature restriction.
We also provide effects system
where both effects that satisfy
and don't satisfy the signature
restriction can be used.
That's it,
thank you for listening.
(APPLAUSE)
STEPHANIE: Thank you Toro.
If you are watching
this stream live,
don't forget about
the Q&A session
that may be available
in your time band
so that you can discuss this
work with the authors.
This is the last paper
in session four,
thank you for attending.
(SOFT INSTRUMENTAL MUSIC PLAYS)