(MUSIC PLAYS)
SUKYOUNG RYU: Hi! My name
is Sukyoung Ryu.
And I'm the Virtualization
Committee member of ICFP 2020
and the General Chair of ICFP 2021.
Hope to see you all in
the next year as well.
I'd like to welcome you
to Session Six of ICFP.
The first talk is entitled
'Compiling Effect Handlers in
Capability-Passing Style'.
This paper will be presented
by Philipp Schuster
and he will tell us about
a language for effect handlers
in capability-passing style
and implementation of the language
as a translation to
simply-typed lambda calculus
in iterated
continuation-passing style.
PHILIPP: Hi. I'm Philipp
and I present our ICFP 20 paper,
'Compiling Effect Handlers in
Capability-Passing Style'
This is joint work with
Jonathan Immanuel Brachthäuser
and Klaus Ostermann.
Effect handlers are great
and more and more languages
are getting support for Effect
Handlers in more and more libraries
where effect handlers emerge.
Still, performance is lacking.
So, this is about
the performance of effect handlers.
Now, there are two separate
aspects to the performance
of effect handlers.
One, enabling compile-time
optimizations
and two, having efficient
run-time operations.
This work is strictly
about the former.
Effect handlers allow you to
abstract over complex patterns
of control flow. Yet, this
abstraction comes at a cost.
To this end, our first
result is a theorem.
I'll read it out for you.
Full elimination - the translations
of capability abstraction,
capability
application, do, handle and so on,
do not introduce any residual lambda
abstractions or applications,
except for those in
the translation of their subterms.
What this means intuitively
is that we fully eliminate
all handler abstraction.
Of course, this is only possible
under certain conditions,
and in the paper, we formally
state those conditions.
When those conditions are met,
we guarantee full elimination
as per this theorem.
A theoretical result is great,
but what about practice?
Well, we've conducted some benchmarks
and they look generally good.
And in one case, for
example, versus Koka,
we see a speed of 409x.
Whoa. So what do we do?
We define the source
language, lambda cap,
in explicit capability
passing style.
And we will see what
that is in a moment.
We then translate this language
to simply typed lambda calculus
in iterated continuation
passing style.
We will also see what
that is in a moment.
This translation specializes
effectful functions
to the number of handlers
they are used under.
We then go on to define a second
language, lambda two cap.
It has exactly the same
syntax as lambda cap,
but a different type system.
We go on to define
the second translation,
this time to two-level
lambda calculus.
This specialized translation
specializes effectful functions
to concrete handler implementations.
So the important keywords are
explicit capability passing style
and iterated continuation
passing style.
Let's look at an example.
I'll show you a little magic trick.
I'll make all handlers disappear,
and this will go in two steps
corresponding to the two translations.
Now this is an effectful
function, choice,
written in our source
language, lambda cap.
It chooses a number between
its argument n and one.
It uses two effects, flip for
non-deterministic choice,
and fail for aborting
the current continuation.
It is written in explicit
capability passing style,
which means it explicitly
abstracts over capabilities,
flip and fail in lowercase here.
If the argument n is
smaller than one,
we fail or else we flip a coin.
And if the result is true,
we return n or else we recurse
and choose a smaller number.
Let's look at the n inside.
Here, we first install
a handler for a flip.
Handler for flip uses its
continuation k twice,
and appends the results.
Then we install a handler for fail,
which discards its continuation k
and immediately answers
with the empty list.
Both handlers introduce capabilities,
lower case flip and fail.
In the call to choice here, we
explicitly pass those capabilities
to the effectful function choice.
Each handler expects
a specific answer type.
The handler for flip expects a list
because it appends the result
of the continuation calls.
The handler of a fail also
happens to expect a list
because it immediately
answers with the empty list.
This is also why we wrap the call
to choice into a singleton list.
We call the list of answer types
from outermost sender to
innermost sender the stack shape.
Let me illustrate
why with a picture.
This is the call stack at
the call to choice.
At the bottom, we have
the handler for flip,
which expects an answer
of type list of int.
Above it, we have
the handle for fail,
which expects also
an answer type list of int.
And then we have a frame which wraps
things into the singleton list.
Now, to approximate
the shape of the stack,
we have the list of answer types.
In this case, it's
a two-element list.
The two elements are list
of int and list of int.
Because we've created the
capability flip at the outer handler
in a context with a stack
shape with a single element,
I want to use it inside
of the inner handler.
We have to fix the mismatch
on the type level here
and explicitly lift the capability.
Guided by the stack shape,
we translate our program to iterated
continuation passing style.
It is like ordinary continuation
passing style, but with a twist.
So, the translation looks like this.
We have the effectful
function choice,
and it abstracts over
capabilities flip and fail.
This is ordinary lambda abstraction.
We then define
a recursive function loop
in iterated continuation
passing style.
This means that it gets one
or more continuation arguments.
The number of continuation arguments
is determined by the number of
elements in the stack shape
because we've used choice
here under two handlers
correspondingly in a stack
shape with two elements,
it now gets two
continuation arguments.
Capabilities are ordinary functions,
also in iterated
continuation passing style.
For example, failure gets
two continuation arguments.
And also in the rest
of the function,
for example, in
the recursive code to loop
we also supply two
continuation arguments.
If we look at the handling side, we
define capabilities flip and fail.
Flip is an iterated CPS,
but in a stack shape
with a single element
and consequently gets
a single continuation.
Fail is an iterated CPS, but in
a stack shape with two elements.
So it gets two continuations.
Now, we also see that lifting
has operational meaning
because we want to use
the flip capability
in a context where we supplied
with two continuation arguments.
We somehow have to
fix this mismatch.
So we defined a new
capability, lifted flip,
which abstracts over
two continuations,
composes them and passes
the composition to the capability flip.
The call to choice now
gets five arguments,
two capabilities, the argument
n, and two continuations.
So far, we've seen our
source language lambda cap
and our translation to
simply typed lambda calculus
in iterated continuation
passing style.
We've specialized effectful
functions to the number of handlers
they are used under.
We want to go further
and specialize functions
to concrete handler implementations.
As it happens, this
program is also typable
under the rules of our second
language, lambda two cap.
So we can use our second translation
to two level lambda calculus.
This will specialize
effectful functions
to concrete handler implementations.
It is the same as our
first translation,
except that we mark some applications
and abstractions as static
and others as dynamic.
Specifically, we mark as static
capability abstraction,
the use of capabilities,
capability definitions,
the lifting of capabilities
and passing of capabilities to functions.
This program now reduces to this.
All handlers are gone.
We've specialized
the effectful function choice
to the concrete handler
implementations of flip and fail.
We call the result of
the specialization choiceFlipFail.
The handler implementations have
been inlined into the body of choice
and the continuations
have been inlined
into the handler implementations.
This enables optimizations
across effect calls.
We are not looking up dynamically
any handler implementations,
and we're not searching for prompts
on the stack or something either.
We directly invoke
the correct continuation.
At the handling side, we see
that the result is still
in iterated continuation
passing style. This is OK.
Now, let's look at those
benchmark results again.
We've benchmarked against different
languages and different systems:
the Koka language
with effect handlers
an implementation of multicore
delimited control, in Chez Scheme,
and effects as implemented
in multicore OCaml.
In all of these, we see significant
speed-ups, sometimes very big.
In this benchmark, we
see a slight slowdown,
but still competitive performance.
Interestingly, in the case
of Chez Scheme,
we don't see a difference
between our first translation
and our second translation.
This is because Chez Scheme
does all these reductions for us.
We didn't have to extend
the Chez Scheme compiler
or teach it any new tricks.
It's just lambdas,
inlining, beta reduction.
To wrap up, we've presented
a compilation technique
for effect handlers.
Important concepts are explicit
capability passing style
and iterated continuation
passing style.
We are translating to just
simply typed lambda calculus.
We don't need any
special run-time system
and we don't need any special
optimizations either.
We have a theorem that
guarantees full elimination
under certain conditions, which
we formally state in the paper.
We have benchmarks which
show good speed-ups.
And right now we're working on
integrating this compilation technique
in a new stand-alone
language called Effekt.
You should go check it out.
PHILIP: If you're interested
in effect handlers
and the implementation technique
of explicitly passing them,
we invite you to read our paper.
At the HOPE Workshop, we will
present our new language Effekt
and discuss its design.
In another ICFP talk, our
collaborator Ningning presents
the important missing link between
traditional effect handlers
and explicitly passing them.
And finally, she also presents
her Haskell implementation
at the Haskell Symposium.
See you there.
(APPLAUSE)
SUKYOUNG: Thank you, Philip.
If you're watching this talk
live as an ICFP participant,
please look to see
if there is a Q&A session
available in your time band
so that you can discuss this work
with the author of the paper.
We will now pause here to sync
up with the talk schedule.
Our next talk addresses
the challenge of extending
the metatheory of
Scala's core type system.
This talk will be presented
by Paolo Giarrusso
and the paper is entitled,
Scala Step-by-Step:
Soundness for DOT with Step-Indexed
Logical Relations in Iris.
PAOLO GIARRUSSO: Hi everybody
and thanks for tuning in.
Today I'll present joint
work with Léo Stefanesco,
Amin Timany, Lars Birkedal,
and Robbert Krebbers.
A new approach to soundness proofs for the DOT calculus,
the core of the Scala programming language.
Before we dive into this
talk, you might ask,
what's interesting about
the Scala type system?
One might answer as
Scala unifies functional
and object-oriented programming,
or has a very expressive
module system.
But what does that mean?
In other functional
programming languages,
software modules are expressed
as special constructs,
such as type classes or ML modules,
which are not first-class and require
a special abstraction mechanism.
Instead, Scala extends regular
objects with abstract type members,
allowing objects to serve
as first-class modules,
hence you can instantiate
modules at run-time
and abstract code across
modules using
regular Scala
abstraction mechanisms,
such as plain functions
or even mix-in inheritance.
While abstract types appear in other
sound type (INAUDIBLE) systems,
Scala abstract type members are
a significant challenge
for a type soundness proof
because they gain impredicative type members,
which are relatives of Type colon Type
and are challenging
to prove sound.
In a few slides, we will
see a very small example.
While Scala is interesting,
its type soundness has been
in fact an open question
since Scala's introduction in 2003.
Soundness proofs has been
machine-checked
for significant Scala fragments:
the DOT calculi, amazing success.
However, we have no proof
that abstract types are
indeed abstract.
And DOT calculi lag behind
Scala even on core features.
And are not catching up.
DOT is hard to extend
while Scala revolution
is not slowing down.
To create a more
sensible DOT calculus,
our approach is to avoid
syntactic proofs, which is
preservation and progress.
Instead, we build
logical relations models
to prove type soundness
and data abstraction.
Then, retrofitted a version
of DOT over this model,
obtaining a more
sensible DOT variant
called guarded DOT or gDOT.
Unfortunately, guarded DOT adds
certain guardedness restrictions.
But in our evaluation,
it's more acceptable.
In exchange, result is more
extensible as we show
through some additional features
that we'll mention later.
To make things concrete,
let's now look at
an example of Scala code.
In this example, we create
validator components
to validate inputs from users.
They provide an abstract type
validator of valid inputs.
And a corresponding smart
constructor is made
that validates its input and returns
either a validator or nothing.
Up to this point, nothing too fancy.
However, new validators
can be created at runtime
each with a distinct
abstract type valid.
Simplify the code.
We had called the
input type to be int.
And we say that
an input n is valid if it
is greater than some constant k.
The solution is in the next slide.
Our solution is an object that
defines the type of validators.
Inhabitants of type validator
contain two members,
the type of valid inputs, valid,
and the smart constructor is make.
Valid is declared to be a subtype of int,
the type of all ints.
That is type valid has int
as upper bound
and implicitly the empty
type nothing as lower bound.
These bounds encode that
valid is abstract.
Hence, inhabitants of valid can
only be constructed through make.
Function mkValidator maps input k
to a validator that accepts
only integers greater than k.
For instance, here by
calling mkValidator zero,
we create a validator
called pos which
only accepts positive integers
as shown by fails and works.
The type system rejects nope
because positive valid is abstract
even though it is
implemented by int,
preventing users from bypassing
our smart constructors.
Thanks to first-class modules,
you can also choose k at runtime
as now when creating legal ages.
As promised, type
legal age is not valid
as a distinct abstract type
because legal ages is
a different object
with different
validation conditions.
This small example already
uses many Scala features.
So we see that in Scala
first-class modules
with abstract types are
encoded as objects
with bounded type members.
We have used the typing rule
for type member introduction.
The type definition type A equal T
inhabits a bounded
type declaration
type A between bound,
between bounds L and U
if type T is indeed
between bounds L and U.
We have even used
impredicative type members.
Types like validator with
nested type members like valid
are still regular types,
not large types,
and are subject to
regular abstraction.
So, for instance, validator
can in turn be a type member.
Next, we sketch how we
prove type soundness.
We'll oversimplify in this talk
and leave the rest for the paper.
Our model uses a logical relation.
That is, we map each type T
to a set V of T of values that behave
as required by type T.
For instance, intersection
types are interpreted
using set intersection.
The set V of S and T
is the intersection
of V of S and V of T.
Then, we map syntactic
typing judgments
to semantic typing judgments.
For instance, S is a subtype of T
if V of S is a subset of V of T.
Crucially, an expression
e has semantic type T
if e runs safely
and any result is in V of T.
Hence, semantically typed expressions
are type-safe by definition.
Then we map each typing
rule to a typing lemma
about semantic typing judgments
that we must prove.
For instance, type S and T
is a subtype of type S
because V of S and T
is a subset of V of S.
We now have type soundness proofs
that is extensible.
Proving new typing lemmas
cannot invalidate old ones
because each lemma is
proved independently.
Next, we show a naive model of
impredicative type members.
We say that a type, if an object
V has a type member A
between bounds L and U,
if V dot A contains some type phi
which is indeed between those
bounds of L and U.
Here, metavariables V and v
range over sets of
semantic types and values
defined as follows:
types are sets of values represented
as membership predicates,
and values can be, among
other things, objects,
that is, finite maps for field
labels to values or types.
However, this definition is illegal
because inlining some types shows
that we are defining SemVal
by a negative recursion,
which is illegal.
This problem is exclusive to
something where we have
to model impredicative type members.
Thankfully, abstract step-indexing
allows us to construct SemVal
with a small change to our recursive equation.
We must guard our recursion.
That is storing types into
values must truncate types
using the Iris later functor.
I want to explain what
exactly that means.
But we can ignore details
and reason about the solution
to this question
using the Iris logic.
Most of the logical relation
would be identical
to the naive model
except for type members.
Since values only contain
truncated type members,
assertions about type members
must be weakened using
the later modality
as shown in this example.
Here, a value v has type
member A between L and U
if v dot A contains type phi
but later phi between
later L and later U.
At this point, we can
retrofit DOT over this model
obtaining gDOT.
So, we turn rules from
pDOT and OOPSLA DOT
into typing lemmas
appropriate to the model.
Each proof is around two
to ten lines of Coq.
We add a type later T
reflecting the later modality
and associated typing rules.
In this process, we obtain some
stronger additional rules.
In other cases, the restrictions
become more principled.
For instance, abstract types
are supported also in nested objects
as we have used in our example.
Distributivity, we obtain
distributivity of and and or
and other connectives.
And we also obtain subtyping
for recursive types
even beyond the typing rules used in
the OOPSLA DOT.
Here we show a few
selected typing rules.
Rules <:-Sel,
Sel-<: show that selecting
a type member A from path p
which is a certain type,
which is a type member between L and U.
gives us a type which is
between later L and later U.
This reflects guardedness
restriction on type members.
Next, rule T-Coerce
shows how we can eliminate
later in many cases
by adding now coercion to types.
Next, rule T-{}-I
allows introducing
recursive objects.
To prevent certain circular
type derivations,
we avoided (INAUDIBLE)
of other DOT calculi
and guard against
recursive self-references
by adding later to
the type of self variable x.
This rule says if you create an object
with definition x and give
it type mu x dot  T,
We must check the definitions
of type T
in a context with the self variable x
as type later T.
Finally, rule D-Val allows
to nest objects inside other objects.
Like in pDOT,
nested objects support
abstract type members.
And this is possible
because of the restriction
we added to the rule for object introduction.
In the paper, we give
motivating examples
for some of our novel features.
We scale this model to gDOT
explaining how to deal with
mu types, singleton types,
path-dependent functions,
paths, and so on.
We demonstrate expressivity despite
the restrictions to type members
and we give proofs about
data abstractions.
And we mechanize
everything in Coq using Iris.
And our soundness proof is
around 9,000 lines.
And our examples take
around 5,000 lines.
For future work, we are extending our model
to deal with type projections
and higher kinds,
additional Scala features
which have not been supported
by past DOT calculi.
We would like to find
a way to elaborate
to DOT from calculi closer to Scala
and to infer occurrences of later
which Scala users currently
do not have to write.
And we hope that these
techniques can be extended
to other object-oriented type systems
which support impredicative type
members or virtual classes.
In conclusion, Scala's type system
calls for extensible type-soundness proofs.
So we use, so we design
our type system
using a semantics-first approach.
The challenge, or one
of the challenges,
was that impredicative
type members are crucial
for Scala's expressivity
but are hard to support.
But luckily, using Iris enabled
machine-checking a solution
in a convenient way in Coq.
Thank you very much
for your attention.
(AUDIENCE APPLAUDS)
SUKYOUNG: Thank you, Paolo.
If you are watching this talk live
as an ICFP participant,
please look to see if there
is a Q&A session
available in your time band
so that you can discuss this work
with the author of the paper.
Our next talk is entitled
A Dependently Typed Calculus with
Pattern Matching
and Erasure Inference.
This paper has been
written by Matus Tejsak.
And he will tell us that
erasure in well-typed programs
is sound in that it
commutes with reduction.
MATUS TEJSAK: Hello, thank you for
coming to my talk.
My name is Matus Tejsak
and I would like to
talk about erasure
in dependently typed programming.
Dependent types are great.
They let us write specifications
and formulate invariants
and let the computer help us
make sure that our programs
conform to those specifications.
For example, here's
a program that reads
a binary number from the input,
adds one to it,
and prints a result out.
Where the type of binary
numbers is indexed
by its unary representation
which is easier to reason about
which allows us to give
the function add1 a type
that guarantees that add1 indeed
computes the successor of
the given binary number.
Unfortunately, just by
looking at the types,
we can already tell
that this program
will run in exponential time
and space with respect
to the number of
bits right from the input.
Why is that?
Well, if we look at
the implicit arguments,
which are usually hidden
and filled in by the elaborator,
we can see that each binary number
also contains
the unit representation
of the binary numbers
contained within
and the function add1 also
takes a unary representation of
the binary number it takes
and those unary representations
are exponentially sized
with respect to the number of bits.
And therefore the representation of
memory looks roughly like this.
The useful bit on
the left is dwarfed by the
compile-time only
information on the right.
So, in this talk,
I would like to convince
you that this is a real problem.
That we should really address this
and that by specifying our
programs more precisely,
we should not make them run slower
and we should not make
a linear program run
in exponential time or worse,
just by saying about it that it
calculates the right answer.
I'll sketch that,
irrelevance, erased
universes or laziness all
solve a slightly different problem.
So, they are not always applicable
or not always the best choice.
I'll sketch the gist of
how we can discover
this compile-time only information
that might be too big
and automatically discover it
and remove it from the program,
thus recovering the intended
run-time complexity.
And I'll show this
optimization makes
other optimizations more powerful,
and also makes
the compiler run faster,
because there's less
code to generate.
In language like Coq,
We might want-we
might attempt to use,
the erased universe of Prop.
However, while this is
great for erasing proofs,
it's not so good at raising indices,
as illustrated by
the function natToBin.
Because what should
be the type of n?
Should the type of n be
erased or not erased?
since function natToBin
requires n to do its job,
n must have a non-erased type.
However, because the same n
is used as an index of Bin,
it must have an erased type.
So, tying erasure to
a type of variable,
is not useful in this case.
We might even try laziness,
that works sometimes,
but it's a dynamic
fix for a static problem.
We can already tell at compile time
which bits can be erased
and which bits we need for runtime.
So, we should not keep
a runtime check,
to prevent evaluation
of that information.
We should just erase it altogether.
Laziness is not an option in
eagerly evaluated languages.
And as illustrated by
the function serverLoop,
we have a choice here between
accumulating thunks
in the variable n,
if we do not evaluate it
and therefore leaking memory,
or evaluating it and having
n explode exponentially in size.
Irrelevance can also be used,
to achieve erasure,
however, irrelevance is too strong.
By irrelevance I mean,
the property of subexpressions
ignored in definitional equality.
This is a very strong property,
and it's not necessary
for erasure at runtime.
In Agda,
irrelevance does not help us
with the binary number example,
just because it's too powerful
and causes problems.
Also inference of irrelevance is harder
than just inference of erasure.
So, there's-if we just need erasure,
we do not need irrelevance with
all the consequences it brings.
So, what do we do then?
Well, here's a small example,
function vlen that takes
a vector and calculates its length.
We can ask the question,
can we erase the second
argument of vlen called n?
Or does vlen need to look at
this argument to do its job?
Well in the first clause,
the second argument is forced to
zero indicated by square brackets,
because the vector is empty.
So, since the types tell us that
the second argument is zero,
we need not look at it. We
do not have to inspect it.
In the second clause,
the types tell us that
the second argument is a successor
of a certain number called n.
So, the types tell us
the tag of the constructor.
But they do not tell us what n is.
However, on the right-hand side,
n is used in the recursive call,
as a second argument of vlen.
So, if the recursive call
does not need the second argument,
we do not need n
and since we know the tag
and we do not need the n,
we do not need the second
argument altogether.
And it's consistent then to say that
the second argument of
vlen can be erased.
To make this a little
bit more formal,
we need to get a bit more explicit
about the pattern variables,
so we insert the two lines
starting with where,
that bind the pattern variables
explicitly and give them types.
Next, we number all colons and
all applications in
the whole program.
So, all name bindings
are numbered now.
Each of these numbers will be-
will eventually be replaced
by a definite annotation
R or E, retained or erased.
But we cannot just fill in
any annotations we like,
because they need to satisfy
some consistency constraints.
So, then we traverse
the whole program
and gather consistency constraints.
For example, in this program,
we can notice that-
that the annotation number 19,
has to be the same as
the annotation number 30,
because it's the same function
as the first argument
of function vlen,
so it has to have
the same annotation.
This is expressible in
the Horn clause form.
Then on the right-hand
side, we can observe that,
if S uses its first
argument and vector length
uses its second argument,
then the pattern variable
n needs to be available.
This is also expressible
in the Horn clause form
and we can see it in
the second line of the table.
Finally on the left-hand
side of this clause,
we can observe that
if n has to be available,
then S needs to remember
its argument,
which means number 32
has to be retained
and vector length has to
retain its second argument,
which means number 31
has to be retained.
This is also expressible
as two Horn clauses.
And in this manner, we go
through the whole program,
gather the constraints
and then find a solution
that erases as much as possible,
while being consistent
with these constraints.
This yields an annotated
program where every variable
and every application has
been annotated with R or E.
And the annotations are
built into the type system.
It's not something we
keep on the side,
it's really built into
the type signatures.
So, then we can erase everything
that's annotated with E,
obtaining the program that
we actually want to run.
And that does not contain
any traces of overhead caused
by dependent typing and indices.
This erasure system has
some nice properties.
For example, the function subst,
does not require-does not
retain its proof arguments.
So, the proof can be erased,
despite being matched on.
The types tell us what
the constructor tag must be.
We know because there's only one
constructor in the type family
and the argument x is not
used on the right-hand side.
Therefore the proof can
be erased and subst
becomes an identity
function after erasure.
Of course, this is doable only
if the type system is sound
and does not allow things
like non-termination.
Erasure also helps
the newtype optimization,
makes it more broadly applicable
and in combination with it,
it can collapse large
richly indexed structures
into just the bare
bones representation,
the meat of the structure.
Finally the identity optimization
gets more powerful with erasure,
because it's much easier to
spot that something is,
is an identity after it's
been erased so weaken E
is more obviously
an identity than weaken.
Finally, here are some benchmarks
of my prototype implementation.
The times shown include the whole
compiler pipeline from parsing,
up to and including native
code degeneration.
And we can see that
with erasure enabled,
the total compilation
time is much shorter,
because there's less
code to generate.
Given that we've shown that we can
distinguish between
compile-time only information
and runtime information
automatically,
we have shown that the commonly
claimed lack of phase distinction
in dependently typed
programs is a myth.
And it's true that the phase
distinction no longer lines up
with the distinction (INAUDIBLE)
terms and types, between
implicit and explicit, but it's
there and we can make use of it.
So, the main direction of further
research is unification with QTT,
which is Bob Atkey's extension
of Conor McBride's work,
featuring linearity as
an additional quantity
to erased and not erased.
It would be nice to have
erasure polymorphism
or quantity polymorphism,
so that functions like apply can
take erase and not erase functions.
Finally, erasure can
be inferred from
a completely un-annotated program.
However, these are
the same drawbacks as Haskell
or an ML program without
type annotations.
You make a mistake somewhere,
the system infers the wrong type
and then something
very far away breaks
and it's hard to find
the real cause.
Moreover, explicit annotation would
help with separate compilation.
So, it would be good to
find a convenient way-
convenient rules for explicit
annotation that would help with both.
Thank you for attention.
Questions are very welcome.
(APPLAUSE)
SUKYOUNG: Thank you, Matus.
If you're watching this talk live,
please don't forget
about a Q&A session,
that may be available
in your time band.
The first talk of this session is
entitled "Raising expectations:
automating expected cost
analysis with types."
Di Wang and David Khan will
present the talk together.
And they will tell us
about a type-based
analysis of deriving upper bounds
on the expected execution cost
of probabilistic programs.
DI WANG: Hello, ICFP, and
future viewers of this video.
My name is Di, a Ph.D. student
at Carnegie Mellon University.
And today my co-author David and I
are going to be presenting our work,
on automatic probabilistic
resource analyzing language,
from our paper "Raising expectations:
automating expected cost
analysis with types",
which is accompanied
by any implementation,
we call PRaML, standing for
probabilistic resource-aware ML.
Resource analysis of
programs is something that
is of renewed interest
in the modern-day.
Not only does it fulfill
the traditional role,
of identifying performance
bottlenecks, but also
the following,
if you care about digital security,
you'll need timing analysis
to mitigate side channel
timing attacks.
If you want to take advantage
of the latest tech trends
in smart contracts,
you will need to be able
to measure your past usage.
And of course,
if you care about
our real world,
it will sure help the climate
to be able to consider
the carbon footprint
of the code
run in data centers.
There are just
so many different resources,
in so many different programs.
So the problem is then nobody
has the time to go through
and formally analyze all of them.
For this reason,
our work builds upon
an approach of language-based
automatic resource analysis.
in PRaML a programmer
may code a (INAUDIBLE)
and just by type inference
receive verifiably
sound resource analysis
at their fingertips.
Now, so far, all of this
already exists in
PRaML's predecessor
resource-aware ML, or RaML.
However, PRaML can model
something that RaML cannot:
probability. Probability
is increasingly important
in modern algorithm design,
randomness and
statistical algorithms
are employed on mass data
constantly to squeeze out
every bit of efficiency.
So it is crucial that
modern resource analysis
systems can cope
with expected costs
rather than just worst case.
This is where our work
on PraML comes in,
RraML extends the worst
case resource analysis
of RaML to measure
the worst case expected value.
And it's always worth noting
that the resulting man put
is also suitable
for probabilistic modeling
and a way we'll discuss
a couple of these
applications later on.
Now, I leave it to David
to talk about more
about the meat of the work.
DAVID: Thank you Di.
Let's start by quickly going over
how type system based
resource analysis works
in a non-probabilistic setting.
We will be using RaML's
automatic amortized
resource analysis type system,
or AARA, the idea of AARA
is based on the potential method
of amortized analysis
set out by Robert Tarjan.
What we're going to do
is imbue the types
at each stage
of a program environment
with some notion
of potential energy
and allow the energy
to change over time,
but changes in potential energy
between each step
then describes the energy
discharged to pay for costs.
The key takeaway is this:
the total potential
needed at the beginning
is an upper bound
on the total cost.
So, by typing the program
with this notion
of potential energy,
we've bounded the cost,
and AARA does this
while still maintaining
the compositionality
of a type system.
This technique even works
for higher-order functions
and polynomial
or exponential cost bounds.
However, let's start small
and make an example
of the mem function
like that from
the Ocaml standard library
list module.
We will use AARA to bound
the number of recursive calls.
So here is a version
of the mem function.
Now, the men function
takes the naive approach
of checking whether
the argument x
is in the given list.
It iterates over the list,
checks each element for equality
and returns true
if it ever finds one.
At worst we might need
to check the whole list,
which means we could expect
n recursive calls
in the worst case
where n is the
length of the list.
We can show this using
the potential method as follows.
First, we explicitly
mark the costs
where they occur
using tick operations.
That would occur right here
at the recursive call.
Then we can type
the list argument
with one unit
of potential per element
written like so,
with a superscript one
representing the amount
of potential per element.
This aligns with
what we've just guessed
The worst case cost will be:
the length of the list.
Then we can write
the type of the whole function
with this, where
these numbers here
on either side of the arrow
represent the resources present
before and after
the function call.
In this case, we can
just let them be zero.
Now let's move on
to the interesting parts
in the function body
and see how we use
these types with potential
and how we match up
with the function signature
just provided.
We first deconstruct the list,
gaining the one unit
of potential that was
previously stored
at the head
of the input list.
Then if the head is the element
we're looking for,
we can just return true
and drop all
the remaining potential.
Otherwise we use
that one free unit of potential
to pay for the tick expression.
And then recurse on the tail
of the input list.
To perform
this recursive call,
we check the potential
in the current environment
against the function signature.
Because the mem function
requires one unit of potential
per element in the list,
and the tail of the input list
still has one unit
of potential per element,
this line type checks.
And that's it.
The potential we guessed
at the beginning,
one per element in the list,
is the worst case bound we guessed.
The length of the list.
As a final note
about this example,
although we did it
by guess and check,
these types actually
can be inferred.
This is because
all the relevant arithmetic
we did to calculate
these constants,
can actually be given
via linear constraints.
If we collect
the linear constraints
and solve them,
we get our desired
resource bounding type.
This continues to hold
for PraML in general as well.
Now, the language we just saw
is a subset of OCaml
and non-probabilistic.
So to make expected values
at all meaningful,
we extend it with what is probably
the most primitive
probabilistic operation possible.
The coin flip.
Specifically, we flip a coin
to decide which
branch of code to run.
We can slot this new behavior
into the RaML type system
with some pretty intuitive rules.
The flip rule deals
with coin flip expressions,
where the coin bias
is a constant.
In this rule,
Gamma is a typing context,
Q is the initial
amount of resources,
A is the resource
annotated type
of the expression.
And of course, P
is the coin flip bias.
So what this bottom part
says is just that
the flip expression
type checks
as A under context
Gamma with Q extra resources.
The key idea
of the flip rule
is that the expected cost
between the two branches,
e1 and e2, can be calculated
as the weighted sum
of their respective
typing judgments.
And you can see
here and here
that we perform
some sort of weighting
by the flip probability p.
We also allow for
a more complicated case
where the coin bias
is parameterized,
as if it were a program variable.
It turns out in
our implementation
that these two rules
can be treated
as special cases
of one more general rule.
However, despite the intuition
behind these rules,
they posed a problem.
While these type rules
do indeed turn out
to be sound,
the probabilistic nature
of the new flip operations
are incompatible
with the operational semantics
used in RaML's AARA.
However, we need
an operational semantics
in order to show
that the resource analysis is sound.
To overcome this.
We created a whole
new operational semantics for PRaML
based on
Borgstrom et al. 2016's
trace based and step-indexed
distribution based semantics.
You can find the details
of this adaptation
in the paper.
With operational semantics in hand,
we can state
soundness as follows.
If expression E types as A
under context Gamma
with Q units of initial potential,
then the expected
cost of evaluating E
is bounded by Q
plus the potential in Gamma.
This soundness statement
should seem familiar.
It is exactly the key takeaway
of the potential method
mentioned earlier.
The initial potential
bounds the cost.
This holds even for programs
that may not terminate.
We can also say that
if the cost model
counts evaluation steps,
then the existence
of any expected
cost bound at all
implies almost sure termination.
Now let's look at this
new type system in action
on a simple example.
Here's the program bernoulli,
which performs a sequence
of Bernoulli trials.
When run, it has a 50% chance
of recursing and a 50%
chance of terminating.
As many might remember
from their intro
to probability course,
this results in a
geometric distribution
with expected value two.
Thus, while it
could go on forever,
we can actually give it
a finite notion of cost.
Let's check it now
using PRaML.
Now the only initial potential
that bernoulli needs is two units.
One unit of potential is spent
immediately on the tick.
After the coin flip,
we assign
zero potential to the head case
because it returns immediately.
And two units of potential
to the tails case.
Then in the tails case,
we reuse the guessed
type of bernoulli,
and it all works out.
Because the weighted sum
of the potential assigned
to these two branches
is exactly one.
The flip rule justifies
billing into these branches
with only one unit of potential,
even though
the tails branch by itself
would require two.
In the paper
we use this same
automated technique on a variety
of more complicated functions
with more interesting
resource bounds.
For instance, we show
that PRaML can analyze
the "gambler's ruin"
wherein two players,
Alice and Bob, continually bet
one dollar against each other
on the results
of a coin flip
until one player
runs out of money.
In the program,
we modeled the amount
of money as
the length of a list.
If the coin is fair,
Alice starts with
A dollars and Bob starts with B dollars,
then this series of bets
is expected to take
A times B rounds.
Our implementation infers
this bound exactly.
PRaML can also infer
non-trivial bounds
with parameterized probabilities.
The Von Neumann function
implements a mechanism
to make a fair coin
from a biased one.
With some scaling trick, PRaML
derives that the function
is expected to take
one over P times
one minus P steps,
where P is the probability
for the biased coin
to show heads.
Both of these examples
also show that PRaML
can be of use
in probabilistic modeling,
As these are
both probabilistic models.
Here are some tables
of various other analyses
of probabilistic models
from the paper.
The bounds themselves
are of various complexities,
but one nice takeaway
is that the time taken
to analyze these programs
automatically, is usually
well under one second.
This is good,
because real world analyses
need to run in
a practical timeframe.
Now let's talk about some more
empirical probabilistic modeling.
Look back quickly
at mem and bernoulli.
If you squint a little,
you might notice that
mem behaves
a lot like bernoulli,
possibly terminating
at each iteration.
In fact, if we say that
equality holds with 50% chance,
then the runtime profiles
of these two programs
are pretty much the same,
and note the constant expected
cost of two from bernoulli
is far better
than the linear
worst-case cost of mem.
This opens up another avenue
for analysis using probability:
approximating
deterministic branches
with probabilistic ones.
If we can empirically determine
that some code
branches with a given probability,
we can approximate it
with a flip and use
the PRaML type system
to get a better sense
of the actual
resource usage.
In our implementation artifact,
we include a mode
for doing this and we include
some results of its application
in our paper.
For instance, insertion sort
achieves linear time complexity
on nearly-sorted data.
That's all I have.
I now leave it to Di for the close.
DI: Thank you, David.
In summary, in this paper
we have developed
a probabilistic extension
to the AARA type system.
We overhauled the operational
semantics to prove it sound.
We also implemented
the result at least back
to determination programs,
with empirical
statistical techniques.
In the paper, we also give
one more application
about automatic analysis
of sample complexity.
That is all we have
the time to talk about
and thank you for listening to
our talk.
Stay healthy
and hopefully
we can talk in person
next year.
(APPLAUSE)
SUKYOUNG: Thank you,
Dee and David,
if you are watching
this talk live,
please don't forget
about a Q &A session
that may be available
in your time band.
Now our next talk is entitled,
"Problem sketching with life
by directional evaluation."
Justin Lubin will present
a talk and he will
introduce Smith,
an example based
program synthesizer
with supper for sketching and no
trace (INAUDIBLE) requirement.
JUSTIN LUBIN: Hi everyone.
My name is Justin Lubin,
and I'm gonna be
presenting programs
sketching with live
bi-directional evaluation.
So this is a program
synthesis project.
And by program synthesis,
I mean computer generation
of programs satisfying
a specification.
So the two key words
to take away here
are satisfying
and specification.
Let's take a look
at what I mean
by those, by specification.
I mean the user
interface to a synthesizer.
It's how the user provides
a notion of correctness
for potential program.
Satisfaction is
then simply a program
meeting the specification criteria.
So let's take a look at two popular
user interfaces, the synthesizers.
The first of which is
logic-based synthesis.
In logic-based synthesis, we
provide a logical formula
as a means of specification.
So for example, if we're trying
to specify the sole function,
we might say that for all
indices i in array A,
A(i) has to be less than
or equal to A(i+1).
Satisfaction in
logic-based synthesis
is typically going to be
static verification.
So for example, we might use
tools such as SMT solvers,
dependent type-checking,
model checking, etcetera.
Now, there have been many great
logic-based synthesizers
that have come out over the years.
For example, Synquid,
Rosette, Sketch and Leon.
These types of tools excel when we
need to encode complex invariants
about more complicated data
structures, such as red-black trees.
Let's take a look at another
interface to program synthesis,
example-based synthesis.
In example-based synthesis,
specification takes the form of
input-output examples.
Here, I've asserted
the sort of the empty list
as the empty list and that
sort of (3,1,2) is (1,2,3).
Satisfaction will now take on
the form of dynamic verification.
What we'll need to do
is we need to test each
input-output pair.
We'll need to evaluate and check.
And the key words on this
slide are evaluate and check.
We'll definitely be
returning to that later.
So, some really great
example-base synthesizers
that have come out include Myth,
Escher and lambda squared.
For this project, we're gonna
be working in the domain
of example-based, richly-typed,
general-purpose, functional,
program synthesis.
Let's take a look at
the current state
of the art in this domain to
see what we're up against.
And that would be the Myth project.
The way that Myth works is
you give it a type signature
instead of input-output examples.
And as output, you get
a function that when run,
will satisfy those assertions.
For the purposes of this talk,
I'm more or less gonna be
treating Myth as a blackbox.
One, it will take in examples
and give us a solution as output.
Myth is a powerful
program synthesizer,
but it has two key limitations
that we might like to address.
Let's take a look at
the first of these two.
Given input-output examples,
Myth will transform an empty
program into a full solution.
What if we, as programmers,
wanted to encode some
domain-specific knowledge
that we might have into
a partial solution
towards the program that
we'd like to make.
Then we'd like for Myth to transform
this partial solution
into a full solution.
The idea here is known
as program sketching.
And it already exists for
logic-based synthesis
in untyped languages via
the Sketch and Rosette projects.
But we want sketching for
example-based synthesis
and richly-typed language.
So, to recap, program sketching
is when you have a program
with some holes in it,
which might possibly
be interdependent,
and arbitrary assertions
on this program,
which is where we're gonna
derive our input-output examples.
And what you get at
the end of the day
is a completed program.
So let's take a look at,
Myth's second limitation
which is known as
the trace-completeness requirement.
To be fair, this isn't just Myth
that suffers from this problem.
A lot of the programs synthesizers
that I mentioned earlier
also have some sort of
trace-completeness requirement.
So, what is trace-completeness?
Well, a set of examples for
a function is trace-complete if
when the function is called
on each example in the set,
all its recursive calls also
have an example in the set.
Let's take a look at
a small example.
Let's say I have the length
function as defined here.
And I want to specify
the example that
length of (1,5,6,1) is 4.
Well, the problem is
that length actually makes
a recursive call here
on the tail of its input.
So, I'm going to actually
need to specify
an example for length of (5,6,1).
And similarly, I'm then
going to need to specify
an example for length of (6,1)
and length of (1)
and length of the empty list.
So, to recap, here are
two limitations of Myth.
First one is that it has
no support for sketching.
And the second is that it has this
trace-completeness requirement.
But, instead of framing
these as limitations,
what if we treated them as goals?
And instead saying that there is
no support for sketching,
we wanted to add
support for sketching
and remove
the trace-completeness requirement.
Then we could call our system Smyth.
So what we'd like to do is
provide Smyth a sketch,
which would be our first goal,
and some non-trace-complete
examples,
which would be our second goal,
and get the same output as before.
Let's take a look at how we
can support this first goal,
adding support for sketching.
So here's how Smyth
is going to work.
As a specification, we're
going to give it a sketch
and some assertions.
And because Smyth is example-based
we're going to need to do
dynamic verification.
As before, this means that we're
going to need to test each assertion.
We're going to evaluate and check.
But here is where it gets tricky.
What exactly do evaluating
and checking mean
when given a program sketch?
Well, the answer to the first of
these questions is live evaluation,
which is a theory that we draw
from the Hazel project
which you can find @hazel.org.
Let's take a look at how it works.
Say we are given
the program e on the left,
which computes 10+20
plus the first of this pair
x, where x is 4, comma, a hole.
Well, we can compute
the 10+20 and get 30 just fine.
And then we can also take
the first of this pair,
which we know is going to
be the concrete value four.
So we can get normal output 34.
Notationally, we would say that
in the empty environment,
e evaluates to 34.
But what if we change
the first of x to second of x.
We can complete the 10+20
just fine as before,
but now second of x is
going to give us a hole.
In traditional programming systems,
this would either
result in an exception
or a crash or some sort
of meaningless output.
But the key instead
of live evaluation
is that we can actually just
evaluate around this hole.
So, because we have
a hole in our input,
we get a hole in our output.
And we get 30 plus hole zero.
Note that we also keep
track of the environment
around the hole at
the time of evaluation
because that's gonna be really
useful for synthesis later.
Notationally, we would say that
in the empty environment,
e live evaluates to 30 plus hole
zero with that environment.
So that's how we can run
these program sketches.
But now how do we check
these programs sketches
against the arbitrary assertions
that we might have on them?
Our answer to that is
a novel mechanism
that we call live unevaluation.
Let's take a look at how
live unevaluation works.
Let's say we are given
the same program before, e,
and evaluates to 30 plus that
whole closure hole zero.
Well, if we want the entire
program to be equal to 100,
then we can actually transform
this global constraint
from an assertion onto
a local constraint on the hole.
Namely, that hole
zero needs to be 70.
As a slightly more
complicated example,
let's say we have
a program e that evaluates
the first of some hole or one.
And we want the entire
program to evaluate to eight.
You can transform this
global constraint
onto a local constraint on the hole,
namely, that hole one
needs to be the pair eight, comma,
top, where top is anything at all.
Finally, let's take a look at
our max program from before.
If we want to assert
that max of (1,2)
needs to be two with
this program sketch,
we can actually live evaluate it.
So in the empty environment,
we say that max (1,2)
live evaluates to (4,2)
with the environment
n=1, m=2 and n'=0.
We live unevaluate
the two onto this expression.
And we get the whole
constraint that hole two
needs to be two in that environment
that I mentioned earlier.
So that's how live
unevaluation works.
Plus satisfaction in Smyth
will look like live evaluation
followed by live unevaluation.
And it's a combination
of these two concepts
that we call live
bidirectional evaluation.
But as a satisfaction mechanism,
live bidirectional evaluation
actually introduces
these new constraints x over
here on the right hand side.
So let's take a look,
at a high level,
how this will fit into
the program synthesis loop.
In Smyth, we're gonna start
with Myth as a blackbox.
Then, when the user
provides a sketch,
we can live evaluate
it and get a result.
We'll also collect these programming
samples from the assertion
and live unevaluate them onto
the result that we get.
This process, which we call
live bidirectional evaluation,
will result on constraints
on individual holes
that we can plug directly into Myth.
Then if we augment Myth
with some additional rules
to handle the partial solutions
that we're looking for,
we can actually get
a partial solution from Myth
and some new program examples.
Then we can iterate this process
until we arrive at a full solution.
So if we look back at our goals,
we can see that live
bidirectional evaluation
enables us to add
support for sketching.
What about this
trace-completeness requirement?
Well, it turns out that live
bidirectional evaluation
also solves this problem.
To see how, let's take a closer
look at trace-completeness.
Let's say we want to
specify the function length
using these two
non-trace-complete examples
as well as a blank sketch.
The first step would be to live
unevaluate these assertions
and get the two hole
constraints that
when x is the empty list,
well, zero needs to be zero.
And when x is (1,5,6,1),
well, zero needs to be four.
Because Smyth is not going to find
a non-branching expression
to satisfy this hole,
it's going to introduce a case
expression that splits on x's.
Now, we live unevaluate
these assertions again
and get two new hole constraints.
Namely, that when x is the empty
list, well, one needs to be zero.
And when tail is (5,6,1), among
other things in the environment,
well, two needs to be four.
Now this first hole
constraint is very easy
for Smyth to solve.
It can simply bind hole one
to be the constant zero.
That will take care of
this first constraint,
so we no longer need
to worry about it.
The second constraint could
be handled similarly,
but Smith avoids over specializing
on large constants like four
because they don't generalize well.
So, instead, it might try to
synthesize the expression
one plus length tail.
Well, we run into a dilemma here.
How can we be calling length on tail
when we don't even
know what length is?
Because that's the function that
we're trying to synthesize
in the first place.
Here's where traditional
program synthesizers
could leverage
the trace-completeness requirement.
If we were guaranteed
to have the example
that when x is equal to (5,6,1),
length of x is going to be three.
And we could simply slot in
three for length of tail
and see that 1+3 is going
to satisfy our requirement
that hole two needs
to be equal to four.
But we don't have that example.
So instead, the key
insight is to realize
that we actually do have
a definition for length of x's.
Length of x's is going to
be equal to hole zero.
In our partial solution,
we see that hole zero is
going to be equal to
this case expression right here,
which depends on hole
one and hole two.
But nonetheless, we can run
live bidirectional evaluation
from before as usual
on these programs,
because they're just
normal sketches.
Doing so will result
in a new set of
live unevaluation problems
that we can just perform
to get a set of new constraints.
And it turns out that this
program that we synthesized
actually satisfies all these
generated constraints,
as well as our original constraint
that hole two needs to be four.
Therefore, all of our constraints
have been taken care of,
so we have a full
solution for length.
So, that's how live
bidirectional evaluation
can also take care of
the trace-completeness requirement for Myth.
So, to wrap up, let's talk
about some of the experiments
that we run to evaluate Smyth.
Here, I'll be talking about
four experiments that we run
based on the Myth benchmark suite.
In the first experiment,
we took the trace-complete examples
from the Myth benchmark suite
to specified various functions
and provided no additional
sketching information to Smyth.
With this information, we
could successfully synthesize
38 out of the 43 benchmarks
from the Myth benchmark suite.
In the paper, we talk
about some hypotheses
why we couldn't get
that number up to 43.
In our second experiment,
we took these
trace-complete examples,
but we removed as many as we could
while still having Smyth
synthesize a correct solution.
We found that with these
non-trace-complete examples,
we could achieve a 61%
specification size
in Smyth as compared to Myth.
In our third experiment, we took
just the recursive functions
from the 38 that we could synthesize
and provided a sketch of
the base case Smyth.
Then, like in experiment two, we
took the trace-complete examples
from experiment one, and paired
them down to a minimal subset
that Smyth needed to be able to
synthesize the function correctly.
Including the sketch
of the base case,
we found that we needed approximately
a 46% specification size
as compared to Myth.
In our fourth experiment, we
ran experiments two and three
in the popular logic-based
synthesizers, Leon and Synquid.
It's commonly said that
logic-based synthesizers
are strictly superior to
example-based synthesizers
because you can simply
encode examples and logic
as a conjunction of implications.
Well, there is some
truth to that sentiment.
It's also true that many
logic-based synthesizers
are not well equipped to handle
that kind of specification.
And in fact, this experiment showed
that while there are many tasks
on which Leon and Synquid
performed quite well,
there are also many tasks
on which they did not,
particularly relating to
non-trace-complete examples.
We hypothesize that
combining the insights
of live bidirectional evaluation
with logic-based program synthesis
could result in a system that
has the power to specify
complex data structure and variance,
while also having the ease of
use of not having to specify
trace-complete examples.
The last thing that I'd like to
say is that these four experiments
are a measure of expressivity.
But we also ran experiments that
tested the robustness of Smyth.
And these are described
more in the paper.
So that's Smyth, an example-based
program synthesizer
with support for sketching and no
trace-completeness requirement.
Here's an overview of what
the system looks like.
And here's a link to where
you can find it on GitHub.
You can also find me
@jplubin on Twitter.
I'd like to give a huge thanks to
my collaborators Nick Collins,
Cyrus Omar and Ravi Chugh for
helping me with this project,
as well as the ICFP
organizers and volunteers
for making this conference possible.
Lastly, I'd like to give
a shout out to an event
that I'm helping organize
ICFP,  #ShutdownPL@ICFP.
There will be an anti-racism event
occurring on Thursday, August 27,
from 2pm to 6pm Eastern time.
I hope to see you there.
And thanks for watching.
(AUDIENCE APPLAUDS)
SUKYOUNG: Thank you, Justin.
And thanks (INAUDIBLE) for organizing
the anti-racism event,
#ShutdownPL@ICFP.
If you are watching this talk live,
please don't forget
about a Q&A session
that may be available
in your time band.
Our next talk is entitled
Elaboration with First-Class
Implicit Function Types.
Andras Kovacs will be
presenting the talk.
ANDRAS KOVACS: Hello everyone,
this is Andras Kovacs.
And I will talk about
elaboration with first-class
implicit function types.
In this talk, I will only give
a rough overview of the paper.
And you can look at
the paper for details.
Let's explain the title
of the talk a bit.
First, what is elaboration?
It is a translation from
surface syntax to core syntax.
Surface syntax is a parsed
representation of what programmers
actually see in a source file.
It is usually compact
and convenient to read and write,
but omits a lot of
typing information.
and it is not
necessarily well-typed.
the core syntax is used
internally by the compiler.
It is simple, well-typed,
and explicitly annotated
but it is much more verbose
than the surface syntax.
Elaboration can include
inference, desugaring,
instance resolution and other things
but this talk mostly
focuses on inference.
In a setting with dependent types
people often use the term elaboration
instead of type inference.
Because inference necessarily
involves term inferences
while the type inference
is a bit too specific.
Second, what are implicit functions?
These are functions such that
arguments are given by inference
by default and not
by the programmer.
IN GHC Haskell forall
types are an example.
These are functions
abstracting over types
or other types that are data.
The arguments for Forall abstraction
are inferred by default as here
but you can all see these
visible type application
to fall back to explicit
arguments as here.
In GHC type level abstraction
in always implicit
and value-level functions
are all these explicit.
But this restriction
is specific to GHC
and it is not something fundamental.
In Agda, likewise having
implicit functions types
but you are free to make any
function implicit or explicit
and type abstraction is
just a special case
of general dependent functions.
Both in GHC and Agda, implicit
function types control elaboration
by signalling where
implicit applications
should be inserted.
After elaboration, implicit functions
are not that important any more
because everything is fully
explicit in the core syntax.
Implicit function types are
first class if they can be used
as simply as any other type.
In GHC with RankNTypes
in enabled
we can use an implicit function
as a function argument type
and in this case type inference
also goes fairly well.
But what if you want to
use an implicit function
in some other parameterized data type?
Such as Maybe as in this
particular example.
This is not really
possible in current GHC.
There is a language extension
called inpredicative types
which technically allows
writing down this type
that is deprecated and doesn't
let you work in practice.
There is another talk at
the current ICFP which introduces a new
and practical usable implementation
of this language extension.
As a side note, users
of lens libraries
may be familiar with
the examples on this slide.
Lenses are polymorphic functions
so they can be used in
higher order functions
but if you want to store
them in data structures
then you have to use some
new type records
What happens in Agda.
Here we can use implicit
functions times anywhere
so this type signature
is completely fine.
However elaboration is not
as smart as it could be
and the next line
does not elaborate.
Here we have to write out
an implicit lambda abstraction
in order to make Agda happy.
The main contribution of this
talk is a general solution
which figures out such insertions
of implicit lambdas.
At this point some people may note
that the previous Agda example
is an instance of something
called impredicative inference.
Or impredicative polymorphism
which is a topic in the wider
field of type inference.
And the main point of this work
is to provide a solution for
impredicative inference.
However impredicativity means
mostly orthogonal things
in the type theory and in
the type inference literature.
You can look at the paper for how
exactly the two notions differ.
I personally prefer to use
the term impredicative
in the technical type
theoretic sense
and talk instead about
implicit functions
in the context of type inference.
With that said, to summarise
the contributions of the current work
we have an elaboration algorithm
which supports strong inference for
first class implicit function types
or impredicative inference
and it also supports dependent
types and global inference
which means that
the whole module of program
can be considered in inference
and not just a particular
function application
as in some previous works.
The algorithm is also efficient
it uses no backtracking or iteration
and it actually traverses
the pre-syntax exactly once.
And lastly the algorithm
a the modest extension
of bidirectional elaboration
as implemented in Agda.
Since the paper's algorithm is
an extension of bidirectional elaboration
first we shall briefly talk about it
and then look at the short comings
with respect to handling first
class implicit functions
and finally look at the solution
presented in the paper.
Bidirectional elaboration
consists of two functions
defined by mutual
recursion on surface syntax
Let us assume a surface expression T
and a core context gamma.
The purpose of elaboration
is to create something
in the core syntax from
the surface expression.
First we have the infer function
which takes as input a core context
and a surface expression
and return a core expression together
with its core type.
the check function additionly takes
an input an expected core type
and returns a core
term with that type.
When the expected type of
the expression is already known,
we use a check function,
otherwise we use infer.
This is similar to
bidirectional type checking
but here each function
also returns a core term.
Let's look at a short
example of how checking works.
We use an informal
monadic notation
as we have as side effect
possibility of failure
and we also carry around a state
context of meta variables.
Here we are checking a lambda
expression with a function type.
So what we do is to expand
the context with the variable
and check the function body
with the codomain type.
After this return of a
core lambda expression.
In general the check function tries
to push types inside constructors
which is beneficial for
performance elaboration
and also for the locality
of error messages.
In the paper the only change
the elaborator can make
on the input surface syntax
is that it can insert
implicit lambdas
and implicit applications.
As we will shortly see,
this implicit insertion relies
crucially on the bidirectional style.
We won't look at the exact
rules of the elaborations here
and then look at some examples.
First let's look at an example
for application insertion.
Assume that we have the usual
polymorphic identity function
and we want to infer a type for ID
applied to the Boolean true
This expression is
a functional application.
So first we are infer a type for
the function argument which is ID.
Then we noticed thatthe inferred type
is an implicit function type.
So we insert an implicit
application here.
First create a fresh meta
variable named alpha,
then we apply the new elaborated
ID expression into it.
In the following, we will name
meta variables using Greek letters.
Now we have a function
from alpha to alpha.
This is good because we started
elaborating an explicit
function application
and now we have an inferred
explicit function type
for of next sub
term of the application.
What remains is to
check the right subterm
with the function domain type.
Here we don't have any
specific checking rule
so we change from
checking to inference
and infer type bool for true.
Then we unify the expected
alpha type with the bool type.
Now we can return the whole
application as elaboration output
together with the bool type.
In general whether we have
a bound or defined variable
name with an implicit function type
when we use the name
implicit applications
are inserted for
the implicit arguments.
Now let's look at an example for
inserting an implicit lambda.
We want to check this
lambda expression
with the usual polymorphic
identity function type.
First we noticed that expression
is not an implicit lambda
much rather an explicit lambda.
So the expression as
it is definitely
does not have
the expected checking type.
However we can wrap the expression
in the newly inserted
implicit lambda
so that's what we are going to do.
We assume the implicit argument
in the typing context
and check the expression with
the codomain of the checking type
which happens to be
an explicit function type here.
Now the types march up
so the checkings succeeds
and return the expression
with the inserted lambda.
To summarize implicit insertion
when we infer
an implicit function type
we may insert
an implicit application
and when we check with
an implicit function type
we may insert an implicit lambda.
This has a nice symmetry
and it performs
in a fairly convenient
and intuitive way in practice.
Note that we don't always perform
insertion in these two cases.
For example when we
check an implicit lambda
with an implicit function type
there is no need to do insertion.
Again for the exact rules
you can look at the paper.
What can go wrong with the solution?
Let's go back to
the failing counterexample.
We also assume that
we do not have rule
for checking the constructor
of the Maybe type.
This is not necessarily
always the case
and actually the most
recent version of Agda
can handle this example fine
but to stick from this example
for the sake of simplicity.
Because we don't have
a checking rule for just
we first infer a type
for this expression
then you find an infer type
with the given annotation.
The just constructor is polymorphic
so it has an implicit type argument
and we insert an application
to a fresh meta variable.
Next we have to check
the lambda x x expression
with the unknown alpha type.
This is the key point of failure.
The problem is that we cannot do
lambda insertion at this point
because the checking
type is unknown.
The only thing we can do is to
infer an explicit function type
for the lambda X X expression
but to first unify
the given type annotation.
Likewise we have dual
version of this problem.
When the infer type is unknown we
cannot do application insertion.
The solution is to represent unknown
insertions in the core theory.
With meta variables, we
already have the ability
to represent unknown terms
so we extend this to all
cover unknown insertions.
We add a strictly
curried function type.
This is a function type such that
the domain is always a record type
and currying holds by definition.
Here we have an example of how currying
computes for this function type.
The type in the left side has
an empty record type as domain
we denote the record type as a rec
followed by a list of types.
Here the list is empty so we
get the empty record type.
This function type computes
to just codomain type,
so the trivial function
argument disappears.
For another example, if the domain
is record type with two fields
the function type computes
for a function type
for two implicit arguments.
In general a curried
function type computes
to an iterated implicit
function type.
The are also appropriate computation
rules for term constructors
which follow the rules for types.
Now we can represent an unknown
number of implicit arguments
by putting the meta
variables in the domain.
We use this to improve
on the elaboration.
Previously, unknown types always
prevented the implicit insertion.
We change this as follows.
We check with an unknown type
we insert with an unknown
number of lambdas
using strictly curried
function type.
Concretely we enter
strictly curried lambda
which may compute later to zero
or more implicit lambdas.
Changing lambda insertion this
way is easy to implement
and improve inference
in a large number
of practically interesting cases.
However we don't enhance
application insertion
and live that to future work.
The reason is that unknown
application insertion
yields rather complex
unification problems
which could be a line of
research on it's own.
Now the running example is
elaborated without issues.
In the inferred type
for the expression
the Rec alpha stands for an unknown
number of implicit arguments.
Also the unknown beta type can
now depend on the argument.
Then being defined inferred
and expected types.
For strictly curried function
unification tries to measure
two sides of the equation
by solving curried function domains.
In this case the domain is
solved to a unary record
which contains a set.
So unification succeeds and we get
the expected elaboration output.
We are nearing the end of the talk
so let's revisit this picture about
elaboration to provide the summary.
This picture is actually
not quite correct.
In practical implementations,
the core syntax which is
used for optimizations
and further compilations is not
the same as the core syntax used
in elaboration, we used to
have a picture like this.
We used slightly larger
and more complicated core theory
for the purpose of elaboration.
Implicit function types provides
control over implicit insertions
and meta variables allowing
representing unknown terms.
However this core theory is also
nice and well behaved type theory.
This is infact a modal type
theory since meta variables
and meta context form
the so called crisp modality
or alternatively,
a contextual modality.
If you don't use meta variables
and we only use
bidirectional type checking,
the inference becomes
rather limited.
Meta variables are the natural solutions
for representing unknown terms
and they are a basic ingredient
in implementing more
sophisticated inference.
It is also important to not that
if you successfully finish elaboration
all meta variables are solved.
And we can also just ignore or translate
away implicit function types
So the extra features don't
affect down stream compilation.
If we allow first class
implicit functions types
that causes implicit
insertion to be more dynamic
and more interleaved in
the elaboration algorithm.
Therefore if you want to
have robust inference
with first class
implicit function types
we need to represent unknown
implicit insertions.
Strictly curried function
types provide a natural
and tight representation.
Additionally strictly
curried functions
are a modest extension
of type theory
so we still have a well behaved
and computationally
adequate core theory.
Unlike the other extra features,
strictly curried features also
disappear after elaboration.
My impression is that
if you want to have
robust impredicative inference
strictly curried functions
are a basic ingredient
similar to how meta variables
for general inference.
Without those basic building
block potential solutions
are significantly limited
in power and efficiency.
(APPLAUSE)
SUKYOUNG: Thank you Andreas.
If you are watching this talk live
be sure to join the Q&A
session with the author
if it is available
in your time zone.
The last talk of this
session is entitled
Kinds are Calling Conventions.
Paul Downen will present the talk.
PAUL DOWNEN: Hi, I'm Paul Downen
and I'll be telling
you about how kinds
can express calling conventions
in programing languages.
Functional languages making
calling function simple and easy.
But there are many different
parameter passing techniques
which impact the performance of
PAUL:.. function calls.
Because this is pervasive
in function languages,
it's important to
make them efficient.
To implement a function call,
we need to be able to answer some
basic questions about its arguments.
First, what is the arguments'
representation at runtime?
It could be an address, a character,
a floating point number etcetera.
And how big is it?
For example, it could be just
1 byte or a 64-bit word.
We also need to know
where is it stored.
It might be in a specialized
floating point register
or it could be
a pointer into the heap.
For the function main call,
we need to know its arity
which is how many
arguments are needed
before its code can be
properly executed.
We also need to know
how many arguments
can be passed simultaneously.
Should it be passed all at
once in multiple chunks?
Or individually, one at a time?
Lastly, we need to know the levity
by which I mean to say
the evaluation
strategy of the argument.
For example, eager
languages use call-by-value
and lazy languages use
call-by-need evaluation.
Laziness in particular
has an overhead
that might not be necessary
for a strict function.
Moreover, we will see that evaluation
strategy interacts with arity
as well as representation.
Since it's probably the least
understood of these three topics,
I will focus primarily
on arity in this talk.
Arity is not always
so simple to see.
Consider these four
functions of the same type.
The type suggests they have arity 2.
They need two arguments before
they produce a result.
But this type might leave out
important operational details
that we only learn from
the function definitions.
Look at the definition of f1.
It starts with two lambas,
so it requires two arguments
before doing any interesting work.
So, f1 definitely has arity 2.
Now, look at f2.
It only starts with one lambda,
however, all it does is call f1.
So, it also requires two
arguments before doing any work.
In fact, we can eta expand f2 and
doing so does not change its
meaning or runtime behavior.
This sound eta expansion makes it
clear that f2 also has arity 2.
F3 is very similar to f1, both
an important difference -
f3 starts with only one
lambda for binding x
then it does some work on x before
requesting the next argument y.
So, what is f3's arity?
As a hint, consider that expensive
of x might be costly to compute
as the name suggests.
And it might even cause side
effects in a language like OCaml.
For this reason, f3
only has arity 1.
F4 is defined similarly to
f2, however this time,
the eta expansion is not sound.
That's because f3 can do some
serious work with only one argument.
So, f4 also has arity 1.
Based on those examples,
let's try to come up
with some informal
intuitive definitions
about what arity is
meant to capture.
First, we already used
the intuition of 'serious work'
when analyzing
the arity of a function.
For example, if f applied to
1, 2, and 3 does work,
but f applied to only
1 and 2 does not,
then arity has... f has arity 3.
Second, we sometimes need
to use eta expansion
to see the full arity of eta
reduced function definitions.
So, if f is equivalent to its thrice-eta expanded form
as shown here, then f has arity 3.
Note that we need to be careful.
Sometimes this eta expansion
might not be sound
because it could change behavior
or the cost of a function.
This is especially true in
languages with effects,
but even pure languages like
Haskell care about efficiency,
so we have to be careful there too.
Third, in an operational sense, arity
tells us a number of arguments
that may pass to a function
simultaneously in a single call.
For example, if f has arity 3,
then f applied to 1, 2 and 3
can be compiled into
a single function call
rather than a chain of
three partial applications.
Now, focus on definitions 2 and 3.
They serve as the main
backbone for our idea.
Definition 3 suggests that arity
is important for performance.
There's reduced cost for calling
functions of higher arity
whereas definition 2 says
that arity can be seen
in terms of the eta law
of the lambda calculus.
The arity of a function corresponds
to the number of
valid eta expansions.
Taking together,
making more eta expansions
valid can improve the arity
and thus, performance of
function calls in a language.
This link sets up our goal in
the context of an intermediate language
for an optimizing compiler.
However arity analysis is done,
that information must somehow be
expressed inside of the internal code
used in the compiler.
We can do this with an ultimatum.
Eta expansion is always valid.
That way, there are no more
corner cases to worry about
and so, arity is always
the largest number
that makes sense for any function.
However, we can't lose
what we already have.
Practical compilers place
restrictions of beta reduction
they are crucial for
algorithmic complexity.
Therefore, our goal is to have
an intermediate language
with unrestricted eta
expansion for functions
but alongside with
restricted beta reduction
for arguments of other types.
Here is our general
approach to the design
of an arity aware
intermediate language.
First, we add a new type
for primitive functions
denoted by this squiggly arrow, rather
than this normal straight arrow
to help distinguish them
from functions in the source
programming language
that have a slightly
different semantics.
In particular, primitive
functions are fully extensional
and this is different
from the functions in
normal programming languages
like Haskell and OCaml
where the eta law might not apply
to all expressions
of a function type.
However, application may still
be restricted for efficiency
and for the purposes of
languages semantics.
So, for example, in the case where
a paremeter is used more than once.
If you apply the function lambda x,
x applied to x to
an expensive argument,
it doesn't need to be
recomputed for both uses of x.
Because of unrestricted eta,
types can now express
the arity of functions.
All we have to do is
count the arrows.
For example, if f is to
type int to bool to string,
we know that it has arity 2 already
without even looking
at f's definition.
But just having unrestricted eta
isn't enough for
practical compilation
that's because there
are some instances
where we intentionally
want to lower the arity
for a different behavior or
a better algorithmic complexity.
For example, we call f3 from before.
Its definition was conspicuously
written as an arity 1 function
just so that the expensive
computation of z
can be shared or used for
many different values of y.
But applying eta expansion,
which is now always allowed,
means that f3 has arity 2, not 1.
If we use a partial
application of f3 many times,
like mapping over a large list here,
it will recompute expensive
of 100 over and over.
That's bad.
We solve this problem
by adding another type
for representing explicit closures.
Here, we can note the closure
of a type with curly braces.
They're introduced with
the Clos constructor
and that lets us wrap up
a unary function from Int to Int
inside of a closure
of the same type.
Including closures in
the results of a function
let us intentionally
break up its arity
when partial applications matter
like in f3 prime.
This is an arity 1 function
taking the first argument
and returning a closure of
another arity 1 function,
that takes the second argument.
This closure is then later used
with an explicit App operation.
So, you can take the closure
we turned by f3 prime of 100
and then, apply it to the second
argument to get a result.
Now, the partial
application of f3 prime
computes expensive of 100 only once
even though the closure it
returns is reused many times.
But there's a subtle impact
of allowing all of these
extra eta expansions.
For example, consider
this definition -
defines a function f to the apparent
computation expensive of 100.
F is used several times
within its scope,
so when exactly is
expensive of 100 evaluated?
That depends on the evaluation
strategy of this let binding.
Under call-by-value,
the right-hand side expensive of 100
must be computed first before
a value can be bound to f.
Instead, under
call-by-need evaluation,
the right-hand side is evaluated
later only when f is first needed,
but its value is remembered
so it never gets re-evaluated
on future uses of f.
Slightly different is
call-by-name evaluation -
there the right-hand side is still
evaluated later when f is used
but it's also re-evaluated every
single time that f is used.
But remember, in this language,
eta expansion is always valid.
So, the definition of x above is
actually the same as x prime here.
But look at x prime,
the evaluation of f definitely
follows a call-by-name order
because the eta expanded right-hand
side is manifesting a value.
That means that expensive
100 will be recomputed
every single time f is called.
Therefore,
the operational consequence
of allowing unrestricted
eta for primitive functions
means that they cannot be evaluated
for any old reason
like in a strict
let binding here or the
seq operation in Haskell.
Primitive functions
can only be evaluated
when they are called with
all of their arguments.
When we link up the high level
notion of arity about eta expansion
with the low level notion about
simultaneous parameter passing,
we need to be careful
about polymorphism.
Consider this
polymorphic definition.
It takes a function f
that returns an arbitrary
type a and applies it twice.
This is done through
the local definition of g
which is the partial
application of f to 3.
Now, what are
the arities of f and g?
Well, I said we could just count
the arrows in the types so,
f's type has two arrows in it,
so it has arity 2.
And g's type is Int to
a, so it has arity 1.
This seems sensible at first,
but what happens when
the polymorphic a
gets instantiated with
a concrete type?
For example, a might be instantiated
with another function type
like Bool to Bool.
While when we do this, now f's
type suddenly has 3 arrows in it.
So, its arity has changed to 3
and g's type becomes
Int to Bool to Bool
so now, the arity is 2
instead of the original 1.
This is a big problem.
We want to be able to statically
compile a fu nction calls
as passing multiple arguments
and jumping to the code of the function.
If we look at the application
of g to 5 and g to 4,
how do we compile those calls?
If g's arity is 1, then this
is a complete function call.
But if it's arity
somehow becomes 2, then
there suddenly aren't
enough arguments
to correctly execute the body of g.
How can we possibly statially
compile multiargument function calls
when the arity of functions
isn't even stable?
These shortcomings can be
overcome with more polymorphism.
The idea is to encode
the intentional details of types
like the runtime representations
and calling conventions
into their kind.
First, we can generalize
the basic kind of types,
usually written as star, to
the more detailed form TYPE r c -
r stands for the runtime
representation of the type a.
It could be a primitive representation
like a pointer or an integer.
or it could be something
compound like an unboxed tuple.
C stands for
the calling convention of a
which spells out how those
values can be invoked.
So, for example if we have
an unknown type variable a,
we can give it a kind like
TYPE Pointer Call of n -
this says that the values
of type a are represented
as pointers at runtime
and that those values can be
called with n arguments.
Note that representing
the arity as a single number
is slightly simplified from
the full system in the paper
which presents all the details.
Now that the arity appears
explicitly in the types,
it can be used to
resolve the ambiguity
that came from polymorphism.
For example, let's return
to the troublesome poly
definition from before.
We can now pin down a specific arity
for the generic type variable
a introduced by the forall.
Here we say that the generic type
a is called with two arguments.
Even though that
the type of a is abstract,
it's kind makes it clear
that f has arity 4.
That's counting for the two
known integers in the type of f
plus two more from
the return type a.
Also, g has the type Int to a,
but we know it has arity 3,
so it takes one known
integer argument
plus two more arguments
from the return type a.
Furthermore, since the calling
convention appears in the types,
we can also abstract over them.
For example, the revapp function
here supplies an argument x
to a function f. Does
this type make sense?
The function f has the type a to b
and to generate the code for calling
f, we need to know its arity.
Since f takes an argument a
and b already has arity 1, this
adds up to an arity of 2.
The argument x has the type a.
To pass it around, we need
to know its representation.
The kind of a is TYPE Pointer c.
So, we know that x is
represented as a pointer,
but we don't know
the calling convention of x.
That's fine because revapp
doesn't call x itself,
it just passes x around.
If you found this talk interesting,
there is even more
material in the paper.
I was only able to talk
about calling conventions
and a little bit about
representations,
but we expressed levity
in this kind system too.
This lets us accommodate both eager
and lazy functional languages
with the exact same shared
intermediate language.
We also described
a compiler pipeline
along with its correctness from a
simple source language to
the intermediate language
and finally, to a low-level
target language.
This compilation depends
on types and kinds.
So, we used a type system to ensure
that static compilation
is always possible
for every single well type program.
In the end, we can say that kinds
give us a formal and high-level
language for capturing the details
of efficient calling
conventions for functions.
Thank you for your attention.
(AUDIENCE CLAPPING)
SUKYOUNG: Thank you Paul.
If you are watching this talk live,
please don't forget
about a Q&A session
that may be available
in your time band.
This is the last
paper in session six.
Thank you for attending.