ADAM CHLIPALA: Hello,
I'm Adam Chlipala,
Program Chair of ICFP 2020.
And it's my pleasure to kick off our
first session of contributed talks.
We're making these
available to the public on YouTube.
Though for those of you who've
registered for the conference,
you also have access to an
additional service called Clowdr,
which gives you a more
interactive experience.
So, if you're registering,
but you're not in Clowdr right now,
please head over there
and look for current
and upcoming talk titles
highlighted on the screen.
For instance, right now,
you should see stable relations
and abstract interpretation
for higher order programs
the very next talk. So, you can
click a talk title like that one,
and get the full
interactive experience,
including text chat
during the talk,
and a video Q&A with
the authors afterward.
Actually, you might find the
authors participating alongside you
in both of those because they
prerecorded their talk videos,
So, they can join
the text chat.
Not all authors are
joining the video Q&A
in both the New York and Asia
time bands that we're offering.
So, check Clowdr for links
to Q&A sessions that are happening.
If you don't see the
one you're interested
in for a talk that's playing
now then probably the authors
are on the other time band instead.
Alright, so, I'll remind you of some
of these details as we
progress through the session.
First up, we're going to have
Benoit Montagu telling us
about abstract interpretation
for higher order programs.
BENOIT MONTAGU: Hello, my name
is Benoit Montagu,
and I'm going to tell you about
joint work with Thomas Jensen
about the abstract interpretation
of high order programs.
The problem we're interested in is
the inference of program frames.
This means that
we want to detect
when a function call
does not change.
For imperative programs,
it amounts to finding
which parts of the global state
are not modified by a function call.
For functional programs,
it amounts to finding
which parts of the inputs
and the outputs are the same.
This frame information
can be used for example,
in optimizing compilers
to perform common
sub expression elimination
and across function calls.
The same information can also
be exploited in
program verification.
In particular, invariant preservation
proves the properties
of the parts
of the Other states
that have not changed
or indeed automatically preserved.
Last year, we published
a paper on what we call
correlation analysis.
It's a static analysis
that infers frames for,
for first order programs.
We applied it to the verification
of an OS micro-kernel.
And it was able
to prove automatically 68%
of the invariant
preservation lemmas.
This means that inferring frames
is really useful in practice.
In this work, we want
to extend the correlation analysis
to infer frames for
a higher order language.
Our long term goal is to
integrate such an analysis
in a general purpose
proof assistant
to make the verification
of large programs easier.
To infer frames
for the lambda calculus,
we follow the methodology
that is offered
by the abstract
interpretation framework.
The first step
is to clearly define
what property
you're interested in.
In this work,
we want to find relations
between the inputs
and the outputs of a lambda term.
The second step
of the methodology
is to define the collecting
semantics for your property.
It describes how
your property evolves
when your program
gets evaluated.
In this work, the collecting
semantics takes the form of
a denotation of a lambda term
into input-output relations.
We have proved that this
denotation is sound and complete,
and as a bonus,
you will find in the paper
an equivalent definition
in the form of a program logic.
The third and final step
of the abstract
interpretation methodology
is to apply successive abstractions
on the collecting semantics.
By doing so you obtain an analysis
with which you
can effectively compute.
In this work,
we have used two abstractions.
The first one is
a variant of a well known
independent attribute abstraction,
and the second one introduces
the correlation domain
represented last year,
that we extend to
support first class functions.
What we get in the end
is a simple modular analysis
that is already quite expressive.
And we have mechanically verified
all these results
in the Coq system.
The language we study
in the paper is the untyped call
by value lambda calculus
extended with pairs and binary sums.
The definition of values
in this language
is the standard one
and we use the standard
small step semantics
for call by value
that perform a substitution t,
to reduce a beta redex.
For this for this
higher order language,
we want to infer relations
between the inputs of programs
and the outputs.
But what are the inputs?
We consider the inputs
of a program
are the possible
substitutions sigma
that assign values to
the free variables
of that program.
Then the input output relation
of a term t
for a set of inputs I
is the set of pairs
made from substitutions drawn
from the set of inputs
and the values that are obtained
from evaluating
the term t sigma.
That is t where all its
free variables have been replaced
with the values defined
by the substitution sigma.
With the semantics
of input-output relations,
we can for instance state
that a term t always returns zero
when the input x
is assigned to a negative value
or that t returns a value
that remains above
the value of the input x.
Now, we remark that if sigma
might define all the inputs
of a program t,
then you can use
any substitution sigma prime
that defines more inputs,
even some inputs that are
not necessary to t
without changing the meaning
of the program t.
In such a case, we say
that sigma prime
extends sigma.
And because specifying
values for more inputs
than necessary does not change
the meaning of a program
We can actually close
the set of inputs I
under the extension
ordering of substitutions
and by doing so,
the input-output relation
of the term
becomes what we call
a stable relation.
A relation is stable
when if an input
substitution sigma
related to similar
is related to some input v,
then any substitution
that is more defined
than sigma must also
be related to the same value v.
This definition should not
surprise the logicians among you,
what we call stability is similar
to the notion of persistence
that is seen
in Kripke-style semantics.
That is to say, if a property
holds in some world
it will it must also hold
in any larger world.
And the definition should be
no surprise to the semanticists
among you either because
a stable relation is in fact
a monotone function
from substitutions
ordered with
the extension ordering
to sets of values
ordered with set inclusion.
So we have defined
in the paper a denotation
that's given a term t
and environment E
builds a stable relation
between the inputs
and the outputs of t,
the environment denotes
a set of admissible inputs.
And as expected
in denotational semantics
the denotation function
is defined in a compositional way
by induction over
the syntax of the program.
For example, the denotation
of a program that builds
a pair out of
two sub programs t1 and t2
is the pairing of their denotations.
Here the pairing
of relations relates
an input sigma
to a pair of values,
where the first component
of that value is related
to the input using
the denotation of t1
and the second component
of the value is related
to the same input
using the denotation of t2.
We have proved that
this denotation is sound
with respect to
the input-output in the sense
that it is an overall approximation
of the input-output relation
This means that if you take
an input substitution sigma
in the set of valid inputs
described by the environment,
and if the evaluation
of the program t
with these inputs
gives you an output value v,
then the input-output pair
(sigma, v) is predicatively
in the denotation
of the program.
Interestingly, the denotation
we have defined is also complete.
This means that
the denotation
of the input-output relation
are the same.
We have mechanically
verified these results
in the Coq proof systems...
A denotation must treat
variables very carefully
and here is why.
You should expect
that the denotation
of a variable is just a lookup
for the variable in the environment.
This is indeed
a correct over-approximation
Within the paper we give
a sound and complete definition.
Here it is. I will not
explain all the details,
but just notice that the definition
uses a relation self (x).
This relation states that
the output must be exactly
what was given
as input for the variable x.
In particular, this means that
the denotation of the variable x
is a relation in which
the variable x occurs.
In other words,
the denotation of a term
may involve
the names of its inputs.
This means that
the semantic denotations
can refer to syntactic variables.
This has consequences
on the well-formedness,
of the definition,
you need to show for example,
that the free variables
of your denotations
are included in the variables
that are defined
by the environment.
But what does it even mean
to be a free variable
for a relation?
Relations are semantic objects
not pieces of syntax.
And to answer this question
We use nominal techniques
to carefully handle names.
If you want to dive
into the details, please
have a look at the paper.
Now how do we
handle functions?
Let's start with
function application.
The denotation of t1
applied to t2
is the app
of the denotations.
This is a relation
where,when you take values
in the denotations of t1 and t2
and apply them together,
you must obtain
a term that evaluates to a value v.
And this result value v
must be the value
in the final denotation.
That's it for applications.
Now for functions,
I won't have time to show you
the full definition
of the denotation
but you should remember that
it can be over approximated
by a relation that
assuming some condition
on the arguments,
gives you the denotation
of the functions body.
Here is the unfolded definition
where I have chosen to hide
some pieces related
to name management.
Let's go through it.
This is a relation where the output
is supposed to be a function
for which we will consider
all possible applications.
When we apply this function
to an argument v1
that satisfies the condition R,
if the evaluation
gives a result v2, then v2
must be in the denotation
of the function body.
But the arguments
and results must be valid
for all possible extensions
of the input substitutions,
as is usually from
the in Kripke style semantics.
And this is essential
because this quantification
of our extensions
of the inputs is the reason
that makes definition
a stable relation. In the end,
we have a modular
denotation rule for functions
that we later use
as a basis for
the modular analysis of functions.
So we have
defined this denotation
is collecting semantics
that describes exactly
the input output
behavior of programs.
And we use it as a starting point
to build a static analysis.
So following the abstract
interpretation methodology,
we applied successive
abstraction steps.
So far our denotation
tells us how the inputs
are related to the outputs globally.
We first apply a invariant
of the independent
attribute abstraction,
working at this point
what we call point-wise relations,
that, that tell us how each input
is independently related
to the output.
For each input x,
we obtain a binary relation
on values, that says
how sigma of x is related
to the output v.
Then, we abstract
these binary relations on values
into an abstract domain
that we call correlations,
and with which
we can effectively compute.
This abstract domain
is an extension
of the correlation of subdomain
from our previous work
that we extended
with first class functions.
You will find plenty of details
on how we did this in the...
...paper.
We implemented the resulting
analysis in OCaml.
This is a bottom-up modular analyzer
that analyses functions only once.
For every function, it
computes a function summary
that approximates the extensional
behavior of that function.
The analysis was really not
designed to compete with
existing control flow analysis
and it does not compete.
Still, it can give
very precise results
even though it follows
a fully modular approach.
Let's consider this
classic CFA example.
This program calls
the identity function twice
on two different arguments and returns
the result of one of the calls.
It's an example where 0-CFA
is not precise enough
and 1-CFA is required to
achieve good precision.
The analyzer first computes
a summary for the identity function.
The summary tells us
that this is a function
whose result is equal to its argument
whatever is the calling context.
This summary is instantiated
once for the first application.
We get that y1 must be bound
to the first injection.
Then, the summary is
instantiated the second time
for the second application and
the analysis tells us that y2 must
be bound to the second injection.
Finally, the analysis
for the results
is the domain we have
obtained for y1,
that is to say it has to
be the first injection.
On this example, we can
see that the analysis
gives the most precise results
and is on par with 1-CFA.
To wrap up, we have defined
solid foundations for the
relational analysis of
higher-order programs
by means of a sound
and complete relational semantics
for the lambda calculus.
We exploited this collecting semantics
to design an effective analysis
and we provide an artifact
for the Coq formalization
of the theoretical development.
As a long-term goal, we would
like to integrate such analysis
with a proof assistant to
reduce the proof efforts
for the verification of
large programs.
On the shorter term, we want to
support more language features
and to increase
the precision of the analysis,
for example by exploiting
numeric abstract domains.
Finally, we are convinced
that our denotational semantics
can serve as a basis
for the future design
of novel relational
control flow analysis.
That's all. Thank you for watching.
(AUDIENCE CLAP)
ADAM: Thanks Benoit.
If you're watching in
the New York time band,
you should now see a link
appear in Clowdr
to join a video chat where you
can ask Benoit questions.
Unfortunately, he is not
available in the Asia time band.
OK. Let's get started
with the next talk.
We have Scott Smith on symbolic
evaluation of functional languages.
SCOTT SMITH: Welcome to our talk on
Higher-Order Demand-Driven
Symbolic Evaluation.
Let's parse this title a bit.
Particularly, what is
meant by demand-driven?
Demand-driven means goal-directed.
So, rather than working forward,
we're going to start with
a goal and work backward.
And this is well-known from logic
programming and tactic-based provers
where it's clear where your goal is.
And so, it's best to start from
that goal and work backward
rather than trying to forward-chain,
although, sometimes
forward-chain is good,
generally you're... shooting
in the dark a lot of times
and you're very far
away from your target.
So, goal-directed is
clearly a win there
and it's the common approach.
Now, if we look at program analysis,
symbolic executors and interpreters,
it's more the opposite
that tends to be...
You don't have a
fixed narrow
goal in this space.
It tends to be one around
the whole program in all these cases.
So, they tend to be forward.
But there are some cases when
demand is useful
if we have a particular
part of the program you want to
get a very accurate result on
and a
demand program analysis
could be effective
and you don't have to go
through all the work
on the whole program.
And so, Reps and collaborators wrote
a series of influential papers
doing this in
the imperative language space
and there have been a few efforts
in the functional space -
one is DDPA which is our work,
so, there are bends on functional
demand
program analysis. And in
the symbolic execution
space, snugglebug is an imperative
demand symbolic executor
and this paper is basically
about filling in this box
with DDSE which is our functional
demand symbolic executor.
And to do a functional
demand symbolic executor,
we need an interpreter which is demand
in which we're going to symbolize.
And so, we're also going to present
DDI which is a new notion
of functional interpreter and
it is novel and has no substitution,
environment or closures
because you can't...
These data structures are built
on the forward direction
and we're not running forward.
And so, the interpreter itself
is pretty interesting.
And so, the outline of the talk
is we're going to briefly talk
about the language syntax.
Then, we're going to do
this, novel interpreter.
And then, we're going to show
how it can be generalized
to a symbolic evaluator.
And then, we're going to look at
our implementation very briefly.
So, the syntax we have is
pretty standard, very simple,
functional language in our theory.
And we're going to have input because
the way we're going to test
our symbolic evaluators
is we're going to find
inputs for each particular
line of the program
and that's sort of our concrete
goal to show that the method works.
And recursion is this
encoded via self-passing
and the implementation also
has additional features
such as recursive data structures.
And the syntax we
use is A-normal Form
and this is an example
and you can see in A-normal Form,
every operator
the components are all atomic
and this exposes the order
which is very useful because
we're going to be running
programs backwards.
So, reading right to
left is very handy
to know the order more explicitly.
And also, variable names are unique.
So, here we have x, y and ret.
And those serve as
the program points because
they're unique.
So, there's...
We'll use that to name
points in a program.
So,
the main function we want to
find is a lookup function.
And the lookup function, we want
to find the value of a variable.
So, that's the variable
we want to lookup.
That's the point at which we want to
start in the program to look it up.
And this one parameter, we'll talk
more about, is the call stack
which we use to disambiguate
different activations
and the final result is a v.
(CLEARS THROAT)
So, yes, this is the program point.
Call stack.
In general, this is
going to be a list,
but for now, we're just
covering the case
where it's a singleton.
And the idea is we're just going to
walk back through the program,
define the variable
as the intuition.
So, here the variable y, if we
actually add this definition,
it's axiomatic that the value is 1,
but if we're down here
at this line f1...
So, remember the line we're
looking up from the program point.
So, define y. This y, we basically
can search back up through here
and we'll find it up here.
And more interesting if we're in
for example, this variable x here,
the only way we're going to
reach that is that via call
from one of these call sites.
And here, this disambiguates
which call we took.
So, we're in the call f1.
That's how we got there.
And we are pretty clear
if we're looking up x.
From the call f1, x is
the argument passed in as y
and then, we can look up
y and in turn get 1.
So, 1 is result of that.
So, let's go through that in detail
how we traced that call.
So, a little more about how
the actual lookup function works.
And so, to lookup f1,
at this point, we know that it's
the return result of the function f.
So, it suffices to lookup
the return variable fret in that code
at the last line of
code which is fret.
So, we're looking up from
the point that we're pointing to
and we're looking up that variable
and the value is immediately
there. It's right in front of us.
And by the way, we have
pushed a call frame
because we're in this
call. So, f1 means the
the call frame that we're
in on the call stack.
And so, it suffices
for fret, clearly, it's x+1.
So, I get is lookup x and add
1 to it and have our results.
So, we're going to lookup x.
That's the underlying lookup.
So, looking up x
from the top of the function,
at this point now it's pretty clear
that since we came
in via the call f1,
we know that we came
in this call here
and the parameter y is
what gets passed to x.
So, just look up x, it
suffices to look up y
from the top of
the program, the empty stack
and that pretty
clearly is going to be 1.
And the final result
is 1+1 which is 2.
So, that's a simple lookup.
And a little more complicated case
is if we have non-local variables.
And here's a simple example of
a curried addition function
and let's start in
the middle of this look up.
So, we want to lookup the value of x.
And this is the tricky case
because it's a non-local variable.
This is defined all the way out here
and the way we got that - the way
we're actually going to run this code
if we get the program, it's going to
be from this call site here
because first, we got 5 for x
and 1 for y and then, we're going to
do this call, in which
case we're in this code.
So, that means that we
had to have come in
via this call site,
ret call site here. So, this
is an example of where we
could have gotten to
you know, lookup from the end
of the program for example.
And so, we're at that line
here gyret, its definition
we want to find the value of x.
So, how do we do?
Well, x is not in scope but
the principle of lexical scoping
is the function we are running
i.e. this function here,
gret, we know that the
x variable must have been in scope
when that function was defined
as you can see.
It's in scope at
the function definition point.
And so, what we do is we know that
that function is the value of g5
because that's
the function we called -
this is the call site
we came from, ret
and that function g5
is called. So, the...
What we do is we write
a lookup like this which means
let's first look for
the function definition
for g5's code is
and then, pop up that off
and resume a lookup for x.
And we should find it in that point.
So, let's do that.
(CLEARS THROAT)
So, define g5, in fact is
the return result of this call.
So, we want to pop into g
body and look for gret
which will be the value of g5.
So, to look up g5, it suffices to
look at gret from within this call
at this line.
So, let's do that and to define
define gret,
well, it's right
there - we found it.
It's the last line
of
the
code. So, all we have to do now
is
to pop
this frame of a stack and
resume looking up for
x and look, we win,
x is within scope now.
So, in fact, it should be very
easy to find the value of x.
It in fact is the parameter
at the call site g5
which in fact is 5.
So, that's the answer.
And so, in general, the lookup,
if we have higher
and higher order functions,
this list can grow longer and longer
but this is the full general
signature of our lookup.
So, it has two lists of
variables basically
and that's all of the
structure of this interpreter.
And here are the full rules.
You can see there's...
It's a lot more complicated
than the pure lambda calculus.
So, there are a lot of subtleties
here but that's fit on the slide
so it's not hopelessly complex.
So, let's now look at how we make
a symbolic version of this.
So, it's very similar parameters
and instead of returning a value,
you're returning a variable
which in then in the constraints,
we also have the constraints set
and that is we're going to
constrain that variable
to have some properties
(CLEARS THROAT)
which we can then use
an SMT solver to find
an actual solution for...
And so, yeah, so this S here
means the symbolic version
of lookups.
So, let's run that on the same example,
the same lookup of f1's value.
So, we go into fret
and look up fret's value
and we can immediately see
it's right there. It's x+1.
So, actually, this time we're
going to return a variable
and remember variables are
indexed by the call stack.
So, this variable's indexed by
f1 in this case,
'cause that's how we came
into this function.
So that's in fact
the result of the lookup.
So we've done
the result of looking up,
but additionally, we have a constraint
which requires this variable
to have the value of whatever
x's lookup is plus one.
And remember this lookup here is
in turn going to return a variable.
So let's proceed with that
lookup and see what it returns.
So to lookup x from this point here,
it suffices to look up the parameter
of the call site, that call site was f1,
so the parameter is y
so it suffices to look up y
and if we see, if we go up, we see
y is up at the top of the program.
It's in fact an input.
So this is, by the way,
use of the input syntax
and inputs are unconstrained because
there's, they could be arbitrary.
And so in the symbolic execution,
we just return the variable
with no added constraints.
So that means that
the final constraint set
is that this fret equals
this lookup here,
which returned just the value
y in the empty stack plus one
so we get that.
That's the only constraint on
this very simple example.
And it's clear there are many
satisfiable solutions to it.
So that's an example of
a symbolic execution.
So in the paper, we make
a formal operational semantics
for all these systems.
And the main result we prove
the most difficult result
is that a backward running
demand operational semantics,
this lookup operation
is in fact isomorphic
to a forward running
operational semantics.
And it's a delicate proof
because they're running
in opposite directions.
And we also proved that the symbolic
evaluator is sound and complete
with respect to
the operational semantics.
And a few subtle details that we
have to skip because of time
is that the call stack, when
we're starting in the middle,
we really want to
start in the middle
'cause that's what
domain lookup means.
We want to start from any
point and you might not,
you will have no idea if the call
stack when you start that run
and we may need to
incrementally infer
where the call stack is as we go.
And also input will not come
in their forward order
when we're doing a reverse lookup
and we need to basically do
a sorting operation on the input
and that's all in the paper.
So for implementation, the artifact
we produce is a test generator.
So given a program
and a target line,
we will find inputs which reach
that target line of code.
And we have an initial proof-of-concept
implementation in OCaml.
And in order to make
it usable at all,
we have to dovetail on all
the different search paths,
or we get lost down
some infinite path.
And so we use a coroutine
non-determinism monad for that purpose.
And just to test it
out a little bit,
there is a paper that has
a forward symbolic evaluator in it,
and we basically solve
the benchmarks from that paper
just sort of as a test to make
sure our system is reasonable.
And to compare very
briefly with related work,
so snugglebug is an imperative
demand symbolic executer.
The Cruanes work that
we just mentioned
is a forward functional
symbolic executer.
And it also has restrictions.
For example, all functions
have to be total
which we don't have in our system.
And Rosette is another forward
symbolic execution framework.
And it has some restrictions on
data types not being
arbitrarily sized.
And our work has,
it's the first that we know of demand
functional symbolic evaluator,
and it has no restrictions
on datatypes or recursion,
and we've proven it sound
and complete. Thank you.
(APPLAUSE)
ADAM: Thanks, Scott.
In either time band, you should
see a link appearing in Cloud
or to join a live Q&A session with
at least one of the authors.
Alright, next up is Kazutaka Matsuda
on A language for partially
invertible computations.
KAZUTAKA MATSUDA: Hello, I'm Kazutaka
Matsuda from Tohoku University.
Today I'd like to introduce our
new programming language, SPARCL,
which is a language for partially
invertible computation.
SPARCL is named after a system for
partially invertible computation
with linear types.
Let us start with a background:
Invertible Programming.
Invertibility is a common
and important concept
in software development.
For example, we have
compression and decompression.
We have undoing and redoing.
We have serialization
and deserialization.
Invertible programming
is a way to provide
correctness by construction.
Then natural question arises.
For normal programming the basic
building blocks are functions,
but for invertible programming, what
should be the building blocks?
Our obvious approach is to use
invertible function for
invertible programming.
However, this approach
is restrictive
because invertible functions
have to be injective,
but it is known that some
functions become invertible
after fixing some argument.
These functions are called
partially invertible functions.
An example of a partially invertible
function is an addition,
which becomes invertible after
fixing either of the arguments.
A more practical example of
a partial invertible function
is Huffman encoding,
which becomes invertible after
fixing Huffman encoding table.
And saying, a question is,
is it possible to do
invertible programming
through a partially-invertible
programming?
If so, what is a language for
partially-invertible programming?
This paper answer to this question.
With designer SPARCL,
which is a programming language
for writing invertible functions
through composing
partially-invertible function.
This is because
partially-invertible functions
are more natural and more expressive.
SPARCL uses linear types,
which is a key to
correctness by construction.
Let us start with an example
to explain the problem
and solution in more detail.
Consider a function
that compute difference
of adjacent element in a list.
Starting from zero, this function
repeatedly compute a difference
from a previous element.
For example, the difference
between one and zero is one,
so it output one.
And the difference between two
and one is one, so it output one.
The different between
five and two is three,
so it outputs three and so on.
This is very simple
function, but indeed useful.
Actually, a variant of this
function can be used
as a pre-processing for image
compression, as found in PNG.
The standard unidirectional
implementation
of this transformation
looks like this.
The subs take a list of int
and returns a list of int.
This function calls go with
additional arguments zero
which intuitively represent
a previous element.
Go takes int and a list of int
and returns a list of int.
If you apply go into the empty
list, it returns an empty list.
If you apply go into x
cons xs, it outputs x-n
and recurs it over x and xs.
Here, we have some observation
about invertibility of subs.
First of all, subs
itself is invertible.
Actually, we can recover
the original input from this result
by using a cumulative summation.
For example, sum of
this elements is one
and sum of these two
elements is two.
Sum of these three elements
is five and so on.
However, go, sorry.
However, subs itself is,
subs does not consist only
of invertible functions.
In fact, go is not invertible
but partially-invertible.
Specifically go n becomes invertible
for any fixed or a static n.
This means that we
need to care about
partial invertibility
in programming go.
This example also illustrates
a challenge in partial
invertible programming,
that is, dynamic data flow
into a static position.
Here, we highlight
the dynamic part with blue.
Here, x, which is dynamic,
flows into the first argument
go, which is static,
because that go becomes invertible
after fixing its first argument.
To overcome the situation,
we propose a SPARCL a language for
partially-invertible computation.
SPARCL comes with linear
types and invertible types.
Invertible types denoted
by A superscript R.
Intuitively it means A-typed values
that has to be handled
only in invertible ways.
Thanks to invertible types,
invertible functions are represented
as ordinary linear functions
between invertible types
in SPARCL like this.
This representation provide
a unified framework
for describing invertible
and partial invertible function.
For example, here we showed
the types of subs and go in SPARCL.
Because subs is invertible function.
In SPARCL subs take invertible list of int
and it returns an invertible list of int.
Because that go is
a partially-invertible function,
which becomes invertible after
fixing its first argument.
Int SPARCL go takes
ordinary int and a list,
invertible list of int
and returns a invertible list of int.
SPARCL also provides a pin operator
to bridge invertible
and ordinary worlds.
By using pin operator,
we can convert invertible
values into ordinary values
locally in this continuation.
Recall that it sometimes
happens that dynamic data flow
into static position,
which is a challenge in
partially-invertible programming.
This pin operator is
a remedy for this situation.
Let us start with
very simple example
to explain programming
basics in SPARCL.
SPARCL is a linear typed, higher-order
functional programming language,
only the special thing is
that it has invertible types.
Here we explain how we handle
values of invertible types.
Here is a partial invertible
addition written in SPARCL.
This definition is very similar to
the standard unidirectional version.
But here our function takes
ordinary natural number
and invertible natural number
and returns an invertible
natural number
to highlight its
partial invertibility.
To construct invertible
natural number
instead of using
ordinary constructors,
we use lifted constructors,
such as S superscript R.
Here, which shows
the partially-invertible multiplication
defined in SPARCL.
Multiplication is similar
to the sub add function,
takes natural numbers,
and invertible natural numbers
and return invertible
natural number.
Unlike the add function,
the mul function uses case analysis
of invertible natural numbers.
To do so, it uses
invertible branching
indicated by invertible
patterns like Z superscript R
and S y superscript R.
A special thing in
invertible branching
is a branch comes with condition.
This with conditions are using SPARCL
direction to determine branches
but we do not describe
the details in this talk.
Now we are ready to show how
we program subs in SPARCL.
Because subs is a function
that computes the values
of adjacent element in a list.
For comparison, we'll also show
the standard unidirectional
definition of subs in Haskell.
So definition of the two
programs look very similar
except the use of constructs
that care about Invertibility.
Subs in SPARCL take
an invertible list of INT
and return invertible list of INT.
Surprisingly the right hand side
of the SPARCL function sub
is identical to
unidirectional version.
The go in SPARCL takes ordinary INT
and invertible list of INT
and returns invertible list of INT.
To manipulate invertible
list INT, the go function
uses lifted constructors
and invertible branching.
The most important part
in the definition is
that it uses the pin operator.
By using the pin operator, we
convert x of type invertible INT
into z of type ordinary INT.
Thanks to this conversion, we
can call go for z and xs.
Because that's
the first argument of go,
expect INT instead
of invertible INT.
We say again that two
programs look very similar.
In this, they have
the same recursive structure.
This is a strength of
SPARCL compared with
existing reversible languages.
Once we have defined
invertible function,
we can use it by using
the forward and backward functions.
Here fwd is a function
that runs an invertible function
in the forward direction.
And bwd that the opposite.
For example, if we apply
fwd subs to this list,
we will obtain this result.
And if we apply, bwd
subs to this list,
we will obtain
the original list again.
Indeed, our pair of fwd subs
and bwd subs forms a bijection.
This is what SPARCL guarantees.
This is a brief
introduction to SPARCL.
But in our paper, we...
we discussed more things.
For example, we defined
the class system
lambda PI arrow of SPARCL.
Now lambda PI arrow is
based on linear calculus,
and lambda q arrow features
a class system of linear Haskell.
So the design of lambda
PI arrow is also
inspired by two-staged languages.
We shall see some formal properties
about lambda PI arrow
including type
safety and bijectivity.
We'll also discuss larger
examples including Huffman encoding
and calculation of developed
native tree rebuilding
from in order and
preorder traversal.
Let us discuss some of related work.
These are some existing research
concerning partial invertibility.
In program transformation,
there's an inversion method
called partial, impartial
and semi-inversion.
Also there are some reverse
programming languages
that support a limited form of
partial invertibility.
The design of SPARCL is inspired
by our previous work HOBiT.
HOBiT is a higher-order
bidirectional programming language
in which lenses are already
presented as ordinary function.
More specifically
Lens between S and T
is represented as an ordinary
function between B S and B T.
Here, B S and B T are
very similar to invertible
types in SPARCL.
But HOBiT does not use linear types
and it does not provide
a pin operator,
which is very useful in partially
invertible programming.
Let us conclude our talk.
We designed SPARCL,
a programming language
for writing invertible functions
through composing
partially-invertible functions.
Because partially-invertible
functions
are more natural
and more expressive.
SPARCL uses linear types,
which is the key to
correctness by construction.
Thank you.
(APPLAUSE)
ADAM: Thanks Kazutaka.
In either time band,
you should see a Q&A
link appear in Clowdr
that brings you to a video chat,
where you can ask
Kazutaka your questions.
Welcome back for a talk
by Aymeric Fromherz
on Concurrent Separation Logic
in the F* Programming Language.
AYMERIC FROMHERZ: Hi. I'm Aymeric
and it's my pleasure to be here
today to present our work on,
SteelCore: An Extensible
Concurrent Separation Logic
for Effectful Dependent Programs.
Our goal in this work is to
verify concurrent programs.
And there has been
lots of recent work
on this topic,
especially on using Concurrent
Separation Logic (CSL)
for verification.
But our main success stories
is the Iris project,
which provides a comprehensive
expressive logic
to reason about
concurrent programs.
Unfortunately, it only
applies to deeply embedded,
simply-typed languages and we
really do enjoy dependent types.
We really do enjoy, for instance,
the use in type theory based proof assistants,
which allow us to combine
modular reasoning
with strong abstractions
and strong specifications.
So one question, we
asked ourselves is
how could we get
a Concurrent Separation Logic
for a dependently-typed language?
Could, for instance,
a shallow embedding work?
But it comes with
certain challenges.
The first one is how do
we actually reflect
the effect of concurrency in
our dependently-typed language?
The second is how do we
support partial correctness,
which is needed when
reasoning with programs
that might have deadlocks
and that might not terminate?
And lastly, IRIS provides this
very convenient feature
to reason about
concurrent programs
called dynamically
allocated invariants.
How do we support these things
in a dependently-typed language?
And I'll come back to
that a bit later.
To verify concurrent programs, we've
been developing
a framework called Steel,
which is a concurrency
version, which is DSL for F*,
an effectful dependently-typed
language designed for verification.
And in this talk, I'm going to
talk especially about Steel core,
which consists of the core
semantics and program logic
of the Steel framework.
So at the very bottom
of Steelcore,
we have a model of computations
using action trees.
And these action trees are
characterized by state typeclass,
which abstracts memory as well
the structure of the separation logic.
And for these action
trees, we provide
an intrinsically typed
definitional interpreter.
And one of the interesting
things about how we get
intrinsically typed here
is that this allows us to,
reasonably to prove
a soundness of our semantics,
without having to rely on
explicit execution traces.
We then instantiate
this state typeclass
of a rich Concurrent
Separation Logic.
That we're going to talk about
more in detail later.
And that provides the basis for
our program logic in Steel.
And finally, on top of that,
on top of this program logic
we can implement dependently-typed,
verified libraries.
Let's have a look at how these
different components work,
starting with our core semantics.
The first step is to define
our state typeclass.
What this typeclass contains
is first the type for memory
and second the type for separation
logic assertions slprop.
As well as, operators
which form a commutative monoid structure.
And lastly, we need to
find a way to interpret
the separation logic
assertion in a given memory.
That is, to decide whether
the separation logic assertion
holds or not in a given memory,
which is this intrep function.
Once this is done, we
can encode computations
as action trees parameterized
by our state typeclass.
These action trees are
indexed by prefix.
First, the written type a,
which is the type of values
returned by the computation.
Second, a precondition
pre as a slprop
and lastly, a postcondition post,
which is a separation
logic assertion
dependent on the value returned by the computation.
We can then encode
computations in a way
that is reminiscent of free monads.
First, we have two standard nodes.
Ret, which returns a value
and Act, which corresponds
to atomic actions
seen as computations.
We can then define composition
of the computations
as a node Bind.
And notice here, how
the indices of the computations
capture the standard rule
of separation logic.
The first condition q of
the first computation
actually corresponds to the precondition
of the second computation.
And another very
interesting thing here
is to look at the type of
this continuation of
the second computation.
We can see here this Dv effect,
which is a primitive effect
in F* for diversions.
What this means is that,
in this composition,
we are actually encoding
positive divergence,
possibly non-terminating
computations.
Lastly, we can define the node
Par for structured parallelism.
The Par role is stand out in
concurrent separation logic.
And observe again, how
the indices of our computations
capture this classic role.
Assuming that
the preconditions p and p prime,
offered to computations
are disjoint,
then it can safely execute with
computations in parallel.
Finally, returning the star of
the first conditions q and q prime.
Building upon these action trees,
we implement an intrinsically-typed
definitional interpreter
that non-deterministically
interleaves atomic actions.
This interpreter run has
the computation type NST.
NST corresponds to
non-deterministic stateful
possibly divergent computations.
And what's interesting here is that
the type of
the interpreter encapsulates
the soundness statement
about those semantics.
If we initially have
the validity of the precondition p
in our initial memory m,
then after execution, we do
have that the postcondition q
is valid in the final memory of m1.
And here, all this is done in
a partial-correctness setting
because NST can model possible
diversions computations.
No that we have a generic semantics,
we need to instantiate
a state typeclass
to provide a program logic.
The first step is to
instantiate the memory type.
And for this, we're going to
remain standard
and consider memory to be the map
from abstract addresses
to typed references.
We can then instantiate
our separation logic.
And the first step is to provide
standard separation logic connectives,
such as star, magic wand,
conjunction, quantification and so on.
But we're also providing
points to assertions,
which are indexed by Partial
Commutative Monoids.
Partial Commutative
Monoids have been
studied extensively in the literature,
and used to encode
a variety of things
such as, for instance,
sharing disciplines.
And lastly, they often provide
dynamically allocated invariants
associated to separate
logic assertions.
And that's what I will present next.
We'll consider named invariants,
where the name will be encoded
as a natural number.
And we will also have
this proposition,
which is here, this squiggly arrow,
which states that a specific name
is associated to one specific
separation logic assertion p.
And so it still a named invariant
is going to be association of
a name with this refinement,
that it's name is actually
associated to one specific
separation logic assertion.
And what's interesting here is that
these invariants are just values.
And as such, they are
freely duplicable
and they can be shared
easily between threads.
Now to dynamically allocate
invariants in Steel,
we provide this function
new invariant,
which takes as an invariant
separation logic assertion p.
This function has the computational
type Steel,
which reflects the computation
that we encoded as action trees.
You can see here that
the indices of the Steel effect
corresponds to the indices
of all action trees.
First index is the type
returned by the computation,
which is here an invariant
associated to P.
And it has a precondition that
initially we need ownership,
we need the validity of
the separation logic assertion P.
After execution of the function
and creation of invariant,
we do not have access to
this resource anymore,
it has been successfully locked
away behind the invariant.
Implementing this function was
one of the main technical
difficulties in Steel.
The code is actually fairly involved
and relies on things like
monotonic state.
If you're interested, I invite
you to go read the paper.
Now that we defined invariants in
Steel, where do we actually use them?
The core idea of an invariant is
that it has to hold at all times.
And because of that, only atomic
commands can access invariants
as long as I restore
them after execution.
So, what is atomic
commands in Steel?
Well, first of all atomic
actions are atomic commands,
but their possible composition
with ghost computations
is also considered to be
an atomic command because
these ghost computations are
computationally irrelevant,
they will not be actually executed,
and hence they can safely
be considered atomic.
And to separate atomic computations
from regular Steel programs,
we define a new effect SteelAtomic
as the effect of the Steel effect.
And you can see it has many
similarities with the Steel effect.
It still has original type A
as well as the precondition
p and postcondition q.
But it also has the additional
index is_ghost which indicates
whether the computation
is ghost or not
and allow safe composition
of atomic commands.
It also has an additional index
that I'll omit for now.
Now that we have this effect, we
can define an invariant handler
which takes an argument
an invariant I associated to an slprop P
and a function F.
And what this handler says that
if F is an atomic function,
which accesses p, but
stores it after execution,
then you can safely open
the invariant execute F
and then close the invariant again.
And because of that, we
can give a signature
that does not involve p in
specification.
In practice, the last index
of the Steel effect I was mentioning,
is a set of currently
open invariants
in the sense that in
the invariants are applicable,
The separation track assertions
that they protect might not be
so opening an invariant
several times
might actually lead to unsoundness.
And so that's what's
SteelCore consists of.
We provided two effects
Steel and SteelAtomic,
which reflect
the effects of concurrency
as defined by our
semantics in F*.
And then on top of this, we
instantiated a program logic
with a memory and original
separation logic
containing standard connectors,
as well as a PCM based
memory model and invariance.
And we also provide a variety of
actions such as, for instance,
an atomic compare and swap, which
allows us to operate on memory.
Now, we can actually use this to
framework to implement verified
dependently type libraries
such as, for instance,
the library for SpinLock,
and there is no reason to stop here
on top of SpinLock, we can
use the SpinLock interface
to implement new libraries
such as, for instance,
a library for ForkJoin operations,
or a library for channel types.
Channel types are a lightweight
version of session types.
The idea is that to each channel,
we're going to associate
one protocol P.
And we're also going to provide
two separation logic assertions
sender and receiver
to reason about these channels.
Using the separation logic assertions,
we can then specify
and implement a send function,
which will take as arguments for
channel C associated to protocol P
as well as message x,
which is compatible
with the current
state of a protocol.
And so what the signature of
this function states is that
if we initially have send
permission on this channel C,
and the channel is
currently as a stage where
it currently needs to be executed, then
we can indeed send this message.
And we then get a send
permission on this channel,
where the protocol advanced
one step after executing x.
And so we can define
the dual version of this,
which would be a receive function.
Using this library, we can
now specify and implement
dependently type protocols
such as, for instance,
the simple PingPong protocol.
What this protocol says is that
we are first expected to send
an integer on a channel
and then we're going to
receive a new integer
which is ensured to be strictly
greater than the one we sent.
So, this is the specification
of our protocol.
And we can now implement
the client version of his protocol
that takes as argument a channel
which is ensured to follow
PingPong protocol.
So, we first send
a message on the channel,
which we hear p to be 17. We
then received a new integer.
And since the channel is
expected to follow protocol,
we can prove that this integer
is actually strictly greater
than the one we sent
which here is 17.
And what's really interesting is
that all of this verification
is done here statically by
virtue of type checking.
If we're for instance to start
our client implementation
by trying to receive a message,
verification will fail because
the protocol states that
the first action has to be send.
To conclude in this talk,
I presented the core semantics
and prognostic of steel
the shallow embedding of
concurrent separation logic in F*
with dependent-typed language.
A Steel Program logic has
a member model which is based
on partial commutative monoids
and it also enables
concurrent reasoning
through dynamically
allocated invariants.
All of our development
is mechanized in about
11,000 lines of code in F*.
And it comes with a stack
of verified libraries,
which is growing every day.
Our hope with the Steel framework
is to provide
a full-fledged dependently
type programming language,
which would be useful for verified
concurrent
and distributed programming.
All of this being built on
top of a lower memory model.
And with an extensible program
logic which is expressed in
an embedded way in F*.
During this talk, there are many details
of our work I didn't mention.
First of all our semantics
actually much more complicated
to enable support for also reasoning
in a style akin to
Implicit Dynamic Frames
on top of separation logic.
Second, we also allow
reasoning on references,
using monotonicity and preorders.
And lastly, we provide
several more libraries.
First of all, we provide
the SpinLocks and functional
libraries that I mentioned.
And we also model
lock coupling lists,
as well as counters with
local states using
closures over slprop. if you're interested
by any of these things,
I invite you to go read the paper.
Thank you for your attention.
ADAM: Thanks, Aymeric.
In either time band, you should
see a Q&A link appear in Clowdr
taking you to a video
chat with at least
one of the authors of this paper.
OK, let's jump into
a talk by Mohsen Lesani.
on compositional verification
of distributed systems.
MOHSEN LESANI: Good morning.
I'm going to talk about TLC,
temporal logic of distributed
components. I am Mohsen Lesani,
an assistant professor at
the University of California Riverside.
My student Jeremiah Griffin
that is actively working
on the Coq framework is
present in the conference.
The other students that helped me
are Narges Shadab and Xizhe Yin.
Distributed systems are critical to
reliable and scalable computing.
However, they are complicated
and prone to bugs.
To manage this complexity,
network middleware has
been traditionally built
in layered stacks of components.
The state of the art for
verification of distributed systems
does not consider either
compositional reasoning,
program logics,
or liveness properties.
We present TLC,
a novel program logic
for compositional
verification of both safety
and liveness properties of
distributed system stacks.
This project includes a layered and
functional programming model
to capture distributed components,
the temporal assertion language
to specify both safety
and liveness properties.
Compositional verification
of distributed stacks.
A novel program logic that supports
intuitive reasoning steps
and an operational semantics
for distributed stacks,
and the soundness of the logic.
We successfully applied
it to compose and verify
stacks of fundamental
distributed components.
The ultimate goal is to build
certified distributed middleware.
And towards this goal, we are
mechanizing our proofs in Coq.
We present a layered
programming model
to capture functional implementations
of distributed components.
The component receives incoming
requests from the parent component,
and incoming indications
from the sub-components
that defines 200 functions
request an indication
for these events.
It also defines a handler
that is periodically called.
These handlers return a triple
the new internal state of the component
and the list of issued outgoing
requests to subcomponents
and outgoing indications
to the parent component.
Let us consider the
perfect link competent,
that uses a stubborn
link subcomponent.
We abbreviate their
names as PL and SL.
SL repeatedly resends messages so that
they are eventually delivered.
This results in multiple deliveries.
Therefore PL is built on the top of
SL to eliminate duplicate messages.
The state of each
node stores counter
the number of messages sent by
the current node and also received
the set of received
message identifiers.
Each message is uniquely identified
by the pair of
the sender node identifier
and the number of
the messages in that node.
Upon a request to send the message
the counter is incremented
and the message is sent together
with the new counter value
using the SL subcomponent.
Upon a delivery indication of
a message from the SL subcomponent,
If the message is already
received, it is ignored.
Otherwise, the message identifier
is added to the received set
and appear delivery
indication event is issued.
Here we briefly illustrate
the propagation of events across the stack.
We have a stack of
components on the left
and a trace of events on the right
with events at different levels.
The request at the top-level
results in a request
for the left subcomponent that
in turn results in a request
for its own subcomponent that
results in an indication
and another indication-up and finally
an indication at the top level.
In the next few slides,
we will use the indication
identifier d of an event
that is the reverse
list of branch indices
from the top component
to that event.
We now take a look at parts
of the assertion language.
We use the classical operators
always and always in the past.
And eventually
and eventually in the past.
The assertion A strong implies
A' is syntactic sugar for
always A implies A'.
The assertion A leads to
A' prime is syntactic sugar for
always A implies eventually A'.
Similarly, the assertion A preceded
by A' is syntactic sugar for
always A implies eventually
in the past A'.
The flexible valuables for
the elements of an event are
the identifier n of the node
that executes the event.
The location identifier d in
the stack that the event is executed at
the output requests ors
an output indications
ois that the event issues
and the prestate s
and the post state s' of the event.
We use the syntactic
sugar assertion self
to describe events that are
applied to the top component.
Now important syntactic sugar,
here down arrow denotes
a request an up arrow denotes
an indication.
This syntactic sugar
describes an event at node n
at the top-level location T,
where the request event
send n' and m is executed.
The bullet is just a separator.
And this second syntactic sugar
describes an event at node n
at the child location one
where the indication even
deliver n' and m is executed.
This specification of both
safety and liveness properties
of the perfect link can be
written almost verbatim
from their natural
language descriptions.
Let's see a reliable delivery
as a liveness property.
If a correct node n sends
a message m to a correct node n',
then n' will eventually deliver m
A no-forge property
is a safety property.
If a node n delivers
a message m with sender n'
then n' has previously sent m to n.
And a similar no-forge property
is stated for stubborn links,
let us consider
compositional verification.
We have two stacks S0 and S1 with
the specifications I0 and I1
To implement a new component C
we use them as subcomponents.
We want to verify
the specification A for C
based on only the specifications
and not the implementations
of the sub-components.
The fundamental question is
how the specification of
a component should be lowered
to be used as a sub-component.
Lowering is not possible
for every assertion.
We observed that lowering specifications
requires certain information
such as the location of
events to be present,
and certain operators such as next to
be absent from the specification.
We identify the subset of
the assertion language that is both
restrictive enough to allow
the definition of the
lowering transformation
and expressive enough
to represent specifications.
The lower function first pushes
and then restricts the assertion.
We visit each one of these
two functions in turn.
When a component is used
as a sub-component,
its events appear at a deeper level.
For example, the location of
the events of the first component
are at the top level
shown by the empty path.
But then the component is used
as the first sub-component.
The events appear at branch
zero written as the path zero.
The push transformation pushes
the locations under branch I.
The important case is the atom case.
The location D is
explicit in the atom
appending I to the location D
effectively pushes the events
to branch I, next
the restrict function.
When a stack is at the top, all
events belong to that stack.
However, when it is pushed to
a sub stack, it's not alone anymore.
It's even sorely interleaved
with the events from the
sibling sub stacks
and the top component.
The restrict transformation
restricts the specification
to remain valid on traces that are
extended with interleaving events.
The important case is always A.
After pushing the session always A
does not necessarily remain valid.
It remains valid on only
the events under that branch.
Therefore, the restricting condition
of being under branch I is added.
Let us take a look at a few basic
and derived inference rules
of the TLC program logic.
The basic inference rules capture
the fundamental reasoning steps
and fit in half a page.
Yet they provide the basis
for the derived rules
and verification of full stacks.
Here we consider two basic
rules and one derived rule.
The judgments of this form
states that under
the assumed assertions comma
the assertion A holds
for the component C.
The rule OI for output
indication states that
if at a node n an output indication
e is issued by a self event,
then eventually at n
and the top-level T,
the indication event e is executed.
The rule OI' states this relation
in the opposite direction.
If at the node n the top-level T
an output indication
event e is executed,
then in the past at that
node n the indication event e
should have been
issued by a self event.
Let us now look at
the derived rule INVL.
This rule reduces a global temporal
invariant for the component
to nontemporal and local proof
obligations for its handler functions.
It states that if
a nontemporal assertion A
holds for all the three handler
functions of the component,
request, indication, and periodic
then the assertion holds
in every self event.
Thus the functional
implementation of the component
can be used to derive
invariants we showcase TLC
with the example proof of
the no-forge property for PL.
If a PL delivery event is executed,
it is preceded by its
corresponding PL send event.
Starting from the Pl delivery event,
the first step states that
if a PL delivery event is executed,
the event should have
been previously issued.
Then the step two shows that
if a PL delivery event is issued,
it is issued by an SL deliver event.
And step three uses the lower
specification of the no-forge
property of the SL subcomponent.
Every SL deliver event
is preceded by an SL send event.
And the other steps are similar
by transitivity of precedence,
we get to no-forge property for PL
these steps can be captured in TLC.
Here we look at step two.
We want to prove that if
a PL deliver event is issued,
the issuing event is
an SL deliver event.
To prove it, we use the rule
INVL that we saw before
with this assertion
A that states that
the PL deliver event is issued
by only an SL delivery
and the definition of the component SC.
The first obligation is
for the request handler.
The request function issues
an empty set of output indications
and so the assertion
A trivially halts.
The next obligation is for
the indication handler.
It issues the PL deliver event,
but that is when an SL
deliver event is processed.
So, the assertion A halts.
And finally the obligation
for the periodic handler
trivially halts in this component.
This results in this assertion.
That is a simple rearrangement
is equivalent to
the assertion in step two.
We define the operational
semantics of distributed stacks.
It models the propagation
of events across the stack
message passing actress nodes in
partially synchronous networks
and crash stop failures.
We prove the soundness of TLC.
TLC derives only valid assumptions
from valid assumptions.
We also proved
the soundness of lowering,
if an invariant is
valid for a stack Si
and Si is a sub stack
of a stack S,
then the lowered invariant
is valid for S as well.
We successfully
applied this approach
to stack of fundamental
distributed components including
stubborn links, perfect
links, best-effort broadcast,
uniform reliable broadcast
and epoch Paxos consensus.
And towards the goal of
certified middleware,
we are mechanizing our
proofs in a Coq framework.
I invite you to read the paper
and I will be glad to
answer your questions.
ADAM: Thanks, Mohsen.
In either time band,
you should now see
a link appearing Clowdr
to join the video Q&A
with Mohsen.
To close out the session
we have Ningning Xie,
presenting a variant
of algebraic effects
that admits efficient
implementation.
NINGNING XIE: Hello
everyone, I'm Ningning.
I'm going to present our work
effect handlers evidently.
Hello, in this work we show that
we can elaborate algebraic
effects the evidence passing
to polymorphic lambda calculus.
This gives new semantics
of algebraic effects.
In particular, there is no need
for a special runtime system
for implementations. This
can be extremely useful
if you want to compile algebraic
effects to languages like C.
Moreover, we show that
with evidence passing
such implementations
can be quite efficient.
Before we go to
the technical details
let's start with an overview
of algebraic effects.
Algebraic effects and an
extension with handlers
are a powerful way to incorporate
effects in programming languages.
To understand how it works,
we start with a simple
example of the reader effect.
On the left-hand side, we
define a simple effect reader,
which has a single operation
ask. The type of ask says that
you can ask by providing
a unit argument,
then you'll there
return you an integer.
Now we can already start using ask.
The expressions below simply could
ask twice and returns the sum.
However, we still don't know
how it would evaluate.
The semantics of effects is
given by effect handlers,
where handlers provide
operation implementations.
we handle an expression by replicatinga
lambda which takes a unit.
in our example, we use x to
denote the operation argument.
In this case unit. The extra
argument k is implicitly provided
by the system, which
denotes the resumption,
that is how to resume the computation
where operation is performed.
In this case, we always
redeem with one.
When the first ask is performed,
the handler returns one
and we have one plus
perform as unit.
Then the second ask is
performed and we have 1+1
which gives a result two.
One remarkable feature
of algebraic effects
is a decoupling of effects and is
the implementation of effects.
In particular, we can
use the same handler
to handle a different computation or
we can easily use a different handler
to handle the same computation.
In summary, algebraic effects
provide a useful way to encode
composable and modular computational
effects by having effects,
which define a family of operations
separately for handlers,
which gives semantics to operations.
We have seen that example of reader
and refer to our paper for
more complicated examples.
However, it is non-trivial to
support algebraic effects
in real world programming languages,
we demonstrate
the issue with this example.
This code has three handlers,
followed by an expression,
which simply could ask twice
as we have seen before.
The three handlers are a reader
handler, an Incr handler,
which increases
the computation results by one,
and an exception handler, which
returns a default value three
if the computation fails.
As before, since the reader
always returns one,
we expect the answer to be two.
Now let's take a closer look at
how this expression evaluates.
We first evaluate
the reader handler.
Now we need to remember that
we have a reader handler
available in the
evaluation context,
since there, we may need to use
the handler to handle
certain operations.
In a similar way, we
evaluate the incr handler,
and then the exception handler.
We then hit the first ask,
but we don't know how to handle it,
thus, we yield up to
the evaluation context,
and hope to find a reader handle.
So inner most handler
is exception handler,
which is not useful in this case,
we keep going up
and find an incr handler,
which is again not
useful in this case.
Finally, we reach a reader
handler, which states that,
we should always resume
with integer one.
Now we need to resume and go
back where the operation
is handled, and this is
where we hit the second ask.
Now we need to repeat
the whole process again
by first yielding up
and then resuming.
As you may have noticed, implementing
algebraic affects this way
requires special runtime
support to yield up,
to capture the resumption
and to resume.
This is very difficult to add to
existing programming languages,
moreover, it is very inefficient.
To support two asks, we have
yield up, and resumed twice,
and it can be more time
consuming if the handler stack
is even larger.
Hence, the goal of our work
is to have composable,
modular, efficient, and easy to
implement computational effects.
To this end, we present new
semantics of algebraic effects
in terms of polymorphic
lambda calculus,
by first introducing
an intermediate evidence calculus.
We can then elaborate
polymorphic algebraic effects,
there are evidence passing
translation to the evidence calculus.
This turns out to be surprisingly
tricky to get right.
In particular, the coherence
of evidence translation
turns out to only be preserved
under scoped resumptions.
Finally, we define a monadic
multi prompt translation
for the evidence calculus to
the polymorphic lambda calculus.
Combining these two translations,
we get an implementation
of algebraic effects upon
polymorphic lambda calculus,
and that requires no
special runtime support.
We have proved soundness
and completeness of the translation.
They also turn out that
doing this translation
does not only get rid of
special runtime system,
but also allows us to implement
algebraic effects more efficiently,
especially for
resumptive operations.
In the rest of the talk, we
first go through the meaning
of the scoped resumptions, and then
discuss these two translations.
To understand the restriction
of scoped resumptions,
let's consider this example.
Here, we have two
handlers, h1 and hevil,
that bracket the expression E.
The whole result is then given to F.
The definition of E performs three
operations, ask, evil, and ask.
The handler h1 is a reader
handler which handles ask
by always resuming with one.
A real expectation now in
that these two asks in e
with the return one.
However, we show that while
the first ask as expected
gives back one, the second ask
gives back a different number two.
How is that possible?
We define the evil
handler in a way that
instead of resuming, it directly
returns the resumption K.
F then gets the resumption,
and applies the resumption
under a different handler
h2, which handles ask
by returning two instead.
Note in this example, K is
captured under a handler
context with h1, and is resumed
under a different handler with h2,
this is very powerful,
perhaps too powerful
that it can interfere with ability
to reason about the program.
We define the notion of scoped
resumptions as a restriction
of general effect handlers, where
resumptions can only be applied
in the very scope of their
original handler context.
Thus, the previous example is
rejected under scoped assumptions.
We believe that all
important effected handlers
can be written with
scoped assumptions
including complicated
examples like async
or concurrent scheduling.
The previous example can also be
re-written to pass the restriction.
In this work, we focus on
the evidence translation
and use a dynamic check
in our formalism.
In the paper, we also
show several designs
on how to check this properly.
Using scoped resumptions, we define
the evidence passing translation.
The key idea of evidence
passing is that,
a vector of handlers is passed
down as an implicit parameter
similar to
the dictionary translation,
in Haskell for type classes.
To understand how
evidence passing works,
we re-evaluate the previous example
using the evidence
passing semantics.
As before, we first evaluate
the reader handler.
This time, we create
a fresh unique marker
represented as m1 to denote this
particular reader handler,
we code the pair of
the marker and the handler
and evidence, and we pass
the evidence down as we evaluate.
We then evaluate the incr handler
by creating another fresh
unique marker m2
and pass the new evidence
along with the existing
reader evidence, that is,
we now have an evidence vector.
We denote our evidence
vector using the letter w.
We do the same for
the exception handler,
and get one more evidence.
Now we hit the first ask operation,
this time, we first inspect
the evidence vector.
From the evidence vector,
we find the reader handler
that is supposed to handle
this operation has marker m1,
we can then yield up,
but in this case,
finding the correct handler
can be much faster than before
because we only needed
to compare the markers.
Actually, the evaluation can
be even faster, that is,
we don't need to yield up at all.
Because from the evidence
vector, we do not only know
the marker of the handler, but we
have the handler itself available.
From the handler
implementation, we know that
the reader handler has a tail
resumptive implementation,
therefore, we can evaluate
the handler in place
and get a result one, as the result
of ask, and keep evaluating.
We can then hit the second
ask and get the other one.
Compared to the previous evaluation,
this time, the evaluation
is a straight line,
which means that it does not
change the control flow at all,
this is just much more efficient
than the previous one.
To make such evaluation
strategies possible,
we have proved
the following theorem.
The theorem essentially states that,
while performing
an operation of effect L,
the handler we find in
the evidence vector w
which is w, l is exactly
the innermost handler
for that operation in the dynamic
evaluation context, which is mh.
Thus, with evidence processing,
we significantly improve
the efficiency of algebraic effects.
In particular, tail resumption
operations can evaluate in place.
This optimization enables
efficient effect operations
at a cost similar to
a virtual method call.
Non tail-resumptive operations
still needed to yield up,
but from the evidence vector,
we can locally decide
which marker to yield to,
which is still more efficient
than finding
the handler dynamically.
Hello everyone.
Next at this passing, we
can then implement handlers
using multi-prompt continuations.
So basically, given evidence
mh, we can directly yield
to a specific prompt n, moreover,
since the evidence provided
the handler implementation
directly, it is no longer needed
in the context.
Such translation is very important
and it provides the missing link
between traditional implementation
based on dynamic search
for the handlers,
and implementations of lexical effect handlers
using multi prompt
delimited control.
Specifically, we define
a multi prompt translation
from the evidence language into
standard polymorphic lambda calculus
where the monad implements
the multi prompt semantics.
Now, no special runtime
system is needed anymore,
and we can generate code
directly for languages
like C or Web Assembly.
Moreover, with our
standard back end,
advanced compilation structures
can be used for example,
compilation guided,
reference counting.
Hello everyone.
We summarize all calculi in
our paper using this figure.
We have a polymorphic algebraic
effect calculus system at e,
we can erase the types
in system at e,
and gets to an untyped algebraic
effect calculus, system lambda e.
Also, we can do an evidence
passing translation
to a polymorphic evidence
calculus, system at ev.
Finally, we show that
system at ev can use
the multi-prompts translation
and translate it to a polymorphic
lambda calculus, system fv.
With both translations available,
we get an implementation
of polymorphic algebraic
effects in terms of polymorphic
lambda calculus.
Hello everyone.
Please read our paper
for more details,
moreover, we have provided
an implementation
of the evidence passing translation
in the Koka programming language.
And initial benchmark
results are very promising.
Finally, we present a Haskell
library of effect handlers
based on the technique
described here,
but we encourage interested
people to read our Haskell paper
or watch the talk for more details.
That's all, thank you for listening.
(CROWD APPLAUDS)
ADAM: Thanks, Ningning.
In either time band, you
should see a Q&A link
appear in Clowdr which you
can click the video chat
with at least one of
the authors of this paper,
and that's it for this session.
Before, or after chatting with
the authors of that last paper,
please take advantage
of our coffee break
to for instance create your
own ad hoc video chat room,
or join one that you
already see there.
We really want to simulate what's
created by the ICFP
social experience so don't be shy.
We'll also have some more
structured social activities
right after the coffee
break as well as throughout
the rest of the three
days conference,
and we'll be back here for
the next technical session
at 2:30 pm New York time.
(BACKGROUND MUSIC)
(UPBEAT FOLK MUSIC)
(SOFT POP MUSIC)
(ROCK MUSIC)
(ELECTRONIC POP MUSIC)