RICHARD EISENBERG: Hi everyone!
Welcome to Technical
Session 5 of ICFP 2020.
My name is Richard Eisenberg.
I'm principal researcher
at Tweak I/O
and a member of the ICFP
Program Committee.
This session will be
streamed via YouTube
but is also available via Clowdr.
So, those of you who registered
if you're on YouTube please
switch over to Clowdr.
You should have gotten
a notification, an email
how to do so.
And that will give you access
to more interactive features
of these presentations.
Including links to the question
and answer sessions from the authors.
So, first up in this session,
we have Joe Cutler who will present
how we can extract recurrent
relations from functions
for amortized analysis.
JOE CUTLER: Hi, I'm Joe Cutler.
I'm an undergraduate at Wesleyan
University in Connecticut.
And this is work with
my advisor Dan Licata
and Norman Danner.
So, if I handed you this
code for mergeSort
and then asked you to
write down a recurrence
for its worst-case execution cost,
you'll probably end up writing down
pretty much exactly this
expression right here.
But the thing you did in
your head to get there
is actually pretty subtle.
It required knowing things about
the sizes of the results of functions.
Like the fact that
split splits lists in half
and abstracting list
down to just a length.
And even more importantly
as a PL person,
you might even have
an operational semantics
for a language that this
function is written in,
that precisely defines
the cost of program execution
in terms of beta redexes
or some other cost metrics.
And how do you know this
recurrence you wrote down
has anything to do whatsoever
with those formal costs?
So, in other words,
how do we make this informal process
of recurrence extraction formal
and ensure that it's correct?
Well, at ICFP five years ago,
the other two authors of this
paper and their co-author
presented an answer to
exactly that question.
And I guess rather than
keep you on suspense,
I just show you what
they came up with.
So, recurrence extraction
is formalized as
a language-to-language translation.
So, given the term in
some source language
we can translate it into
a language that we call lambda C
which is a language whose terms are
syntactic recurrence relations.
Now, the overall idea
of this translation
which we often call formal
recurrence extraction
is to translate terms to
output their evaluation cost
along with the size of the result.
So, a term of type A in a source
gets translated to a pair.
Consisting of the cost
to evaluate that term
along with the resulting value,
the size of the resulting
value of type A.
Now, this size translation
that I'm talking about
is essentially
the identity on values
but it shifts to a higher type
where the size of a function is
a recurrence in a traditional sense.
So, it's a function from
sizes to cost and sizes.
Now, the real meat of this
recurrence extraction
is the term translation which
is defined compositionally
by recursion over raw syntax.
So, given a term in the source,
we can just translate it
to a term in lambda C.
Now, if you're
a monadically minded person,
you might recognize
all of this as being
a monadic translation
into the writer monad.
And all of this helps
motivate the definition
of a size translation.
Arrows in the source become
Kleisli arrows in lambda C.
So we've extracted
recurrences
from the source language
into lambda C.
And now we need to prove that
this extraction procedure is correct.
Otherwise all of this is no better
than just extracting recurrences
the old informal way.
So, the first step here is to fix
an operational semantics
from the source language which
is indexed by execution cost.
You can read this judgement as
M evaluates in n steps to V.
And then we prove this following
theorem using a logical relation.
So, for any closed term m of type A,
if m evaluates in n steps to v,
then the extracted cost of running
M is an upper bound on n,
and also the usual logical relations
value relation nonsense.
But anyway, this theorem is the
crucial step, it formally connects
the operational cost model
to the extracted recurrences.
One important piece of the
informal analysis
that this translation doesn't take
into account is size abstraction,
like say, analysing a function
which takes a list in terms
of its length or a tree function
by depth or something like that.
Now, we do this abstraction
using a denotational semantics
from lambda c into
partially ordered sets.
And this means that the
objects that we get out
are the standard objects you'd
recognise as recurrences.
You can compute closed forms and
asymptotics and stuff like that.
OK, that was a lot of technical
detail, I acknowledge that
but luckily all this has all
been done before.
And in the year since this
technique was developed,
it's been employed to formalise
recurrence extraction
for increasingly realistic languages
from the simply typed
lambda calculus to inductive
types all the way up to PCF
and ML-style let polymorphism.
But all this prior work
is limited in the kinds of analyses
they can handle.
Only ever worst case cost
analysis and in many cases,
worst case cost analysis
simply isn't enough
to get tight bounds, we,
and a technique like say,
amortized analysis is required
to get better bounds.
And so in this work we extend
the recurrence extraction technique
to handle amortized analysis.
So, in the paper we go over
two standard examples
of amortized analysis to
demonstrate the effectiveness
of our technique. And the first
is a simple binary counter
and the second is splay trees
as presented in Okasaki.
The splay trees are notable because
they aren't really well handled
by automated amortized
analysis techniques
such as resource aware ML.
And since the analysis of splay trees
is really complicated,
I only have like
10 more minutes.
I'll use the binary counter as
a running example to motivate the way
that we made our papers
main contribution.
So, consider a binary number
represented as a list of bits
with the least significant
bit at the head,
we can define an increment function
in the standard way.
Note that if the least
significant bit is zero,
the increment is
constant time
but if the least
significant bit is one,
we have to make a recursive
call down the tail.
Now we can define a set function
which just sets the counter
to a natural number value by
looping increments end times.
So, here are the recurrences
that you'd expect to get
from these functions using
the informal method.
By the way, for the rest of the
talk will fix the cost model,
the cons operations are
the only cost the operation,
in each incurring costs.
So, these two recurrences here solve
to T inc being linear,
and T set being n log n.
But this actually isn't a tight bound
for set,it's actually linear.
Intuitively, this is because
the constant time case
of the increment happens way
more often while you're looping.
But you have to take the max between
the two non empty branches
when you extract the recurrence,
which makes it look like
increment traverses the
whole list every single time.
And unfortunately, this is exactly
what the prior work in
formal recurrence extraction
would do to this example.
So, motivate some
stuff down the line,
let's take a look at
how that would go.
So, we can take our increment
function written
in the source language
and pass it through
the recurrence extraction
translation to get a function
into a pair c cross which
computes the cost of running
an increment along with
the size of the result.
Now, the first component of
this pair is the important one,
it's the execution cost. So I'll
just write down the subscripts c.
Now this syntactic
recurrence that you get out
is exactly what I hope
You'd expect. The key cases,
when the least significant bit
is one,it costs one for the cons
plus the cost of
recursing down the tail.
Now, after this, we use
the denotational semantics
to interpret this recurrence
as a map between Posets.
Most importantly, we interpret the
bit list type as the natural numbers
which abstracts a list to its
length in the traditional way.
Now the monotone maps of
posets we get in the semantics
represent the exact
same loose bounds
that we talked about before .
If you carry it all through
for set you still get O(n log n).
So, we've seen how the
previous work comes up short.
Now let's take a look at how
the amortized analysis
of the binary counter actually
should work to help inform
how to change the
recurrence extraction
to get the tight amortized
bounds we are looking for.
So, here's a quick refresher
on amortized analysis
for those of you who've forgotten
about what the big deal was
since you last
learned about it.
So, amortized analysis comes
in a few different forms
but all of them boil down
to essentially smoothing out cost
across programme execution.
So, that when you analyse repeated
executions of the same function,
they don't all look like
the most costly one
and instead look like say
the average one.
And the approach to amortized
analysis that we take in the paper,
which is usually called the bankers
method is to maintain
an invariant, the imaginary credits
on the nodes of a data structure.
So, these credits
incur costs to create,
but then you can spend
them to decrease cost.
And by passing these credits
around the program,
you can rearrange costs.
The credit invariant for
the binary counter is that
we keep one credit on each
cons cell, which holds a one bit.
So, here's an example to
illustrate how this works.
We start with an empty count
with no credits.
And then the first increment
flips the first bit
and we spawn a credit to put on the
one, total amortized cost here
is one cons plus one created
credit equals two amortized cost.
And then the next call to
increment flips the first bit
from one to zero and the
second bit from zero to one.
And then to reestablish the credit
invariant we spawn a credit
to put on the new one bit,
which incurs a cost of one
but then that's cancelled out by
spending the credit which used
to be on the least significant bit.
Again total two amortized costs.
This is the essence of the analysis
and you can convince yourself
that in every case, the amortised
cost of increment is two.
So, in order to do this kind of
analysis by recurrence extraction,
we need to make
these credit policies
expressible in the
source language.
So, to that end, we extend
our source language
with credits to make a language
that we called lambda A.
So, lambda A internalises
everything you need to
express credit invariants
in your code,
and it comes in
three main parts.
So, first we need
to be able to track
the credits using
the type system.
So, this new typing judgement
says that m is a term of Type A
and context gamma, which
can use up to C credits.
Now, since we don't want
credits to be duplicated
and then the same credit
spent twice, the type system
is Affine which means that variables
can be used at most once.
So, next we need to be able
to attach these credits
to terms like say
the elements of a list.
And to do this we add a
modality to the language.
The terms of type bang, cA,
are morally terms of Type A
that carry c extra credits.
And the intro/elim rules
for this modality
are actually pretty intuitive.
The intro rule says that
we have a term m of Type A
and we have C Extra
Credits lying around,
and we don't need to construct,
that we don't need to construct m,
we can just attach them to M
and get a term type bang cA.
And the elim rule says that if
we have a term of type bang cA,
we can peel the credits off
the term and allow them
and the value to be used in
a continuation to make more stuff.
So, finally, we need the ability
to create and spend credits,
of course, and the create rule
here says that if we have a term
which uses a plus c credits,
we can simply create C of them
and duly the spend rule says
that if we have A plus c credits,
we can spend c of them
and then use a term
which only requires
A credits.
Now, all of these changes I just
described are completely local
to lambda A. We don't change
the recurrence language at all,
it's still fully structural
and has no modality.
So, we've extended the source
language with the features
that let us formally specify these
credit invariants in our code.
Now let's take a look at how
the binary counter example
would actually get
encoded into this language.
So, in lambda a, we redefine the
bit type to be unit plus bang one
unit, a bit is either in-left of
a unit which represents a zero,
or in-right of a unit
with one credit attached,
which represents one. And
then the code for increment
is the exact same
behaviour as before,
it just maintains the credit policy.
If the list is empty or has zeros,
in the least significant bit,
we create a credit and make
a one bit value by attaching
that credit to a unit value
and then returning that
as the least significant bit.
And it's the least significant bit
as one, we detach
the credit using transfer, spend it
and then make a recursive call
on the tail and cons as zero
one to the result.
So, all good lambda A can
express the credit policy
that we were looking for,
but now we need
to actually extract
recurrences from it.
But the recurrence extraction for
lambda A is actually quite simple.
So, let's briefly recall that
the recurrence extraction
from a term consists of a pair
of the cost to compute
the term along with its size.
So, since creating A credits
incurs a cost of A
just add A to the extracted cost
and dually we subtract A
from the cost
component when we spent.
Now, since the credits as
I mentioned earlier aren't present
in the recurrence language,
the extraction has to erase
the modality and its
corresponding form.
So, save gets erased completely and
transfer gets turned into a let.
All good. So, now that we have
the recurrence extraction
in place for lambda a,
let's extract terms recurrences
for the binary counter,
solve them and hopefully
get the tight boundary
we're looking for.
So, above line here is the term
for inc that we wrote earlier
and below I've written the cost
component of the recurrence
you get in lambda C
for this term.
So, when the argument to
this recurrence is empty,
or has zero is the least
significant bit,
increment costs two, one from
the cons one from creating credit
When is the least significant bit
one, the cost we extract is simply
the cost of the
recursive call.
Now, why is this?
Well, we do one cons operation
which costs one and
then we spend a credit
from the least significant bit,
which subtracts one.
So, we're just left with the cost
of the recursive call down the tail.
It's super easy to see that this
function is two everywhere.
And indeed the monotone map
of posets that it denotes
is in fact the constant
function two.
So, carrying this
all through for set,
we get to the corresponding
mathematical recurrence
is order n as desired. So we have
a recurrence extraction procedure
that extracts tight bounds
for amortized analyses.
And the final step here
is to prove a theorem
like the bounding theorem
for prior work
which connects these recurrences
to the operational semantics.
And similar to how we
did it in prior work.
We first define a big step
operational semantics for lambda a,
but this time indexed by amortized
cost. So, this judgement reads
that M evaluates to V
with an amortized cost.
Then we use a logical relation to
prove the same bounding theorem
as before but this time the cost
per bounding is an amortized cost.
But the crucial consequence
of this theorem
is that for closed terms, the
amortized cost that we get
for the recurrence is a bound on
the actual execution cost.
And so for example, the set
programme isn't just linear
in this strange cost metric
where we can subtract
and add arbitrary costs.
It actually does a linear amount
of cons operations.
So, in summary,
we formalise the process
of doing amortized analysis
by recurrence extraction.
Given an amortized analysis
of a data structure
such as a binary counter
or splay tree written in lambda a,
we can automatically extract
correct recurrences into lambda c.
This extraction procedure
has been proven correct
and is expressive
enough to handle
non trivial analyses
like splay trees.
Thank you very much.
AUDIENCE: Applause
RICHARD: Thanks, Joe.
Now in both the New York
and Asia time bands.
You should be able to click a
link in the sidebar in Clowdr
to be able to access
the Q&A sessions.
OK, our next talk is featuring
Arthur Chargueraud
about separation logic for
sequential programs.
ARTHUR CHARGUERAUD: Separation logic
was introduced in
the early 2000s.
Since then, it has had tremendous
success at programme verification.
I believe that today, the ideas
of separation logic deserve
to be taught much more widely.
For this reason, I've been working
on a course on separation logic.
The course focuses on
sequential programs.
Concurrency is interesting
but it's much harder.
Course is written in the style of
the Software Foundations series,
where every definition
every lemma,
and every exercise is formalised
using the Coq proof assistant.
The course covers modern
features of Separation logic.
These are features that will not
present in the original papers
in separation logic, but have
since then proved very useful
for developing practical tools.
The third contribution of this paper
is an extensive
related work section,
which I believe nicely completes
'Peter O'Hearn's' survey,
which was published last year
by focusing specifically
on the contributions to make a nice
presentations of separation logic.
The course is organised
in 10 chapters.
So, the first three
chapters focus on
basic features of
separation logic,
such as heap predicates,
triples, entailement.
The next few chapters focus
on the presentation
of reasoning rules,
either in the form of triples in the
form of weakest preconditions,
or in the form of
characteristic formulae,
which are a form of weakest
precondition generator.
The remaining chapters focus
on more advanced features
such as a magic wand,
the treatment of affine predicates,
and language extensions,
such as records, arrays
loops or n-ary functions.
Let me take a few minutes
to explain how the course
is set up at a
very high level.
Traditional courses on separation
logic consider while loop language.
I consider instead like other
colleagues before me
an imperative
lambda calculus.
This choice leads to
major simplification.
The fact that there are
no mutable variables lead
to an elegant statement
of the frame rule
without any side-condition.
At the same time, using
lambda calculus means
that every term
produces a value
and this leads to a
minor complication.
The fact that post conditions
need to describe
not just an output state
but also an output value.
Quickly, where preconditions
are the type of heap to prop
post conditions of
type value to heap to prop.
These set of operators such as the
star, the magic wand or entailment,
this needs to be extended to a form
that operates on post condition.
These are marked with a little
dot symbol below the operator.
The semantics is described in the
standard way as a call by value,
substitution based,
big step style semantics.
The choice of a big step semantics
is well suited for reasoning
about total correctness
of sequential programs.
It makes the proof simpler.
Both the syntax and
the semantics are described
in standard ways following
the style of the presentation
of the prior Software
Foundation volumes,
which will make it easy
for students to follow.
Separation logic is presented
in a shallow embedding.
This means that the core heap
predicates of separation logic
are defined as Coq functions
from heap to propositions.
Entailment is defined
in the standard way
as simplest possible way
as pointwise entailment.
The remaining operators
are encoded in terms of
these core operators.
For the details
I'll just refer
to the course.
Triples are defined in two stage.
First, the hoarse Triple H t Q
asserts that for any state as
satisfying the precondition,
the term t terminates on a value V
and an open state S prime
that together satisfy
the post condition Q.
A separation logic
Triple H t Q is defined
by quantifying universally
on a predicate H prime
that describes
the rest of the world.
And asserting that the triple
made of H stop H prime
and Q-Star Q H prime makes
up a valid or triple.
The standard technique of
baking in the frame rule
leads to simple proofs
for the structural rules,
such as a frame rule
or the consequence rule.
I'd like to take
the rest of the talk
to present four features of
modern separation logic,
which I believe should
be to interest
to every ICFP researcher.
Let me begin with
a ramified frame rule.
The frame rule in its
most standard statement
is almost never applicable.
Indeed, you need both
the precondition
and the post-condition to
syntactically feature a star H2.
But in practice, one would
typically use a combined rule
that integrates
the rule of consequence,
and is stated as follows;
to prove this triple H T Q
derivable from a triple H1 T Q1.
One has to show that
the precondition H
decomposes as H1 star H2,
and then show that
the post-condition Q1
when extended with H2 recovers
the post-condition Q.
H2 can be computed as
a difference between H and H1.
Computing this difference
can be well automated
in a simple case, but
if H contains existentially
quantified variables,
it can be quite tricky
to figure out whether these
corresponding variables
should get quantified
in H1 or in H2.
The ramified frame rule avoid
this problem altogether
by removing the need to
introduce H2 in the first place.
It reformulates the premises
as a single entailment.
H entails H1 star.
Some predicates, such that
when augmenting Q1
with it, we obtain Q.
The operator at play
here is the magic wand
for post-condition.
Without going into further
detail, let me just point out
that the ramified frame rule
has proved very practical
for developing practical tools.
The second point I'd
like to focus on is;
the weakest preconditioned
presentation
of separation logic.
Just like in our logic,
weakest precondition
is a key ingredient, but what
is the definition of WP
in separation logic?
And what is a statement
of a frame rule
in weakest precondition style?
So WP, just like in our
logic, can be defined
as an equivalence
between a triple H D Q
and the entailment from H to WP T Q.
This equivalence is not
quite a definition.
The two definitions that
can be considered;
one is a low level definition
working in terms of heaps.
Another one is based on an encoding
using the operators
of separation logic.
The weakest precondition frame
rule can be read as follows;
if I own a resource state
in which I can execute
the term T and obtain
the post-condition Q
and separately, I own a piece
of state described by H.
Then altogether,
I own a piece of state
in which the execution
of T terminates
and produces
a post-condition described
by Q extended with H.
Interestingly, the weakest
precondition frame rule
can be combined with the ideas
of the ramified frame rule,
leading to the rule shown at
the bottom of the slide here.
This rule subsumes all
the structural rules
of separation logic.
The third feature is
the mixing of affine
and linear predicates.
A linear predicate describes
a resource that must remain
accounted for throughout
the reasoning.
It is essential, for example,
to prove that every allocated data
eventually gets deallocated,
or every file open
eventually gets closed.
And the affine heap predicate
on the contrary,
describes a resource that
may be freely discarded
in the reasoning.
Typically,this notion of affine predicate
is a must have for garbage
collected languages,
which do not feature
explicit free operations.
So it is straightforward to set up
a linear separation logic,
and it is not much harder
to set up an affine
separation logic,
but what is a simple way to
set up a separation logic,
where both linear and affine
predicates can coexist?
By describing
the (INAUDIBLE) construction
that is relatively simple,
which relies on
the introduction of a predicate
H affine, that can be
customized to define
which heaps should be considered
affine as opposed to linear.
Top of that can define
the notion of affine predicates
that characterize only
heaps that are affine.
And the notion of
affine top predicate
which characterizes any affine heap.
The definition of
separation logic triples
can be generalized by
introducing the top,
the affine top predicate
in the post-condition.
Doing so preserved
the validity of all the prior
rules of separation logic
and adds two additional rules.
The first one asserts that any piece
of precondition H prime
may be discarded
from the precondition
provided that it's affine.
The second rule allows to
extend the post-condition
within the affine top predicate
reflecting on the fact
that it is fine to
produce a post-condition
that is bigger than the desired one.
Fourth and last feature
I'd like to describe
is a frame friendly rule
for reasoning about loops.
So consider for
example, an operation
that traverses a linked list,
or traverses a tree data
structure recursively.
If the separation is implemented
as a recursive function,
one can invoke the frame rule
around the recursive calls
to forget about the cells
or the parts of the trees
that are passed by.
On the contrary, if
the operation is implemented
as a loop and specified using
a loop invariant,
the loop invariant must describe
the list segment
of cells that have already
been passed by or worse,
in the case of a tree, must
describe the tree context
associated with the past that
has already been traversed.
The question here is how can
we reason about syntactic
loop construct as easily
as recursive function
that will allow us to
exploit the frame rule?
So what we're trying to achieve here
is essentially simulate
an encoding of a while loop
as a recursive function,
but without introducing
the overheads of an actual
explicit encoding.
The idea is to specify the while loop
by relating the behavior of
the state at the given iteration
with the state at
the last iteration.
And such a specification
can be established
by induction using Coq's
induction mechanism
by applying the following
unrolling rule,
which essentially unfolds
the whie loop one iteration.
This rule introduces
a conditional sequence
and a recursive occurrence
of the while loop.
When reasoning about this
recursive occurrence
of the while loop, one may
apply the frame rule
to frame the parts of
the list or of the tree
that we are stepping over.
So in the course,
I described an example
illustrating this proof technique
and compare it with the proof
based on the loop environment.
In conclusion, you can
find on my webpage
the paper, including
its eight page appendix
on all the course material,
both in Coq format
and HTML format.
This course is meant
to be released soon
as a volume of the software
foundation series.
I'm actually seeking for feedback,
both from students
and teachers to further
polish the material.
So if you're interested,
please get in touch with me,
and I will be happy to
serve as a TA for you
if you are teaching the course.
Thank you very much.
(APPLAUSE)
Richard: OK, thank you
very much, Arthur.
He is now available in
the New York Time Band
for question and answer,
and we'll take a brief
pause to sync up
with the advertised schedule.
Now, we have Aaron Stump,
presenting his "Strong
Functional Pearl:
"Harper's Regular-Expression
Matcher in Cedille."
AARON: Hello, I'm Aaron Stump,
and today, I'm going to present to you
our "Strong Functional Pearl:
"Harper's Regular-Expression
Matcher in Cedille."
Harper's regular-expression matcher
is a continuation-based algorithm
for regular-expression matching,
introduced by Robert
Harper, in his JFP paper,
titled, "Proof-Directed Debugging."
And the basic idea of the algorithm
is to decompose regular expressions.
So, you're going to dig down
into the regular expression,
building up a success continuation.
If you detect a clash,
where the regular
expression is asking
for some character that's
not there in the string,
then, you just return false.
But, if you find a character match,
then, you're gonna invoke
the continuation,
to keep processing
the suffix of the string.
And Harper's paper is, you know,
he called it
"Proof-Directed Debugging,"
because there's an interesting bug
in the termination argument
for this algorithm,
unless you use standard
regular expressions.
So, your R star is allowed,
only if the empty string, epsilon,
is not in language of R.
And here, in this talk,
we're gonna enforce
that syntactically,
using a typed StdReg, for
standard regular expressions.
And this is an idea
we got from a paper,
from Dan Licata and his students.
So, here's a look at
the implementation in Haskell.
We're going to move to
the implementation in Cedille,
in a little bit, but to
start off in Haskell,
so, it's a continuation-based
algorithm.
So, we have a type K
for continuations.
It takes strings to bools.
They're going to take suffixes,
tell us whether or not they match.
And then, there's a type,
matchT, for convenience.
It just says continuation
goes to bool.
So here, we see the two helper-
central helper functions
of the algorithm.
There's matchh.
It takes a string, in one of
these regular expressions,
and a continuation.
Now, the first equation
matchh you see,
if that string is empty,
then, we just return false,
'cause these are standard
regular expressions.
They cannot match the empty string.
Otherwise, we just split the string
into its head, c, and tail, cs,
and we invoke this second helper
function, called matchi.
OK, and here, we see the semantics,
in the form of these standard
regular expressions, too.
So, matchi, this,
you could match NoMatch
regular expression.
That just says
nothing's gonna match.
We just return false.
There's MatchChar, with
a character of c prime,
and then, you check,
does c equal c prime?
And if so, that's the success case,
and you invoke this continuation,
k,on the suffix, cs,
and otherwise, you return false.
For an Or regular expression,
we just decompose,
and just check disjunctively
the two parts of
the regular expression.
For the Plus case, though,
this is where the interesting
termination issue comes up.
So, if we have Plus r,
we want to match r, to see
if it matches one time,
'cause this is Plus r, of course,
being one or more matches.
So, we match it one time,
and then, in the continuation
that starts out with
Lambda cs prime,
we're gonna say, well,
let's try just calling
the continuation k on cs prime.
That would represent
exactly one match of r.
But, if that fails,
then, we want to go,
and we're supposed to recursively
try the whole
regular-expression again,
on the suffix, cs prime.
So, that's what I've got
highlighted in red there.
And the interesting thing
about that, of course,
is that the regular expression
is exactly the same
as we started with.
Plus r, we just make
our criss-cross plus r.
So, there's been no
structural decrease here,
which is quite worrisome for
a termination situation.
And then, concat,
similarly decomposes
and updates the continuation.
So, the problem of termination
for this algorithm
has been actually studied,
by a number of different
previous works.
You can sort of see
the main problem right here,
in this little part
that I pulled out
from the code we were
just looking at.
And so, we have a matchh,
that calls matchi,
and matchi wants to
call back to matchh,
in this red highlighted
call site there,
but it's calling it
with the cs prime.
It's just a value it got
from a continuation.
It has no idea.
You know, the code, there's no
obvious syntactic connection
between cs prime and cs.
So, it seems that you need
something like a proof
that the length of cs prime
is less than the length of cs,
or something like this.
And, in fact, previous works
the tackled termination
of Harper's
regular-expression matcher,
some of them anyway,
used dependantly typed continuations.
And, in fact, one of these papers,
a very nice paper
I highly recommend,
by Bove, Krauss, and Sozeau,
raise this challenge, that
there seems to be no easy way
to achieve the same effect,
without the use of dependent types.
So, in this pearl, we're gonna show-
we're showing Harper's matcher
as a strong functional program,
in the sense of David Turner.
So, the idea is that we want,
in strong functional programming,
is we want to statically enforce
termination of programs,
but the name of the game here is,
you're only allowed to use
the types of regular old
functional programming.
Just polymorphic types.
You can't use dependent types.
You can't use sized types.
You're not allowed to use
tetermination proofs,
or variants, or metrics,
or well-founded orders.
All that heavy duty machinery
of termination is not allowed,
in the regime of strong
functional programming.
And so, we are happy to report that,
in fact, you can do this example
without dependent types.
You can just use the tool box
of well, advanced, strong
functional program.
How so, how can you do that?
That's what we're going to talk about,
for the time we have here.
And this is - we're using our
language, Cedille, for this.
And so, strong functional
programming in Cedille.
Cedille is a dependent type theory,
kind of like Coq or Agda,
and termination of programs
is enforced by typing.
But here, Cedille has
some particularities
that make it a bit different
from Coq and Agda,
and one of them is how
termination is handled.
So, and that's part of what we're going to have
a little tutorial about,
in this talk.
So, in Cedille,
when you're writing
a recursive function,
you're presented with something
that we call a recursion universe.
It's a typed interface for
doing the recursion, OK?
So, you get an abstract type r.
That's what you're sort of
thinking of as the universe,
the recursion universe,
and it has some operations on it,
that help you write your recursion.
You're not allowed to make
direct recursive calls,
in your code.
You have to kinda go
through this interface.
And the language, though, provides-
Cedille provides special syntax
for these recursion universes,
that pretty much hide
that hide
a lot of the machinery
and make it feel
a quite idiomatic,
way of writing
recursive functions.
So, I want to emphasize
even though Cedille
is this type threory
that lets you do proofs
and things like that,
dependently typed programs
here we're not using
any dependent types
or any of that
kind of machinery,
we're just using
strong functional programming.
OK. So let's see
how this works
in several steps.
So first, the first point,
we're going to see
Cedille's recursion universes.
So we start off
with something called
a Mendler style
recursion universe.
OK. And so this is kind
of like the underlying interface.
And again, Cedille
provides sort of a little
bit nicer surface language
access to this interface,
but this is the basic interface
that we're relying on.
So let's let F be a signature
function for a data type.
So for example,
if your data type was list of A's,
then your signature function
is FX equals unit or A cross X.
OK. So, if you wanna
suppose you're trying
to write a function.
that's gonna compute
a value of type X
from your datatype D
then what the recursion universe
provides you is
this abstract type R
is mentioning.
It's just some type.
You have no idea,
anything about the type,
except what the interface
gives you about it.
The first thing it gives you
is an eval function
R to X, OK.
And this is the function
you have to invoke.
If you want to make
a recursive call,
you gotta call eval,
but you can only call it
on an R thing.
You can't call it
on just some random
other D thing.
And you're also given
a substructure, sub data structure
of type fr, in other words,
you're given this little package
That is presenting you,
the data that you have,
except at the sort
of factorial position it's got
The abstract type R.
And so the key thing
about this is that,
and this is, this goes
back to this idea
of Mendler style recursion
is that you can only call
eval on sub data,
because the only things
you have lying around
of type R, are the things
that are hidden,
you know, presented to you
in this sub data structure.
And so that's the only stuff
you can call it eval on.
So that ensures your,
you are doing
a structural termination,
even though there's no
sort of check about,
you know, is this variable,
I'm making a quick call
on somehow structurally
derived from my input
or anything like that.
It's all done
through the typing.
OK. So that's Mendler-Style.
Now Mendler-Style paramorphic
recursion universe.
So this is the next sort
of step that presenting
sort of a conceptual development
of this idea of Cedille's
recursion universe.
So for computing X,
from data type D
now for paramorphic recursion,
the universe gives you
the same stuff you had
before the recursion universe
has all these same pieces,
but it also comes
as, highlighted in black,
with a reveal function,
R to D, so this unmasks R
as really being D, OK.
So, but notice you can't
go the other way around.
You cannot inject D into R
that would be totally
unsound from
a termination perspective.
'Cause you could just
stick random values into R
and the recurse on them.
But here you,
you are allowed to sort of
leave the recursion universe.
You can sort of, you know,
I don't know wormhole
out of there
if you want to,
to have some data D,
and this is really important.
If you wanna write
efficient accessor
functions like predecessor
or tail or something.
Now finally, what we need
for the Harper's
regular expression matcher
is we need support
for nested recursion.
So you have all the same stuff
we had before,
except we change a little bit,
the return type
of your function.
Now couldn't is now
could depend on D.
So you compute X of D
from a data type D
and the, the reason
that's really important to shift,
as I see it say below
my bullet points there
from X of kind star,
to X of kind star to star,
is it now the eval function,
you can write eval function
that goes from R to X of R.
And that gives you
the possibility of seeing
when you return something
from your recursive call,
that it also has
type R and hence,
you could make
a recursive call again on that.
So a recursion is then allowed
on values that
Val has returned.
So that enables a form
of nested recursion,
and the continuations
are basically hiding
a form of nested recursion.
OK. So let's take
a look at how we do
this in Cedille
Harper's match in Cedille.
So, the critical part
about the nested
recursion is here.
So in,
In blue, I've had,
it's Cedille syntax
for indicating the abstract type R,
if we're doing
a recursion here,
mu match, then mu
is for the sort of
kicking off recursion
then type/match is R
That's the abstract type
of the recursion universe.
And the X, the type
we're computing here
has to be given explicitly
Cedille can't
infer this for you.
And it can mention this R,
and that's just like XR, XD.
Now we have
a way of mentioning
we're indicating
the functionality of X
and X does have to be
positive for this to work.
And finally where
the eval function
is conveniently called match.
And so it looks,
this looks very much like
an idiomatic recursion.
Now, here, we're doing
something it'd be tough
to do in other type theories
where passing the recursive
the recursive function match
there to the helper
function matchi,
but anyway,
that match is the eval
and it has the type below
it takes in the abstract type R
which here is denoted
type/match and proceeds.
OK. So that's sort
of the setup for the recursion,
introducing, the recursion
universe pieces
that we then need
to write this helper function
and make that deal with that
one nasty recursive call.
So you can see
highlighted here,
it's transliterated
into Cedille.
I hope you can sort of
still make out the structure.
We have a plus R case
and that I pulled out here
and we were gonna
make this recursive call
to check one
occurrence of R,
and, then in the end,
when we make
the recursive call
we're calling and match cs prime,
and that's great,
this match function is,
is actually coming in to matchi
As you saw it,
where matchi was invoked
in my previous slide,
this match functions
coming into matchi
and it's expecting type T
where T is actually
just some abstract type.
You really don't need
to know much about it,
except we can recurse on it.
If you're looking
at the type signature
of matchi at the top,
we can recurse on it.
And the suffix comes
in at that time.
And so when we call
match of CS prime, match
is expecting input of type
T and CS prime has type T
because CS prime
is the input to the continuation.
And the continuation
is denoted there
in blue has type KT,
which is T to bool.
OK. So to conclude,
we've talked about
Harper's regular
expression matcher,
which uses continuations
for very elegant control flow
that leads to complications
for termination reasoning.
And we saw a solution now using
strong functional programming
in Cedille,
it's type based.
There's no fancy,
extra additions
beyond regular types
of functional programming,
no dependent types,
nothing like that,
even though Cedille
does support those separately.
So we use this idea
of a recursion universe that,
that gives you a form
of type based nested
paramorphic recursion.
And it turns out that
Harper's matcher is just
a perfect fit for this.
It's very easy.
We don't have time
to wade through
all the code,
but it's really pretty much
a direct port of the
Haskell code
because of the way
that the abstract type
for the eval function
matches up perfectly
with the inputs
for the continuation.
So thanks very much to funders,
and I'd really like to thank
the very dedicated
anonymous ICFP reviewers
who gave us
outstanding really
above and beyond
kind of criticism
and help getting this
into good shape
and shepherd Richard Eisenberg
and colleagues
here at Iowa.
And thanks to you
for watching.
(APPLAUSE)
RICHARD: Great,
thanks, Aaron.
And now in the New York
and Asia time band,
we have authors available
for question and answer.
So please follow
the links via Clowdr,
if you wish to join them.
We'll take a brief pause
until the next talk at 11:45
in the New York time band.
Next up we have Nandor Licker
who will present Duplo,
a framework for
Ocaml post-link optimization.
NANDOR LICKER: Hello,
my name is Nandor Licker
And today I'm going to talk
about Duplo a framework
for Ocaml post link optimization.
I built with Dr. Tim Jones
at the university of Cambridge.
Why build a post link optimizer?
And why build one
for Ocaml in particular.
Ocaml is a high level language,
which means that it is not
well suited for expressing
specific low-level constructs
as an example,
we consider a simple type
to represent complex numbers,
composed of an imaginary
and a real component.
If we declare
a complex number
as a pair of floats,
we ended up
with many allocations,
even though we only care
about eight bytes of data
to store two 32 bit floats,
the object will be spread
across 56 bytes
and three distinct allocations
producing three distinct blocks
on the heap.
Ideally, we'd like
a single block with a header
and eight bytes of data.
So how do we get there?
We can write a lot of code,
possibly fiddling with bits
and express the type
in Ocaml.
However, the solution
is unlikely to be elegent.
We could also change
the runtime or the compiler.
However, this is not
practical nor scalable,
and could become
a maintenance nightmare.
We choose to instead
use an existing
language feature namely
the foreign function interface,
the FFI allows us to use
the right tool for the right job.
We can express
low level constructs
in C and call them
from Ocaml.
The FFI of Ocaml
is particularly powerful.
Thanks to its minimal runtime
and simple object representation.
This allows us
to read arbitrary objects
from the Ocaml heap
and also to allocate
arbitrary objects
on the Ocaml heap.
Such features allow the FFI
to be flexible enough
to build a wide variety
of types and functions.
However, the FFI
does not come for free.
Besides the implicit trampolines
that heap management code
requires to invoke
C from Ocaml,
we pay the cost of missed
optimization opportunities.
In the typical build, Ocaml
and C meet in assembly
and the linker unfortunately
high level transformations
in machine code
are far from trivial.
We need a common form,
more suitable for analysis,
ideally, a representation
that has not yet gone
through register allocation
nor instruction selection.
So the goal of Duplo is to
ameliorate this FFI overhead
and to lose the overhead,
we want to optimize
across the language boundary.
However, on one side,
we have a Ocaml
and C on the other.
Two very different languages
with different memory models
and different run times.
In order to apply
any optimizations,
we need to first find
a common denominator
capable of capturing
the semantics of both
C and Ocaml.
Duplo achieves this
with representation,
we call LLIR, low level
intermediate representation.
The framework provides
a custom version
of (INAUDIBLE) to LLIR
of the Ocaml compiler
to lower Ocaml to LLIR
and an entire tool chain
turning LLIR modules
into a single module containing
whole program information.
And finally an optimizer,
which we call LLIR opt
to analyze and transform
the program
before lowering it
to executable machine code.
LLIR is the central
component of our project.
It is built to be easy to optimize.
It is in SSA form
has virtual registers,
simple instructions
and primitive types
with direct hardware equivalents,
even though it is not LLVM IR
it's in their representation
in C++ is almost
identical to LLVM IR.
Mirroring several useful methods
and we're using support libraries,
including valuable functions
and iterators
such as dominator reconstruction.
And (INAUDIBLE) traversals.
We find a cool style
of our transformations
to be quite similar
to that of LLVM.
And this familiarity
is highly valuable.
Despite some similarities LLVM
is definitely not LLVM IR.
It is less abstract
and a lot closer to hardware.
Why is LLIR low level?
This choice is almost
entirely constrained
by the Ocaml compiler
and the intermediate
representations found in clang.
Ocaml first compiles
to Lambda form
with closures,
which have no direct
equivalent in LLVM.
Requires to step one level down
in the Ocaml compiler.
The next step is CMM,
which still has
some high level features.
So we need to go
down another level.
We are left with building
LLIR from Mach Linear,
which are essentially
equivalent to machine code,
LLVM IR is more
abstract than that.
We need to lower it
a bit in LLVM.
Conveniently, we defined LLIR
to be almost like machine code.
We lower LLVM IR
to LLIR to the target
specific backend of LLVM
passing through
selection DAG and LLIR
specific machine IR.
On the Ocaml side.
We generate LLIR
from linear as the mapping
is almost one to one.
We are essentially
cross-compiling
to a new target
in both compilers.
Getting to LLIR
is only the start of the journey.
We also need to generate
machine code from LLIR.
And this step is not trivial.
Code generators
tend to be complex
pieces of code
and Ocaml has run time
and a garbage collector
that we do not wish
to alter that imposes
further constraints.
Since our tool chain
already includes clang
We decided to use
the LLVM code generator
from its selection diagram
presentation onwards.
We have added
custom instructions
required by the Ocaml GC
we're using the entirety
of the target-specific
machine IR pipeline.
Since we cross compile C to LLIR,
we have a mapping
from a selection DAG to LLIR,
in our backend,
we map LLIR to selection DAG
due to the circular dependency.
Most of the LLIR instructions
have a direct correspondent
in selection DAG
with the exception
of some more
complex constructs,
such as function calls
and 80 bits floats.
Simple instructions such as
add, subtract, multiply, and so on.
Do not really warrant
a custom mapping
from selection DAG
to LLIR, nor from
LILR to selection DAG.
So, we simply map selection DAG,
to LLIR instruction,
and LLIR instruction
back to selection DAG
but function calls
are specific to each target.
And even in all of LLVMs backends,
they require a custom mapping
from LLVM IR to selection DAG,
and we have that mapping
for LLIR as well.
And because
of these constraints,
we actually had
very little freedom
when designing
our new representation.
Probably the most
pressing question
is why not lower to LLVM IR.
Previous attempts
made some progress
albeit with
a run time cost,
Ocaml is not
an easy language
to map to LLVM
it's exception handling
requires explicit
stack manipulation
Ocaml also has
a shadow stack
for root pointers.
This aspect is crucial
for performance
while LLVM offers some support
for garbage collectors.
It does not get
a specific to the needs
of Ocaml. Through Duplo
we made significant progress though.
We have added
the required instruction
to a single portion
of the target specific pipeline
in order to handle
the frame tables used by the,
the default Ocaml
garbage collector and run time.
However, to achieve
the same ideal at the LLVM IR level,
extensive changes
are required.
To illustrate LLIR,
we can look at the simple methods
in LLIR form,
which confused the magnitude
of a vector allocated
on your Ocaml heap.
It reads an argument,
a pointer to a pair
using an arg instruction.
Individual elements
are loaded using LD
from offsets computed
using basic pointer arithmetic,
the elements of squared
using the multiply instruction,
are passed on to the sqrt function
before being boxed
into a heap allocated.
block, we can
notice the annotations,
the Ocaml runtime requires us
to identify all heap pointers,
which we do using @camel_value.
And emit frame tables
describing those which are live
across call sites that can allocate,
all marked through @caml_frame.
Finding a common representation
is the only part of the problem.
In this representation,
optimizations,
opportunities to prefer
optimizations should be scarce
Ocaml should have
already optimized everything
LLVM should have also
optimized everything,
and we are left with
the nontrivial task
of identifying optimization
opportunities
that are exposed only when both Ocaml
and C sources are present.
Naturally, the first step is
to create optimization
opportunities for other steps.
Inlining achieves this,
unfortunately, inlining
in this context
is not as simple as copying
a body into a callee.
The world is split into two
realms: Ocaml and C,
the two communicate through a trampoline
recording vital information
for the runtime.
When we inline C into Ocaml,
we actually create
a bigger Ocaml function
and push the trampolines down.
Even though G initially called
F without a trampoline,
after in-lining, it requires
one, each kind of allocation,
doesn't need one, in Carmel FF,
we are left with a mess.
The function now tracks heap
roots using both Carmel values
and the specific root measurement
mechanism specific to C.
In the future, we aim to
address this problem
by moving roots over to
the Carmel value mechanism.
This is a great improvement
since it eliminates the upfront
cost of root management,
that's necessary in C.
As your global information,
in the future,
we will also build to
move C functions,
which allocate over
to the Ocaml realm.
First simplify manual
root management,
and possibly ending up on
using Ocaml value annotations
to identify roots.
While you're not there
yet, at some point,
we will be able to not care
about whether our function
is Ocaml specific or C
specific erasing the boundary
between the two heaps.
To illustrate some more problems,
we consider a function that
increments of double,
unboxing a value, adding one
to it and boxing it back,
sending it back to the OCaml heap.
After in-lining,
we see that the boxing
Ocaml copy double call
is now annotated,
and it has a trampoline.
But what happens if we inline
two consecutive invocations?
Unfortunately, we get the chain
of boxing unboxing steps.
This is expected
and quite unfortunate.
We are now faced with
the nontrivial task
of understanding pointers
and blocks on the heap
to perform even
a simple transformation,
such as constant propagation.
And the stage we are at in
the pipeline does not help,
the common ground between C
and OCaml memory
representations
is not particularly verbose.
We can work only with the assumption
that pointers have stored
at addresses aligned to eight bytes.
We essentially have no
type of information.
And if, even if we have
type information,
due to the fact that C has unions,
the type information you could
possibly keep would be minimal,
and the only piece of
information we'll be left with
is this fact that pointers
are aligned to eight bytes,
which allows us to model
the heap as bags of pointers
aligned as specific addresses.
As a proof of concept, we have
built two transformations
working with pointers.
A local analisys to propagate
value store to memory
to loads reading them
and a global analysis to
identify indirect call targets
essential for dead code elimination.
Presently, our optimizer
implements a number
of classic transformations
which are recquired
mostly to eliminate inefficiencies
in the C, OCaml, LLIR lowering.
While we have exposed
many new opportunities,
our goal for the moment
was to implement
the minimal battery of
transformations required
to emit code as fast as,
at least as fast as
it was emitted by,
OCaml and C previously.
The other transformations
include sparse condition
and constant propagation,
unreachable code elimination
control flow simplification
and these are schedules
after inlining
and simplify
the program quite a bit.
Tail recursion elimination is vital.
LLVM cannot lower direct tail recursion
as effectively as OCaml,
but it generates identical code
if these functions are
turned into loops instead.
An interesting transformation
specific to this context
is trampoline elimination.
OCaml requires a trampoline
to switch from
the OCaml calling convention
to the C calling
convention when invoking
a C method indirectly.
Since you have global information,
we can change the calling
convention of C method
to the OCaml one,
completely eliminating
these trampolines.
These transformations,
along with the LLVM cde generator
provide some benefit.
We benchmarked our optimizer
on a subset of benchmarks
from operf-macro
and operf-micro.
Unfortunately, we did not yet
implement some optimizations
performed by the OCaml compiler
which we have disabled in
our reference version.
We do not cache some
globals in registers
and we do not inline allocations.
Despite these mitigations,
the relative results should
still be relevant.
Our linker delivers
a significant reduction
in code size while LLVM manages
to select better instructions
providing some improvement
on large informations
and we're quite happy
about these results.
When comparing
the fact of the small set
of transformations we
have implemented,
the effect is moderate.
There are not many opportunities
for cross-language optimization
as our in-line heuristics
and (INAUDIBLE) analysis
are quite primitive.
As an example, we currently
inline aggressively functions
which box or
deconstruct arguments
in the hope of propagating
constants through them.
In the future, we have to
build better huristics
to base our inline decision on how,
for the purpose of this project,
the difficultly was in figuring out
how to do inlining
in the first place.
We do gain in performance a bit
by mitigating inefficiencies
in both back ends
and inlining some small
methods through the
battery of transformations
we have presented earlier.
To sum up, we have presented
a Duplo framework
to inline C into OCaml,
analyzing and transforming
the resulting code.
We built a new representation
to capture both
OCaml and C which we call LLIR.
Finally, as our code generator,
we assure how OCaml can be lowered
to part of the LLVM pipeline,
yielding and improving in
code size and performance.
(CROWN APPLAUDS)
RICHARD: Thanks very much, Nandor,
who's now available in
the New York Time Band
for question and answer,
you can click the link in Clowdr.
Now we have Vikraman Choudhury
discussing how to embed
purity in an impure language
via the use of a comonad.
VIKRAMAN: Hello, I'm
Vikraman Choudhury,
and I'm going to be presenting
some joint work with Neel
Krishnaswami on our paper,
'Recovering Purity With
Comonads and Capabilities'.
The basic problem in this
paper is the following,
we've known for a while
now how to extend
a purely functional
language with monads
to encode side effects.
However, what if we already have
an impure functional language?
Can we extend the type system
to encode the absence of effects?
So let's try to motivate
why you such a thing might be
useful with some examples.
Consider a strict call
by value language,
which allows side effects
and let's consider
the map functional.
So map is a higher order function,
which takes the function F
and applies it to every
element of the list,
because there are at least two
different ways of writing map.
In map one,
we recursively call map one
on the tail of the list
before evaluating F on
the head of the list.
And in map two,
we evaluate F on
the head of the list
before recursively calling
map two on the tail of the list.
So these two functions
should be equal,
but in an impure language like this,
they can have different
side effects.
So, as an example,
let's evaluate map one and map
two on the following inputs.
So here F is the identity
function on strings,
but it's impure.
It prints its input
string to standard out
before returning it.
So let's try to use map one.
We expand the let and we observe
that it reaches the end of the list
when it tries to evaluate
F on the string right.
So this prints, right.
Reducing more where you see
that it calls F on to,
which prints to,
and then it calls F on left,
which prints left
and finally it
returns the original list.
So it produced a side effect
where it printed right to left.
If however, we reduce map
two on the same inputs,
we notice that it evaluates
f first on the string left,
then on the string to
and then on right,
and finally returns
the original list.
So even though both of
these map functions
return the same output,
they produce different side effects.
Alternatively consider
these two functions f and g
from int to int.
They perform different side effects
before returning their output.
Now, suppose we map g on xs,
followed by mapping f on the output,
and optimizing compiler
could perform map fusion
on this expression.
But in this impure language,
if we mapped f compose g on xs,
that would produce
a different side effect.
So this map fusion optimization
pass would be invalid.
So I hope these examples
are motivating
and they show that it
would indeed be useful
to be able to encode
the absence of effects
in an impure language.
So first let's see how
effects are being encoded
in this language with some examples.
Let's consider the function g.
It takes the channel c, a string s,
prints s on the channel
c, then returns s.
So this function is impure
because it uses the channel
it was passed to,
to perform an effect.
Now consider this function
f from string to string.
This is also impure,
but it is defined by partially
applying g to standard out.
Now standard out is
a channel that's available
in the global environment.
So there's a difference
between f and g.
g isn't safe,
because it uses the channel
that was passed as an argument.
But f uses standard
out which is used
from the global environment.
So, this gives us an idea,
we should be able to
control the use of effects
by controlling the channel variables
that a function has access
to in its environment.
So we were interested in purity,
but we can refine this to
a different notion of safety.
So we formalize this idea using
the notion of capabilities.
So capabilities are
a well known thing
in the systems
programming community.
A capability is defined to
be a token of authority,
for example, a security token
or a permission
in our impure language.
A channel variable, for
example, standard out
is a capability.
Then we define the notion
of capability safety.
We say that a program
is capability safe
when it only performs effects
using the capabilities
it has access to at runtime.
So for example, this function
G is capability safe,
but F is not.
But G is not pure, it's only safe.
So, we'll come back to how
we could encode purity using safety.
But for now, let's try to extend
our language with safety.
So first, we want to distinguish
between two kinds of variables,
safe variables and impure variables.
Safe variables, are capability
safe and impure variables
are just arbitrary
variables in our language.
So we use these qualifiers,
S or I in blue and red
to annotate the bindings of
variables in our context.
Then, we would like to
internalize the notion of safety
using a safe type constructor.
We add a box type constructor
and we add two new term
formers, box and let box.
So, these are expressions and
we distinguish between
expressions and values.
Boxing an expression
turns it into a value.
We also have a new safety judgment
which we use to judge
whether a term E of type A
is safe in context gamma.
So now we want to ensure
that safe variables
can only depend on
other safe variables.
So we add a sub structural
operation on our contexts,
so this purify operation
drops all the impure
variables in our context.
Then, if we know that
a term is well typed
in a safe context, we
know that it's safe.
And if we know that a term is safe,
we can put it inside the box
using our box introduction rule.
And finally, we also have
a let box elimination rule
for our box type constructor.
So if E1 is a boxed term,
we can bind to
the underlying value X.
And we can eliminate to E2
if it is well typed in
the extended context,
where X is marked with
a safe annotation.
So these were the additional
typing rules for the box type.
Let's also take a quick look
at the other typing rules.
The rules for variables
remains essentially unchanged.
For functions, to introduce a lambda
we allow the bound
variable to be impure.
So that we can substitute
arbitrary expressions.
The Lambda application
rule remains the same.
And then finally, the rule for
print is just as expected.
It's simply a unit.
Now, at this point we note
that this box constructor
is a comonad.
It has a co-unit,
and it has a co-multiplication.
And in fact, our syntax
for adding comonads
to our type theory is inspired
by the classic Pfenning Davies
paper on the judgemental
reconstruction of S4 modal logic.
Instead of a dual context,
we use annotations on our variables.
And for more details on
the syntax, see our paper.
So coming back to our
original motivation,
can we used this notion of
safety to recover purity?
Well, we say that a function
is pure if it is safe
and it has access to zero
capabilities in its environment.
So box of A arrow B is
the type of safe functions
but they're not necessarily pure.
And box of box of A arrow
B is the the type of pure functions.
So going back to our
original example,
we can now write a pure variant
of our map one
and map two functions.
We force the function
argument to be pure
and it should be only applied
to a list of safe expressions.
We can use box and let
box to rewrite the body
of map one and map two.
So using this new definition
for map one and map two,
we can show that they
are provably equal
in the extended calculus.
Finally to conclude, let me
point out some of the main
takeaways from this talk.
First, we can use this notion
of capabilities to control effects,
and to control the usage of effects.
This idea of capability
safety or denying the usage
of a capability from
the environment can be captured
using a comonad
type discipline.
Let me also highlight some
of the technical results
in our paper.
We formalize an effectful
calculus and we extended
with a safety modality and we
show how to do substitution
and so on.
We show how to recover purity
from capability safety.
And we also discussed how
to do capability taming.
That is, how to implementally
add safety to an already
impure language or a library.
We give a categorical
semantics for this language.
It is given by a cartesian
closed category
with a monad
and a comonad
which interact with each other.
We give a construction of
capability spaces,
which give us
a denotational semantics,
which satisfies the axiomatic
categorical structure
that we need for our semantics.
The idea of this
construction in fact
comes from an old paper
of Martin Hoffman.
Also capability spaces
have more structure
than we actually use
for our semantics.
It can be used to give
the model of linear type theory,
which we discussed in the paper.
We also give the full equational
theory for this calculus
and we use our
denotational semantics
to prove its soundness.
Finally, we also show how to embed
the pure simply-typed
lambda calculus
into our language, using
this comonadic modality.
This embedding, preserves
the equational theory
of the pure STLC.
Also, we show that our language
is a conservative extension
of the STLC.
This is a requirement for
a purely functional language
that Amr Sabry told us
about a long time ago.
And yeah, that's all I had to say.
Please see the extended
version of our paper
if you're interested
and thank you very much
for listening.
(AUDIENCE CLAPS)
RICHARD: Thanks Vikraman.
He is now available in both
the New York and Asia time bands
for question and answer.
I will take a brief pause
for the next talk at 12:15
in the New York time band.
Next up, we have Xiaohong
Chen to present
a general approach to define
binders using matching logic.
XIAOHONG CHEN: Hello everyone.
Welcome to this video.
My name is Xiaohong Chen.
My talk today is about
a general approach to define
binders using matching logic.
This is a joint work
with my supervisor
Professor Grigore Rosu.
Our papers can be found
at the links below.
The technical report includes
all the proof details
in the appendix.
The main motivation of the work
is the K formal semantic framework
and its logical foundation,
matching logic.
The K framework allows users to
define the formal semantics
of any programming languages.
As shown in the picture, once
the semantics is defined,
all language tools
such as parsers, interpreters,
and verifiers are
automatically generated by K.
In practice, K has been used
to define
the formal semantics
of many real world languages,
such as C, Java
and JavaScript.
K allows users to define
the common language features
easily, including binders.
For example, the following K
definition defines the syntax
of lambda calculus.
An expression is either a variable
or an expression applied
to another expression
or has the form lambda var.e.
The binder is an attribute,
which will trigger the internal
decision mechanism in K
to provide the correct implementation
of capture avoiding substitution.
Currently, this only works
for a restricted form
of binders but with this paper,
we can give the binding attributes
a clean, mathematical explanation,
which will make K to support
more general binders
in the future.
Mathematically speaking,
every K definition
is a logical theory of matching logic
where the syntax and semantics
of a programming language
are defined using
matching logic axioms.
So our job in this paper
is to show how to define binders
as matching logic theories.
Matching logic is expressive.
Many important logical
systems can be defined
as matching logic theories.
These include first logic,
separation logic, Hoare
logic for verification,
temporal logics,
and many others.
However no logical systems where
binding plays a major role
have been thoroughly
defined in matching logic
until this paper.
In this paper, we studied
the typical systems
that include binders,
such as lambda calculus
and type systems.
We defined them as
matching logic theories
and we proved that our
definitions are correct
by showing that they
preserve the syntax,
semantics and formal reasoning
of the target system.
Here is an overview of
the main contribution
of the paper.
Firstly, we simplify matching logic
and propose a variant
that is more suitable
to define binders.
Secondly, we use lambda
calculus as an example
and define it as a machine
logic theory, gamma lambda.
The key observation
is then lambda XE
does two things at a time.
It creates the binding of X in E
and also builds a term,
lambda XE.
In matching logic, we
separate these two.
We first use bracket XE
to define the graph of the function
that maps X to E.
Here, XE is the pair of X and E
and the matching logic
exists means union.
So this pattern is
the set of all pairs XE
where X ranges over the variables.
The intention packs
the graph set into one element,
which then includes all
the binding information.
Then we define lambda XE by
applying the construct to lambda
to the graph set XE.
The constructor builds the term.
In short, we use the built-in
exist binder of matching logic
to build a graph set
and create a binding
and then use constructors
to build the term.
To show that the above
definition is indeed correct,
we prove the following theorems.
We proof that gamma lambda
is a conservative extension
of lambda calculus.
So any equations between
two lambda expressions
are provable in lambda calculus
if and only if they are probable
in theory gamma lambda.
We also show that gamma lambda
is sound and complete.
So semantic validity
and provability coincide.
One important advantage
of our approach
is that the theory gamma
lambda automatically
gives a class of
matching logic models
and the following two theorems
connect those models
to lambda calculus.
The representative
completeness states
that for any lambda theory, t,
which is a set of lambda equations,
there is a model MT of
theory gamma lambda,
such that MT captures
precisely the lambda theory t.
That is E1 equals E2
is provable in t,
if and only if it holds in MT.
The last theorem states
that for any lambda
calculus model A,
there is a matching logic model, MA,
of the theory gamma
lambda that captures A.
Lambda calculus has
many different models.
In this paper, we
consider the models
that are concrete Cartesian
closed categories
or called concrete CCC models.
The technical details can
be found in the paper.
To sum up, our definition
of lambda calculus
that first creates the binding
and then, builds the term is correct
and captures lambda
calculus faithfully.
Then at the end of the paper,
we generalize it to other systems
with binders, such as system F,
pure type systems, et cetera.
In the following, I'll give
a high-level overview
of matching logic,
including the syntax semantics
and then as an example,
I'll define lambda calculus
in matching logic.
Due to time limit,
I won't discuss the generalization
part in this talk.
However, I'll be happy to
address it in the Q&A session.
Matching logic is a very
simple and minimal
and yet, expressive logic.
It is the logical foundation
of the K framework.
Its syntax defines formulas,
which we call patterns,
using only certain constructs.
They are element variables,
which are like first logic variables
that range over elements.
Set variables, which are like
propositional variables
in modal logic that
range over subsets.
Symbols are like set variables,
except that their
interpretations are fixed
by the models and do not change.
Phi one, phi two is
the application value
where we apply phi one to phi two.
if phi one is
a functional constructor,
then the result is like
a first logic term.
If phi one is a predicate,
then the result is like
a first logic (INAUDIBLE) formula
but in general, any
pattern can be applied
to any other pattern,
giving matching logic
maximum flexibility.
Next to constructs,
bottom and implication
are standard propositional
constraints.
Other propositional operations
can be defined from these two.
Finally exists x phi
is the existential quantification
like in first-order logic.
Now, we move on to the semantics.
The semantics of matching
logic is one sentence,
a pattern phi is interpreted
as the set of elements
that match it, in other
words, patterns mean sets.
Formerly, a model M has
a non-empty carrier set
and binary application
function from M x M
to the power set of M,
which will be used to interpret
the application pattern.
Each symbol is also
interpreted as a subset of M.
Now, given a valuation that
assigns element variables
to elements and set
variables to sets,
the pattern interpretation
phi rho is defined like this,
for example, x evaluates
to the elements rho of x,
sigma evaluates to
the interpretation, sigma M,
bottom evaluates to the empty set,
meaning that no
elements can match it.
Application is interpreted
using the application function,
but now phi one
and phi two are also sets,
we range over their
inhabitants by a1 and a2
and take the union
of all the results,
this is called
the point wise extension.
Finally, exists x phi is interpreted
by ranging over all elements a in n,
and taking the big union of
all the resulting sets,
in short, exists means big
union in matching logic.
In matching logic,
we use theories to capture
the target logical systems
such as lambda calculus,
a theory consists of two components,
a set of symbols
and a set of axioms
that define the behavior
of the symbols.
We also define notations which
are just syntactic sugar.
With the proper notations,
we can capture the formulas
of those expressions
in the target system as is
without any translation.
We say that a model M is
a model of the theory, gamma,
if all axioms hold in a model,
that is they are interpreted
to the total sets,
then for each theory, we have
a class of these models
whose properties can be
expressed by patterns
for gamma to correctly
capture the target system,
we need to establish an equivalence
between the models of gamma
and the models of the target system.
Then, we can use matching
logic patterns to express
and reason about the properties
about the target system.
In section four of the paper,
we define the matching logic theories
that captures many important
mathematical concepts
such as equality, membership,
the concept of sorts
and many sorted functions,
pairs and the power
sort two to the s,
whose elements are the sets
of elements of sort s.
Based on these
infrastructure definitions,
we now define binders
in matching logic.
We define the theory gamma lambda
that captures lambda calculus
due to time limits are only
showed intuitive ideas.
Intuitively, the lambda
abstraction, lambda Xe,
creates infinitely many alpha
equivalent representations,
lambda X1 e, X1 substitutes for X, etc.
Our idea is to
capture these representations.
To do that we construct
an argument value pair
where the first argument
is the variable
and the second is
the substituted expression.
Then we define this
existential pattern.
Recall that semantics of existing
matching logic means set union.
So this pattern means
the union of all pairs.
In other words this pattern
is the graph of the function
that maps x into e.
To wrap up the definition we take
the intension of the graph set.
The intension of a set
equals to the set itself
but the set is no longer regarded
as a collection of elements
but as a single element
in a power set domain.
This way we can avoid
the pointwise extension
when we apply the constructed
lambda to the set.
We introduce a notation (x, e) to
mean the intension of the graph set
which is one element
that includes all the binding
information of x into e.
And finally, we define lambda x,
e as the application pattern
where the constructed lambda is
applied to the graph set (x, e).
In short, to define
lambda abstraction
we first use the building binder
exist to define the graph set
and capture the binding behavior
then we build the lambda
term using the constructor
and matching logic application.
The correctness of
the definition means that
the encoding from lambda
calculus to matching logic
is faithful with respect
to the syntax semantics
and the formal reasoning
of Lambda Calculus.
In terms of the syntax,
matching logic captures
lambda expressions verbatim.
The lambda abstraction
becomes this pattern
where we use lambda to build a term
and use (x, e) which is
the graph set to build the binding.
In lambda calculus formal reasoning
means equational reasoning
thus the beta-reduction rule.
To capture that we
add beta reduction
as an axiom schema to
the theory lambda
then we can prove that gamma lambda
indeed captures lambda
calculus faithfully
in the sense that lambda
calculus reasoning
is equivalent to the matching
logic formal reasoning
within the theory gamma lambda
and is also equivalent to
the semantic validity
within the theory gamma lambda.
To conclude in this paper
we gave a generic way to dealing
with binding using matching logic.
Since matching logic is
the logic foundation of K
our work is useful to
the development of K.
In the paper we proposed
a simple matching logic variant
that has only 7 synthetic constructs
and with fully developed
models and proof theories.
Then we defined the matching
logic theory for lambda calculus
where lambda abstraction is defined
by applying the construct lambda
to the graph set (x, e).
We proved the correctness
of this definition
by showing the equivalence
among the validity
and the provability of lambda
calculus and matching logic.
Finally, we extending our approach
to all binders in a systematic way
where the details can
be found in the paper.
Due to the time limit,
I cannot fully cover all
technical details in this talk.
The paper and the companion technical
report contain all the details.
I am happy to answer any questions
about the work in the Q&A session.
Thank you for watching.
RICHARD: Thanks very much Xiaohong,
who is now available in both
the New York and Asian time bands
for question and answer.
Next up we have Pierce Darragh
presenting Parsing with Zippers,
a Functional Pearl.
PIERCE DARRAGH: Hello, thank you
for watching my talk.
My name is Pierce Darragh
and I will be walking you
through parsing with zippers,
a functional pearl written
by Michael D. Adams and me.
So let's get to it.
Parsing with zippers is
an extension of the earlier work
of parsing with derivatives
which we'll call PwD for short.
We address an underlying
inefficiency in PwD's algorithm
by implementing a new
generalized form of the zipper
and using it to manage derivations.
Our resulting algorithm
is significantly faster
than the original
PwD implementation,
measurably faster than
the optimized PwD implementation
of Adams et al in 2015
and it is only around 100 lines of
OCami cord when fully implemented.
The primary contribution of
parsing with derivatives
was the generalized
Brzozowski's derivatives
from regular expressions
to context free grammars.
This is not trivial.
The Brzozowski derivative
uses two eager algorithms
perfectly fine for regular
languages but not so with CFGs
which have recursion.
PwD introduced laziness to fix most
of for one of those algorithms
and memoization
and fixed points for the other.
The result is
an algorithm that is elegant
in its theoretical simplicity
and which can also
produce full parse trees
instead of only recognizing inputs
as Brzozowski derivatives do.
Let's see a brief example
of PwD in action.
We start with a grammar consisting
of a root concatenation node
shown with the circle-like
concatenation operator
that has two children
concatenation nodes
each of which has two
children token nodes.
This grammar parses only
the string a,b,c,d.
We will attempt to parse that string
shown disassembled in
the tokens at the top.
We take the first token from
the input string labeling it current
then we derive the grammar
beginning at the root node.
At each step a pattern match is run
to determine what to do
with the current node.
The derivative proceeds
down the left side
of each concatenation node
as it attempts to find
a token node.
Eventually it finds
the first token node, a.
When the algorithm
comes to a token node
it attempts to match that
token to the current token
that we are taking the derivative
of the grammar with respect to,
in this case also a.
Because the tokens match
we replace the token grammar
expression with a lambda
indicating a successful parse.
Since we have successfully derived
the grammar with respect to a
let's proceed and attempt to derive
the result with respect to b.
Again we being our search
at the root of the grammar
exploring each node and sequence
until we find
an unmatched token node.
In this case, the traversal down to
the lambda will be thrown away
so I am only showing the traversal
down towards the b node.
Because the current token
and the found token node matched
we replace the node with a lambda
node and return a new grammar.
We'll stop the parsing
example at this point.
The take away is that
each derivative
will start at the root of
the previous derivative result grammar.
In this simple example, this
only means one extra step
but with more complex
grammar with many layers
it can be very many steps.
This is wasted effort.
Most often subsequent derivatives
need to essentially resume
from where the previous
derivative left off.
The PwD algorithm does
not account for this
and so it spends a lot of time
on redundant traversals.
To avoid this we'll
employ the zipper.
The zipper is a functional data
structure for navigating trees
introduced by Huet in 1997.
We start with a simple definition
for a tree data type
consisting of either
an item which is leaf node
or a section which is a branch.
Next we introduce the path.
A path is essentially a context.
It represents the part of the tree
which has essentially been traversed
and also keeps track of
siblings of the subtree
currently being focused on.
Last we have the location which
is really the zipper itself.
This is a pair of a path
with the focused-on subtree
which is generally referred to
as the focus of the zipper.
To solidify this concept let
us look at the visualization.
In this diagram blue
squares represent paths,
yellow triangles
represent tree nodes
and the red circle is the zipper.
The red arrow going down from
the zipper is the focus expression
and the black arrow going
up points to the path.
I'll take a few steps with the tree.
We begin by doing down
through the subtree t1.
When we go down into
a concatenation node
a new node path will be created
representing the path back up
through that concatenation node.
This will be attached to the zipper
which will be focused on the first
child of the concatenation node
t2 in this case.
The remaining children t3 and t4
are in the node paths
right siblings list.
We are not limited traversing
the tree a specific order.
We can immediately move to right
without going at any
other direction.
Notice that a new node
path is constructed
which has t2 as the left
sibling of the focus
and t4 as the right sibling.
If we go down through t3 we'll
create a new node path c3
which itself points up to c2.
Because t3 had no siblings
the left and right sibling
lists in c3 are left empty.
Lastly, we can return up
through a path in this case c3.
When we do this we could create
a new node to replace t3
which is why I've underlined t3
in the diagram at this point.
In any case, a new
zipper is constructed
focusing on the tree node
we just traveled through
with the path back at
the root as always.
This brings us to parsing with
zippers or PwZ for short.
We use zippers to save the location
where the derivative
was successfully taken.
By doing this we eliminate
almost all of the retraversals
in the original parsing
with derivatives algorithm.
We use a slightly modified zipper
definition compared to the original.
For one, we actually call
it a zipper in the code
instead of location.
We also rename tree to exp,
meaning grammar expansions
and path to cxt meaning contexts.
All context constructors
end with a capital C
to indicate their status.
Now there is a problem with our
zipper implementation which is this.
It can't yet handle all
context-free grammars.
It can work fine for concatenation
tokens but that's it.
Many CFGs have alternates and cycles
which are part of what
makes CFG so useful.
We'll have to improve our zipper
if we want to use it
for parsing CFGs.
First, we look at supporting
alternates in the grammar.
This requires adding an alternate
constructor to the exp type
and a corresponding alternate
context constructor to the cxt type.
Here we have a simple grammar.
The inverted triangle labelled
a1 is an alternate node
and t1 and t2 are its children.
They should be processed
independently of one another.
When the zipper moves through
the alternate node a1 it splits.
We get two context
nodes and two zippers
which is exactly what we wanted.
Now the children of
an alternate node
are handled in
a non-deterministic manner.
When we eventually traverse back up,
possibly modifying either or both
of the child nodes in the process
we create a new alternate
node for each child.
These are handled independently
by the algorithm.
For non zipper grammars
the solution is technically sufficient
however, there are
some inefficiencies.
Here we have a situation where
three expressions have been parsed
which all descend to
a share expression t1.
There are three separate zippers
sitting between each of
the associated context
and this t1 expression.
Parsing with the first zipper
creates a new context c4
and a new zipper z4 which
sits between the new context
and the child expression t2.
Parsing with the second zipper
creates an identical context and zipper
but they are separate
from the first ones
and the third zipper
will do the same.
We now have three identical
contexts all labelled c4
and three identical
zippers all labelled z4.
This is wasted effort.
Not only that but if we were to add
support for cycles at this point
the inefficiency could compound
and lead to the number of
zippers becoming exponential
with respect to
the length of the input.
We can't have that.
Here is the code as
we currently have it
but now we'll add memoization.
The memoization entries simply take
the place of the child contexts
within each context type as
well as within the zipper.
We now have a memoization
table shown on the left.
Although the zipper is now actually
pointing upwards to memoization entries
I've shown them here according
to the associated context
for visual simplicity.
When zipper z1 is attempts
to parse into expression t1
we'll add an entry to
the memoization table
so subsequent derivations
do not repeat work.
It is important that the table
entry is added before descending
or else you may still end up
with redundant traversals.
When the first zipper z1 descends
through the expression t1
a new entry is added to
the memoization table indexed
by a pair consisting of
the current input token position
which we will call p here
and the expression.
The Zipper's context c1 is
added to the parent's field.
When the derivative is complete
the result field will be populated
and we will continue parsing
upwards through the parents.
Now, when zipper z2 attempts to
parse through expression t1
it first checks
the memoization table.
If the current input
token position is still p
then the look up
the table will succeed.
Instead of doing any
additional processing
z2 will simply add its current
context c2 to the parent's field.
The last zipper z3 will do the same.
When the child zipper z4
eventually returns from parsing
through the t2 expression
and ascends up through
the context c4
it will split again to
return the computed result
to each of the parent
contexts c1, c2 and c3.
By using this memoization table
we have avoided creating
redundant zippers
when traversing down the grammar.
What happens when we
decide to traverse up?
Here is an example where a zipper
is focused on an alternate
which has not been parsed yet.
So it has no entry in
the memoization table.
The way the algorithm
worked at this point
causes two new zippers to be spanned
each pointing to a new
alt c context node.
Note that both contexts, c2 and c3,
point to the same memoization entry
for the a1 alternate expression
that we just passed through.
Let's say zipper z2
does its work first
and returns up through context c2.
A new alt node is constructed, a2.
This is added to the result
field of the old alternate node,
a1's memoization table entry.
When the second child zipper z3
passes up through context c3
it also creates a new alt node, a3.
This node is also added
to a1's result field.
Two alternate nodes
have been created
and each has spawned a zipper
that will navigate up
through parent context
c1, this is inefficient
and similar to the problem
with unshared expressions
the situation can lead to
an exponential blow-up
in the number of zippers spawned
when deriving over a cyclic grammar.
To address this we will
adjust our memoization code
to also memoize contexts in
addition to expressions.
Because the situation only
arises for alternate nodes
we simply extend the alt constructor
to have a mutable list
of child expressions.
This will allow us to incrementally
update a constructed alt nodes
list of children as new zippers
return up through the tree.
We also now only need
a single expression
to be saved in the result field
of the memoization entry.
Let's see how it works.
We start back at this point
where a zipper has just passed up
through an alt c alternate context
and created a new alternate node a2.
The node is added as the lone
result in the memoization table.
When the second zipper
moves up in the tree
it simply modifies
the existing a2 node.
Now, there is only
one zipper created
above the newly
constructed alternate node
and we have avoided
the potential exponential behavior
we would have had earlier.
While adding memoization to
reduce inefficiencies
I mentioned some concerns
about a hypothetical future
when we support cyclic grammars.
Have no fear, the time
has come to handle cycles
and behold, they are
handled already.
Where recursive descent
parsers face a dilemma
in choosing how times to
descend into a left recursion
we side step the issue entirely.
Our memoization strategy automatically
converts cycles in the grammar
into cycles in the contexts.
This allows us to postpone
making any choices
until further parsing reveals
how many repetitions
are actually needed.
The diagram for this
is a bit complex
so I suggest reading
section 7 of our paper
for more detailed explanation.
With that, the fundamental theory
of our algorithm is laid out
but there remains one more
advancement to discuss
prior to looking at the evaluation.
We can completely eliminate
the memoization tables
and I'll show why.
All our memoization are indexed
by the current input position
but we parse
the input consequentially
so there is never a need
to maintain old entries.
We eliminate
the position as an index
and instead make two
fields in the table entry
to denote the start
and end positions
corresponding to a successful parse.
However, since this table is now
indexed only by an expression
we can actually
eliminate it entirely
and simply put a memoization entry
inside each expression automatically
Here is the code as it existed
with the memoization table.
And here is the code which
eliminates memoization tables.
We now have a new definition of EXP
which contains a memoization record
and an EXP prime which was
previously called EXP.
The memoization entries now record
start and end positions associated
with successful parses
allowing the algorithm
to quickly discern
whether the entry has grown stale.
And with that, the work is done.
Let's briefly look at our
performance evaluation.
We ran parsing with Zippers over
the Python 3.4.3 standard library
and compared the results
to a few other parsers.
Parse derivatives
from Mike et al, 2011.
Optimized parse derivatives
from Adams et al, 2016.
Menhir an LRK parsing
generator from Ocaml
and Deep gen a GLR partial
generator for Ocaml.
The parsing with
derivatives implementation
had to be ported from
Racket to OCaml
and Menhir's LRK limitations
require that we reformulate
some of the Python grammar to
avoid potential ambiguities
that might distort our comparisons.
We run the benchmarks on
the digital ocean droplet
with a dedicated CPU
to ensure we did not introduce
any sources of invalidity
due to other tasks.
The results show that parsing with
zippers significantly outperform
the original parsing with
derivatives algorithm
and even outperforms
the optimized version of PwD
that relies on many low level
tunings and adjustments
to the app algorithm.
Although PWZ does not surpass
the pressure generators in our test
we believe the result
to be significant
because of the simplicity
of the algorithm.
At only around
a hundred lines of code,
parsing with zippers is simple
enough to be written by hand
and yet it is fairly competitive
as long as performance
is not absolutely crucial.
Additionally we claim
parsing with zippers
can handle all context free grammars
even with recursions
and ambiguities
which Menhir cannot do.
So we have introduced
parsing with zippers,
a new general parsing algorithm
that is simple to implement,
it provides surprisingly
good performance.
Parsing with derivatives generalise
the Bruzewski derivative
from regular expressions to
context free grammars.
We have generalized
the zipper from tree structures
to context free grammars.
We also consider
asymptotic complexity,
other divergences from PwD
and a few more points
in the discussion
and evaluation sections of the paper
which I would encourage you to read
if you have further questions
that I did not address.
I hope you have enjoyed this
presentation of parsing with Zippers,
a Function Pearl, by
Pierce Darragh, that's me
and Michael D. Adams.
Please feel free to contact us
if you have any additional
questions or comments.
Thank you.
(APPLAUSE)
RICHARD: Thanks very much Pierce.
In the New York time band,
the authors are now available
for question and answer.
I'm afraid not in
the Asia time band.
OK, last up in this session
we have Timothee Haudebourg
presenting Regular Language Type
Inference with Term Rewriting.
TIMOTHEE HAUDEBOURG: Hello everyone.
My name is Timothee Haudebourg.
And in this presentation we will
be talking about our latest work
on the automatic verification of
higher-order functional programs
where we designed a Regular
language Type Inference system
using term rewriting.
This is joint work with Thomas
Genet and Thomas Jensen
at the French institute for
research and computer science.
And the things that
we have developed
is dedicated to the fully
automatic verification
of higher-order functional program
processing algebraic data
types. What see on this
slide is an example
of what we are going to achieve.
On the left side is a user input.
It is a higher-order
functional program
written for the purpose of
the presentation in OCaml.
It defines a recursive function sort
that implements
an insertion sort algorithms
taking as parameters
a comparison function.
And also a sorted predicate that verifies
that the list is indeed sorted
according to the same
input comparison function.
The right side shows that we imagine
could be the user interface.
Here the user can type in the
property he wants to verify.
So here for example, we want
to verify that for all list l
the output of the sort
function is indeed sorted
according to the corresponding predicate.
Note that the property uses predicates
that are defined in the program
and without any more information
without annotation, we are able to
check if the property is verified
or find a counterexample.
If the property cannot be verified
with a regular abstraction
of the program, it will diverge.
To understand why our
contribution was necessary
in how it relates to
other higher-order functional
program verification techniques
I'd like to place every
technique on this diagram.
Many properties can be verified
by simplifying or abstracting
the behavior of the input
program in a certain way
so we can classify
verification techniques
according to the abstraction
they can generate.
On the bottom we put techniques
that can verify properties
with any regular abstraction.
On the top we put techniques
that can verify property
with any abstraction.
Overall, this axis measures a range
of properties that can be verified
by the technique.
On left to right, we measure
how much a user is active
during the verification.
On the left we have fully
automatic techniques
and on the right manual techniques.
Proof assistants such
as Coq, Isabelle HOL
can be placed in this region.
They can verify a large
range of properties
but require a lot of manual work.
Refinement type inference techniques
which can be seen in
the Liquid types or F star
require less manual work.
So the user only needs
to give some hints
usually as program type annotations
however the range of verifiable
properties is reduced.
Fully automated techniques
have been developed
around higher-order model checking,
predicate abstraction and more.
These techniques do not
require any annotations
but mainly focus on
relational properties
over numerical data types.
And are generally not good at
verifying regular properties
over algebraic data types.
There have been some attempts to
fully automatic verification
of regular properties including
our previous work in Timbuk
although these techniques are
incomplete and not scalable.
In our paper, we
propose a new technique
that is complete on
regular properties
and modular to scale better.
In our work we use term
rewriting systems
to model programs
and their semantics
and we use regular language
of terms as types.
Which we are able to
automatically infer using regular
invariant learning techniques.
Before I detail this type
inference technique
let's start by an introduction
of our theoretical frameworks.
Terms, language and rewriting systems.
The term is a labelled tree that we
usually represent like this.
It is composed of a symbol f
living in a ranked alphabet
and n subterms t1 to tn.
Where n is the arity of the symbol f.
We call a pattern a term that
has a variable in it.
Terms are useful to represent
functional language expressions.
This slide shows how OCaml expressions
can be translated into terms.
Constants do not change,
they have no subterms
unless it is a number in which
case we'll represent it by a tree
using Peano's number
representation.
Functions and applications
can be translated
into a term where the arity of
the symbol is the arity of the function
and the subterms are parameters.
However this representation does
not allow partial application of f.
So instead we use the special
@ symbol to represent
a function application
which takes a function
and its first parameter.
Control structures such as if-then-else
are simply represented as terms.
Finally let bindings
and anonymous functions
are erased living only
the bound body here k.
This is because the program's logic
is preserved elsewhere as
a term writing system.
A term rewriting system defines
a set of rewriting rules
between patterns that encode
the program's logic.
Here is an example
of the OCaml program
defining the sorted
predicate function on top.
Translated it into a rewriting
system on the bottom.
Because there are a lot of
function applications
you see a lot of @ symbols
which takes a lot of room
and is hard to read.
To simplify, we will write
space between the function
and it's parameters instead
of @ just like this.
Underlined elements are
the variables of the patterns.
We see that each pattern
matching rule on the top
is translated into the one or more
rewriting rules on the bottom.
Rewriting system can also
be used to describe
a regular language of
terms as tree automata.
Here is for instance on the right.
The tree automaton
recognising every natural number
which can be used to partially
represent the int type in OCaml.
So rewriting rule defines
that 0 rewrites into int
because it is int
and s of int as you saw is also int.
In fact true automata can model
any algebraic data type of OCaml.
Here is the tree automata for
the following type of integer list.
It defines two more
rules for nil and cons
that closely match
the OCaml type definition.
Tree automata can even
represent regular language
that are not possible
to define in OCaml.
For instance, here is tree automata
recognising even numbers.
This can be seen as
the subtype of int.
In our case we call it
a regular language type.
Now that we are familiarized
with rewriting systems
and regular language types
let's dive into our
verification technique.
Remember that in our initial example
the user wants to verify that
in his program for all list l
the output of sort l
is sorted according to
the corresponding predicate.
In our verification settings,
this problem is first translated
into a rewriting problem.
Here it states that for all term l
in the regular language of lists
and for all term v
if the input term rewrites into v
then v must be equal to true.
In particular, it cannot be false.
So list must be sorted.
The arrow relation is defined
by the term writing system
translating from the input program.
As we have seen earlier, regular
languages can be seen as types.
So we then translate our problem
into a type checking problem
where we need to check that
the following term is well typed
using regular language types.
The overall target type is a regular
language containing only the term true.
Note that to check that
we will need to infer the appropriate
intermediate type for sort L
since it is not given.
From the partially typed given
input there on the right.
the type checking algorithm
is defined as follows.
First we extract
the type signature
for the top most symbol, sorted.
We know the expected
output type, true.
Constant values such as some
comparison functions, CMP
are typed with themselves
and can be reported
directly on the signature.
We complete the blanks
in the signature
using our type inference procedure.
We find that to output true,
the list must be sorted which is
represented by the regular language
named sorted.
We propagate back what we have found
and check that it matches
the initial type information
and then we reapeat,
the same procedure
with the subterm.
Here we need to check, sort l.
We again extract the template
signature for sort.
Here we already have all
the type information about sort.
We just need to check it.
The algorithm stops, when
all the types have been found
or when a type occur, when
there is a contradiction.
Of course everything is built on
top of type inference procedure
which has been able to find
the regular language of sorted lists.
Let's see how this procedure works.
So the problem is as follows.
As input we have rewriting
system of symbol f
and an output regular
language type o.
We want to find every
input type A1 to An
such that every term f(t1)
to tn is typed with O
when each ti is typed with AI.
This can be summarised with
the following abstract
writing rule for f.
For instance let's consider
the following rewriting system
defining the recursive function
even deciding if
a number is even or not.
We want to know for which
input regular language type
this function returns true.
So here our target output
type contains only true.
The expected output of
the procedure is a partial abstraction
of the input term rewriting system.
Focusing on even.
this tells us that even returns
true for every even number.
The new type Even is computed
during the analysis.
For recursive functions
such as this one
the type inference is done using
an invariant learning procedure.
In our paper, we defined
a counter-example
guided regular invariant
learning procedure
based on tree automata
completion and SMT solving.
It consists in repeating four steps
until it finds a solution
or a counter-example.
Step one we experiment.
We evaluate some terms of
the form of f of t1 to tn
where f is an analysed symbol and t1
to tn some random input values.
We do that efficiently using
the tree automaton completion algorithm.
We then observe the result
of our experiments
and deduce some constraints on
the language we are learning.
We then make an hypothesis
by using an SMT solver
and we solve the constraints
we generate an abstraction
of the program execution.
This gives us possible
regular language solution.
We check the correctness
of the abstraction
by checking it's completeness
with regards to the rewriting
system and the input domain.
If it is, we are done,
and if it isn't we continue
by doing more experiments.
To illustrate the procedure,
let's take back
the even function example.
First we experiment with
the values 0, 1 and 2
that are recognised in this
automata by this state X0, X1, X2.
Using the tree automaton completion
we know that Even of 0
and Even of 2 rewrites to true.
This is encoded by
the following rules.
If we only use this information,
then we cannot observe
the constraints.
Every tested value
so far rewrites to true.
As a consequence,
if everything rewrites to true
then there is no point in
separating X0 from X1 from X2.
The solution to our
anti-constraint system
is to merge them together
into a new state tau zero
By applying the substitution
in the automaton
we get a candidate abstraction
for rewriting system
where even applied to any
number returns to true.
Of course this does not pass the test.
Every input value for
Even is represented
but some rewriting rules
are not used in particular
this abstraction misses the fact
that even of 1 rewrites to false.
So we can not stop here.
To continue we add Even of
one in our experiment.
It rewrites to false.
This time we observe that in
order to separate true from false
we need to have X0 different from X2
and X1 different from X2.
By solving this new constant system
we make a new hypothesis
in which X0 are X2 are
equals, away from X1.
If we look closely, we can notice
that this new potential abstraction
separates even and odd numbers
which is exactly what we want.
And this time every input
value is represented.
And every possible
rewriting rule is used.
So we can stop the analysis here.
We have found an abstraction that
gives us the correct input type
for the output true.
Which is new language even
organizing even numbers.
We have proved that this
procedure is regularly
complete as it can
learn any regular language
and complete in refutation.
We have implemented it in Ocaml
in a new version of Timbuk
and tested it on more
than 80 problems.
When possible, we
compared the performances
with the previous version of Timbuk.
We saw that it is on average,
a second slower than Timbuk Three
which can be explained
by an overhead
due to our typing facility.
However, in the subset of problems
on which we could compare,
our implementation could
handle 16% more problems
without timing out.
Surprisingly, the greatest
improvement is in the memory usage
where in the worst case,
Timbuk Three would consume
several gigabytes of memory
to solve some problems
where we never got
passed 40 megabytes.
This is mostly due to our
modular type system approach
that allows us to split
the problem into smaller parts.
Thank you for listening
and don't hesitate to download
the source code which is
available on our GitHub
at the address below.
(AUDIENCE APPLAUDS)
RICHARD: OK, thanks, Timothee,
who's available in the New York
time band for question and answer.
We are now down with Technical
Session number five of ICFP.
In the New York time band, we have
an ICFP coffee break coming up
and yeah, at 1:30, there's
a virtualization feedback meeting
with Benjamin Pierce, Jonathan Bell,
and Krista Lopez coming up.
So that's an exciting thing to join.
In the Asia time band
in one half hour,
there will be a session on mentoring
with Mathias Felleisen.
Thanks very much and I hope
you enjoy the rest of ICFP.
(UPBEAT FOLK MUSIC)
(INDIE ROCK MUSIC)
(ELECTRONIC POP MUSIC)
(ROCK MUSIC)