ALAN JEFFREY: Hello everybody.
And welcome to the second
session of ICFP 2020.
You're joining us on YouTube,
and registered participants
for the conference
can also join us in chat,
on the Clowdr system.
And also, if they want
to join a live Q&A,
with the authors, after the talk.
And so the first talk
for the session,
is going to be achieving high
performance thre fuctional way,
and it'll be presented by,
Bastian Hagedorn.
BASTIAN: Hi, this Bastian Hagedorn,
from the university of Münster,
and I'll be presenting
a functional pearl,
on achieving high-perfomance,
the functional way.
This one's about expressing
high-performance
program optimizations,
as rewrite strategies.
This is joint work with colleagues
from the universities of Edinburgh
and Glasgow.
Let me begin with
asking the question,
why we care about high
performance in the first place?
And the answer is quite simple,
We literally cannot afford not to.
Because apparently it cost
about a quarter million dollars
to perform state of the art
machine learning research.
And this high cost is mostly due to
the long time required to train neural
networks on parallel hardware.
It gets worse when you translate
the dollar spent into carbon emitted.
So here, training
this neural network,
releases about five tons of carbon
into the atmosphere,
which is equivalent to driving
11,000 miles with a car.
And just to show you
how insane it is,
here's a map showing a road trip,
from the North of Norway,
all the way down to South Africa.
Which corresponds to
roughly 11,000 miles.
So clearly, we need to find a way,
to reduce those costs,
and optimizing a program, to
achieve high performance.
Might allow us to significantly
reduce the time required to,
to, for example,
train neural networks.
So, how do we achieve
high perfomance?
Here's a naive implementation
of a matrix multiplication
and computation in CUDA,
which targets GPU's.
And if you know, a little
bit about CUDA and GPU's,
I'd argue that,
this is quite easy to
write and to understand.
But unfortunately, this
program is also not very fast.
So, for achieving the highest
performance on modern GPU's,
the simple program has to
be significantly modified.
So for example, here is
an optimized version,
of the same computation,
which achieves up to three orders
of magnitude more performance.
And if we compare this again
to our road trip example,
and the carbon emitted,
a thousand X improvement
barely allows us to drive
15 minutes on the highway.
However, this manual way of
achieving high performance,
requires some expert to sit down,
for quite some time,
and to optimize the program,
in a time intensive
and incredibly error prone process.
So, another way,
to achieve high performance,
is what I call the decoupled way,
which was pioneered by the domain
specific compiler called Halide.
And the key idea here,
is to decouple what
is being computed,
from how it is optimized.
So this allows a domain scientist,
to focus on implementing
the computation,
which can then be
separately optimized,
by a performance engineer,
with the so called schedule.
And this way of achieving
high performance,
is currently very popular,
there're many compilers
following this approach.
So, this particular example here,
is taken from the TVM
machine learning compiler,
which is currently
the state of the art,
in generating high performance
machine learning implementation.
TVM comes with a tutorial
on how to optimize matrix
modifications for CPU's.
And we'll take a closer
look at that in a moment.
So the TVM compiler uses both
the algorithm and the schedule,
to generate an efficient
implementation.
So here, for example, we
see the blocking version
from the TVM tutorial,
which applies some specific
group transformations.
The best version presented
in this tutorial,
is about 200 times faster
than the baseline,
but only requires to add a few
more lines to the schedule,
or at least that's the idea.
So when you take
a closer look at this,
the schedule based approach,
you'll find a few problems.
One of the first few
things you might find is that
the algorithm and
the schedule are not fully separated.
Here, the schedule uses
the same path in identifier,
that has been declared
in the algorithm.
And that simply means that,
both the algorithm and the schedule
have to live in the same scope,
and that hinders
the re-use of the schedule,
for optimizing
a different computation.
The next problem is that there's
no well-defined semantics,
for the scheduling preemptives.
So there's only
a documentation online,
And for some primitives,
this is quite cryptic
and basically requires,
knowledge of how the compiler
internally implements
the scheduling primitives.
And finally, all scheduling
primitives are built in,
which makes them hard to extend.
So typically every  primitive,
like tile or vectorize,
represents a common
optimization,
you might want to apply,
but as soon as you need
something slightly different
you're in trouble.
Because, there's no easy way to extend
the set of exposed optimizations
besides digging deep into
the implementation of the compiler itself.
And this is something we
don't often want to do.
So, this is why with our
functional approach,
we aim for a more principled way,
to describe and apply high-performance
program optimizations.
Specifically, we aim
to separate concerns, by
specifying computation at
a high obstruction level only,
without changing them for
expressing optimizations.
We aim to facilitate reuse by
defining optimization strategies,
clearly separated from
the computations.
We aim to enable composability
by allowing to define both
computations and optimizations
as compositions of
user defined building blocks.
We aim to allow reasoning by
giving those building blocks
well-defined semantics.
And finally, we aim to be
explicit and avoid all implicit
default behavior of the compiler.
And essentially we argue that
a strategy language should
be built with the same
standards as a language
describing the computation. Now,
let me show you the functional,
way of achieving
high performance.
In our approach we follow
the same idea of decoupling
computations and optimizations,
but we're using the well established
functional programming
techniques to express both.
So on the top left, we have a high
level program that is written in
the function programming
language called rise.
That is based on
the ICFP paper from 2015.
And on the right, you see
an optimization strategy that describes
how to optimize that rise program.
And this is written in elevate,
which is based on ideas already
published in the late nineties.
Our compiler then rewrites
the rise program based on the
optimizations described in
the elevate strategy and
eventually generates
high performance code.
Our functional pearl is all
about how to express the high
performance optimizations
typically applied manually or
using the schedule based approach.
However, as composable
rewrites strategies instead.
Alright, let's see how we do
this and we'll start by taking
a closer look at
elevate our language
for describing the optimizations.
The most basic building block
in elevate is a strategy and
a strategy is simply a function
from some program P to what
we call a rewrite result and
a rewrite result is simply saying
whether the applied strategy
succeeded in which case it contains
the rewritten program,
or it failed in which case it
contained the strategy,
which failed.
Rewrite rules are examples
for very simple strategies.
And you could, for example,
go ahead and implement
the typical fusion rule for rise
programs as an elevate strategy.
As you see on the bottom. This
rule simply says that whenever
you see a rise program that
contains two consecutive maps,
you can fuse those maps
and return the fused program,
and if there are no
consecutive two maps,
then this rule is simply not
applicable and it fails.
For building more powerful strategies,
we can combine tools
and elevate using several
different combinators.
So for example,
the sequence combinator allows
to apply two strategies in sequence.
The left choice operator
expects also two strategies,
but only applies the second one
in case the first one fails.
The try combinator tries to
apply the given strategy and
if it is not applicable, it's
simply returns the unchanged
input program by applying
the ID strategy.
And finally, the repeat strategy
allows us to repetitively apply
the same strategy until it
is no longer applicable.
Now, what if we have
the following situation.
Here you see a rise program
that contains three maps.
And if we now want to apply
the mapfusion rule, we have just defined,
there are two possible
locations for fusing the maps.
So we can either use the first
two or the last two maps.
And with elevate, you can
precisely define locations in
the AST using so-called traverses.
So for example, the body traversal
applies a given strategy at
the body of a function
abstruction mode.
And in this example, body
mapfusion would then fuse the
first two maps as we've seen here.
Similarly, we define traversals
for the other nodes and
could for example, apply
for the argument of fusion,
for fusing the last thing that's in
this expression and in the paper,
we explained in more detail how
to describe precise locations
using these and other traverses.
Sometimes it's not desirable
to specify a precise path,
but instead we might want to
say something like apply this
given strategy at
the first place you'll find,
and this is what bottom
up or top down do.
So these traverses strategies,
traverse AST either like from top
down or bottom up
and apply the given strategy
at the first place where it's
applicable and then stop.
Another useful traversal is
the normalized strategy,
which applies a given strategy
exhaustively until it is no longer
applicable anywhere in
the give expression.
And in the paper we define a few
normal forms for rise expression.
And one simple example
for one of those is
the beta eta-normal form, which
simply applies beta reduction
and eta reduction
as often as possible.
Using those generic building
blocks, we then try to implement
TVM scheduling language
and try to especially define
elevate strategies that
apply the same optimizations
as describing the TVM tutorial,
which we've mentioned earlier.
So here's what the baseline
version looks like.
And for TVM, we described
the matrix multiplication using
the pipe and API and use
the default schedule
to generate unoptimized code.
For our functional way, we describe
the matrix multiplication
computation using rise
and its functional array
primitives like
map and reduce.
And we define a separate
strategy in elevate,
which explained how to
optimize this computation.
And here we can already see that
we have a clear separation
between the computation
and the optimization.
More crucially TVM's default
strategy implicitly describes
some way of lowering
the program to execute the code.
And we don't really know
how this is performed.
With our approach, we aim to
completely avoid implicit behavior
and describe every
transformation explicitly.
So here, we're simply saying
that the dot product should
be computed using a single
statement, by fusing the map and
the reduce pattern, similar to
how TVM computes the dot product.
This way we implemented each of the
seven differently optimized versions.
And in the paper we described,
for example, how to implement
TVMs built-in tile
optimization as a composition
of only a few rewrite rules
and the combinators and
traversals we've just seen.
Also our functional approach
allows us to define
the different optimized versions
as reusable strategies.
So here, for example,
we define the loop perms strategy,
which we will reuse in
the following more optimized versions.
This is the most optimized
version implemented
in both TVM and our approach.
And here you can see that
we are able to reuse and
to build upon
the loop perm strategy,
whereas in TVM we always have to
describe the whole optimization
from scratch because we cannot
easily define our own abstruction.
One crucial problem is also that
the TVM algorithm has to be
changed a few times during
the tutorial because the scheduling
language is not powerful enough
to express all desirable
optimizations.
Our approach with rise and elevate
does not require us to do so.
And we use the same rise matrix
multiplication that is optimized
by seven different
and separate elevate strategies.
To evaluate our approach,
we look at two things.
So first in the first experiment,
we simply counted the number of
successful rewrite steps for
versions, which you can see here.
And since the baseline version
does not perform any interesting
transformations it only
requires a few rewrite steps.
But as soon as we're performing
actual program optimizations,
we reach about yeah,
45 thousands and
later up to 62,000
separate rewrites steps.
And this shows that our
approach is scalable because
we were able to define
the complex TVM like optimizations
by simply composing a few
rewrite rules using elevate.
Also performing this many steps
took less than two seconds
per version on a regular notebook.
So this is no bottleneck.
Obviously we also wanted to see
if the performance we achieve
with our functional way
matches the performance
achieved by the TVM compiler.
And here you see the performance
achieved for each of
the seven different versions and
you'll find that we are able
to achieve a similar trend,
which means that our
elevate strategies encode
the same high performance
program optimizations as applied
by the state of
the art TVM compiler.
And if you would like to find out
more about a functional way of
achieving high performance,
simply contact us and
have a look at our
paper and with this,
I'd like to end the presentation.
I mentioned that you can find
all our implementations
online or in the artifacts.
Thanks for your attention.
(CLAPS)
ALAN JEFFREY: So thank you, Bastian.
So for anybody who is wanting to join
the authors for the live Q&A,
you can click on the link that's
in the Clowdr page for this talk.
Our next paper in the second
session of ICFP 2020,
is going to be Staged selective
parser combinators and
it's going to be presented by
Jamie Willis and Nick Wu.
JAMIE: Hello? Can you hear me?
NICK: Hello? Yeah, I can hear you.
JAMIE: Nice. I can hear you too.
NICK: So I don't know if we've met.
My name is Nick Wu. I'm from
Imperial college London.
JAMIE: Oh, Hey, I'm Jamie
Willis. I'm also from Imperial.
NICK: Oh, what a coincidence.
It's strange doing an
online conference with
prerecord videos. Isn't it?
JAMIE: Yeah. ICFP is
interesting this year.
I wonder if anyone's made the most
of it in their presentation somehow.
NICK: Indeed. So what
are you working on?
JAMIE: I've been
working with parsers.
NICK: Oh, nice. I'm a big
fan of parser combinators.
JAMIE: What are those?
NICK: Oh, well, they're a way of building
a parse that follows
the structure of a grammar closely
by treating parses as first
class values and building
larger parsers from smaller ones.
JAMIE: Right. Can I have an example?
NICK: Let's look at the BNF for
a language that recognizes
strings of characters. Let's
suppose that they're non-empty.
So here's some code the non
terminal alpha is the choice of
letters from A to Z and alphas
consists of what of those followed
either by more alphas or by
absent on the empty token.
JAMIE: Okay. So how'd you
actually write the parsers then.
NICK: Right? And so in Haskell
alpha is a value
of type parser char since
it pauses a character.
And here we simply give
the alternative between each of the chars.
The alphas parser returns a list of
chars by first parsing an alpha,
and then appending it to the results
of more alphas
or just the empty list.
JAMIE: Right. So how does that
strange cons thing work?
NICK: Okay. So parsers are afflictive
so we can lift normal functions
and constructors like cons
so that they can work on parsers.
So here the pure cons
just makes the function
work at the parser level. And then
the app, which is the star will
ensure that Px is parsed
first followed by Pxs.
And then it's put
together with cons.
JAMIE: That doesn't seem like
something you can execute.
NICK: Well, if you want to
actually run one of these parsers
on an input string Xs, then you
use the run parser function that
will take the string and return
the parse result if it can.
JAMIE: Right. So those combinators
seem really verbose
I usually just use EBNF like this,
where you'd use a character class
and a plus, and it gets
rid of a lot of the bloat.
NICK: Yeah, sure. That makes
sense. Well, you can also do
this with combinators as well.
Here's what you do with alphas.
We're using one of which will
take one of the A to Z in
the ranges you've done. And the plus
says that you simply
want some of those.
JAMIE: Ah, that's neat. Okay. So
how are oneOf and some implemented?
NICK: Well, there also in terms of
simple Combinators oneOf is,
in terms of the primitive satisfy
and satisfy takes a primitive,
takes a predicate and accepts
an input character that satisfies it.
For oneOf we simply want it to be
an element of a given list Cs.
Some can actually be
implemented in terms of
what we've seen
so far. Can you see how?
JAMIE: Sure. Let me see. I think
if I took the alphas example,
I could reverse engineer it. So
I guess if I factor this alpha out
then that would give me some,
so I'd replace alphas and PX
and then alphas with some PX.
NICK: Yeah, that's right. And
you could furthermore factor out
what's inside
the brackets to have both an
implementation of some and many.
JAMIE: Right. So some is
the BNF plus then many is the star
using parse combinators surely
has a performance impact.
NICK: Right. Yes. So there's
definitely some overhead to using
these kinds of combinators.
But on the other hand,
if you represent these
combinators as a deep embedding
where the Combinators are
all data constructors,
then you can do things
like grammar analysis,
which is driven by various laws,
such as the applicative
and alternative laws.
JAMIE: I guess you could
optimize it that way.
I think it's easier to
understand performance by
thinking of an underlying
state machine.
NICK: What do you mean?
JAMIE: Well, you can represent
parsers as a machine with one
stack for intermediate results
and another for handling failure.
And then you parse by executing
instructions that interact
with these stacks when they're
given some input stream.
So I guess we would take your
previous parser as an example.
So here it would be.
NICK: Whoa, is that really still Haskell?
JAMIE: Yeah, sure. This is clearly
just a recursive machine reading,
alphabetical characters,
setting up failure handlers
before recursing again
and combining elements of the stack.
What's there not to understand?
Isn't this how you were
taught to use Haskell?
NICK: Well, I you'll have to go
a bit slower than that for me.
JAMIE: Right? Sure. So just read
those dollars as semi-colons and
your favorite imperative language.
Then alpha is similar to yours.
It's just an instruction
that verifies a
prediacate on the next input token,
and then continues with another
instruction K and alphas performs,
alpha and then leaves the
result on the stack.
It then does a catch block
to handle any failure.
And inside this block,
alphas is run again,
which leaves its result
on the stack too.
And the two results are
combined with left two cons.
Then things are free to carry on
with the next instruction K.
But if failure happens, then
the first instructions about
second block before the case
check that the input
hasn't changed since
starting to catch.
And the case instruction then
uses that information to either
fail or combine out for the empty list
before continuing with that same K.
NICK: Oh, I see. So your
representation is much
more explicit about
control flow than mine.
JAMIE: Yeah. Analyzing
the control from my machine is quite
straightforward. I think it's just
a lot more complex in your case.
NICK: Yeah. That's true. The control
flow for the grammar isn't obvious
at all, until you start looking
at something like derivatives.
JAMIE: Okay. Hang on. I think
I can see what's happening here.
The representation that
I have is the same as yours.
It's just been transformed into
CPS continuation parsing style.
That's what makes
the control flow explicit.
Basically each instruction
takes us an argument,
the next instruction executes.
And this is interpreted
by passing around two
continuations at runtime. The
good continuation and the bad one.
NICK: Of course. So if you
can convert between the
two representations, then you'll be
able to get both the high level
optimizations and grammar
analysis of my approach and
the low level optimizations
and control flow analysis of yours.
You get the best of both worlds.
There's a problem though.
The machine you showed
me before is untyped.
How can we convince ourselves
that the translation
is working properly? My
Combinator tree is fully typed.
JAMIE: Well, my stack represents
what's already been computed, right?
I guess in your world, that
corresponds to combinators
that have already been executed
and each Combinator will
push exactly one thing to
the stack. If it's successful.
NICK: So what if we can propagate
my type information into
a type level stack. Here,
let me show you what I mean.
So Halt is basically produces
a machine that expects
an A on an empty stack
and returns that A.
JAMIE: Whoa whoa whoa! Wait.
How does that get implemented?
NICK: I see you just use an H
list. It's a heterogeneous list
so that the values can
have different types.
The types of each elements are
kept in a type level list.
And this list is
the same as the one that
will appear in our
instruction types.
JAMIE: Oh, right. Okay.
Thanks for that, carry on.
NICK: Where was I? Okay,
so push take some X and
the machine that expects X
and Xs and produces a machine
that expects just Xs. And pop
takes the machine that expects
only the stack Xs
and produces a machine
that expects an X on
top of the stack Xs.
JAMIE: Right? I think I see. So
the continuation machine expects
a stack of a certain type
and then the instruction
will adapt that stack to fit.
I guess that compiling combinators
to a machine means taking
a machine that accepts the result and
makes progress towards
some final goal.
So that's something like this then.
CompileSub will take a parser
containing returning an A and
then a machine that accepts
that A along with some X's and
then we can build
a machine that requires
just that Xs in
order to continue.
And the final continuation
is going to be Halt.
It takes the one lement on
the stack and gives it back.
NICK: Right. So how would
you translate combinators?
So for example, the pure, which
has type A to parser A and app,
which has type parser A to B
to parser A to parser B.
JAMIE: Oh, easy,
something like this.
So for pure that's just the push
instruction, right.
With some N that will
continue on afterwards.
And then for app, we just
need to compile PF and
then we'll compile PX. And after
that, we combine the two results
that are on the stack with function
application using lift two.
NICK: Oh, neat. So what about
the and then variant of app where
discard the first argument,
rather than applying a function,
something like parser A
to parser B to parser B?
JAMIE: Oh, sure. All you need
to do is pop up to pass in the
first result so you compile P
then you pop that was off and
then you compile Q
and then carry on with M.
NICK: Oh, neat. So I can see
how this might work out.
You know, now that we can
see this as using CPS,
it kind of reminds me of some
work that my PhD student,
Matt Pickering has been
doing lately on staging.
Actually, there's a paper being
presented at the Haskell symposium
about it coming up in
just a couple of days.
JAMIE: So what staging exactly?
NICK: Alright. Well, so staging
as a form of meta programming,
where you can perform work on
statically known results ahead of
time leaving only
dynamic information
that runtime it's
basically giving you...
fine grained control over evaluation
in your compiler.
In our case the shape of the machine
for Parser and its
combinators is static.
In other words, it's
known by the compiler.
JAMIE WILLIS: I think
I understand so this means
we can perform that translation
from combinations to machine,
and evaluate most of
it, at compile time.
I've heard of template Haskell,
but that's untyped right.
It seems a bit of a waste
of all the hard work
we did to make everything
typed?
NICOLAS: Yeah, indeed and I guess
you haven't heard of typed template Haskell.
Unlike template Haskell
where you build AST's with
typed template Haskell
you can only work with
well typed terms which
ensures that the processes is safe,
For example, if you
have some term E of type A,
then it could be quoted
to get the code
that represents E at
run time,
quoting, which is of type code A.
If you want to splice
or run some code
you simply use the anti
quotes by adding a dollar
to the front so for some
code C of type code A
Splice C gives back
a value of type A.
JAMIE: Oh, so what I have to do,
is code to the parts
that are gonna happen at runtime.
NICOLAS: Yep.
JAMIE: OK, so let's have a look
at the machine state the where it's interpreted
and see what we can
uncover.
So quickly, let's look at how we actually
evaluate the machine,
normally with the run
machine function.
So, we're going to
provide some machine
state gamma to the eval function,
and that's going to interpret
the meaning of each instruction.
So, all gamma is is just a
our heterogeneous open
stack along with a return
continuation
for recursion a stack
for failure handlers
and the input xs itself.
And so the bit that we can actually
stage about this would
be the eval function,
because it's the machine
that's done at compile time, right.
So, if I just add code around it,
then that makes
the function from machine
state to final value code
and that, that'll be done at run time.
And you can break this into
a compile time function
that takes code and returns code
that's fairly straightforward,
but we should get to
more than this, right.
So the machines take gammas
always the same shape,
so we should be able to get rid
of that at compile time too.
So if I push the code
into the gamma,
then we can ensure it
only exist at a compile time.
Yeah so runtime will produce
a function with four arguments,
one for each component,
but the actual records gone.
There's sort of this, gonna
be more we can do now.
NICOLAS: Well,
the fact that, H list.
In ops has the type Xs implies,
but it must have those, shape that
we can do at compile time.
And that's determined by instructions
also known at compile time.
So you could push the code
inside the H list.
JAMIE: I see, so, if I map
the code over the values in the H list,
then the H list itself is only
going to exist at compile time,
and the values exist at runtime.
And I guess the structure,
the handle stack is
the same it's determined by
the instructions as well.
So I guess we can operate that
list at compile time too.
So, with all things considered,
I guess the only thing
we don't really know
at compile time is
what the input is,
and specifically what each
continuation is at any given point.
Everything else is gone
NICOLAS: Exactly and that's why we
like staging so much.
JAMIE: Awesome, so here's what
the staged evaluation
for push and halt
look like then.
So, halt will take
the operand stack out of gamma
and extract the top element
and splice it into some code
that builds it just for
that value at run time,
and eval push there aren't
actually any quotes
in the body at all,
so it must purely happen at compile time.
That's really cool.
So, I guess let's
push
an example through this mechanism
and see what code it generates.
Wow, this is, this is quite cool,
so I guess we can see that
none of the abstractions
from the combinators in
the machine are here at all.
It's literally just a couple of
functions, taking this argument,
this good continuation
the bad continuation.
And some input and it'll
all thread around together,
this is, this is awesome.
NICOLAS: Yeah, it is,
it's really good.
But there is a small problem.
Most parser combinators
such as parsec
this combinator called bind,
which is usually used
to implement context
sensitive parsing
the stuff that was previously parsed
can influence the grammar,
that is used to parse the rest.
The trouble is that I don't
think this can be staged.
JAMIE: That's a pain,
I mean do you really need
to create a whole new parser
so that we can't inspect,
what sort of things do you
actually use it for.
NICOLAS: I suppose, most of the time
the grammar is static,
and bind is used to select
the part of the grammar
that's already known.
JAMIE: Oh, well we've already
seen an operation
like that right?
it was it was case.
So both of the outcomes
are known statically,
but you don't know which path
is taken until runtime.
NICOLAS: Interesting.
I wonder if this corresponds
to Marco's work on selected functors,
it seems to behave similarly
to his branch operation
which arbitrates between two
branches depending on a coproduct.
JAMIE: Yeah, I think that
sounds about right.
NICOLAS: Great, so if you give up bind
and work with selectors
instead we can use staging,
and that makes things really fast.
JAMIE: Let me
quickly whip something up
and we can see how it performs
on some benchmarks, I made earlier.
NICOLAS: Wow. Kids these days are really
fast at programming things.
JAMIE: Perfect. It works first
time that's unusual
It must be there's strong types.
Right here's the results.
So, this graph is showing us
that actually compared
to the other combinator
libraries we're about three
or four times faster,
and we're even beating happy
that's a parser generator library.
NICOLAS: Wow, that's
really good performance.
JAMIE: Yeah, this is great.
Maybe we should write
a paper about this.
NICOLAS: Well, you're pretty good
at coding things quickly
and I'm pretty good at writing
papers quickly, so here you go.
Cool. I'm gonna stop
recording now I think.
BACKGROUND CLAPPING
ALAN JEFFREY: OK, thank you, Jamie and Nic.
So if you want to
join the authors for
a Q&A in the New York time zone.
Then you can click on
the link in the Clowdr room,
Hello and welcome back to
the second session for ICFP 2020.
And our next talk is going to
be, Kindly Bent to Free Us,
and it's going to be presented
by Gabriel Radanne.
GABRIEL RADANNE: Hi everyone
so I'm Gabriel Radanne
and I'm going to talk to you
about memory safety
for a little while.
Here is a report provided
by the Chromium team
about high severity
security bugs in chromium,
and you can see that
almost two thirds
of the bugs in chromium
are memory related,
and one third of the bugs, are simple
use after free errors.
So you could say OK.
Chromium is written in
a mix of C and C++
and surely these don't happen
in high level typed languages. Right.
Let's write OCaml code.
Here is a small example of code
where we open a database,
we write a grade database of grades,
we write some grade into
the database so that's great,
we close the database, then we try
to read the literature
grade, and print it.
So the OCaml type checker
will happily type check
and compile this program,
and later on we'll have
runtime error. So,
there are various ways to, deal with
this kind of errors,
and today I'm going to present Affe,
which is an ML like language
that prevent precisely
this kind of error.
So here is the same program
written in Affe.
It looks very much like the ML program
the program from before,
except this time when we
reach the last line
and the type checker will refuse
at compile time, this program.
So we have a few
specificity in Affe.
The first one is that we use
kinds, to determine usage.
So, here is a grade database
is of type database,
and the database is kind of linear.
And so this resource
must be use linearly,
and when it's closed, you
don't use it anymore.
On the contrary, here we
have the math string
and string are unrestricted.
And so you can you can use them
in unrestricted fashions.
Furthermore, we have borrows,
so as present in rust
and other languages
borrows allows
to do imperative programming
very conveniently
and that's why we use them here.
Finally, the final
specificity of affe
is that we have complete
type inference.
So before I used.
I used a type annotation here
to simplify, to make
it easier to read.
But I don't need to. Here
type is completely inferred.
So, to present Affe, I'm going to
go through various of its features,
and I'm going to start by linearity.
So as I said before
kinds determine usage.
We have three kinds linear, resource
must be used exactly once.
Affine or resource must be used
exactly at most one zero ones.
And unrestricted
the object can use
arbitrary many times
from zero to infinity.
Here are a few examples.
We have a database type of
kind lin, a string type of type,
of kind unrestricted.
We can also have parameterized kind.
So, for example, a list.
As the kind of content,
if we have a list of database.
Then, this must be used linearly.
If we have a list of strings,
it can be used in
an unrestricted fashion
to use these kind of parameters kind
We also have kind constraints.
So here, we can, a we
have the type function,
create list which takes an element
and replicates it multiple
time to create a list.
Since the element is
going to be replicated.
Because then naturally,
its content must be unrestricted.
And that's exactly what
this constraint says.
Finally, we also use subkinding,
so un is smaller than f
which is smaller than lin.
And that means that if a function
only expect linear objects,
we can pass it unrestricted objects.
And the reason is that if something
can be used in unrestricted fashion,
in particular, it can
be used linearly
This is the base of our language,
and we're going to
use it to build up everything else.
And in particular,
functions and captures.
So here's a piece of code where
we open the grade database.
Then we create a function
that logs, some message,
and then close the database.
As you can see, we
have a capture here,
the login, login close
function captures
a grade database and grade,
a grade database is linear,
it must be used exactly once.
And so, the log function must
also be called exactly once.
If we ask the Affe checker
it's going to give us
this type, string arrow
Annotated by Lin, and unit,
and the annotation on
the arrow indicates
that, indicates
the usage of this function,
it indicates that log n close
must be called exactly once.
If you're wanting to
make everything here.
This will, this annotation,
does not say anything
about the argument.
Here the argument is of type
string so it's unrestricted,
you can do whatever
you want with it.
The arrow and in particular
this linear arrow
is not early but from linear logic.
It only says something
about the function itself
All right, so we can do.
Nice functional
programming with all this.
Let's look about imperative.
Let's look at imperative
programming,
and for that we need
borrows and regions
as in Rust and other languages,
a borrow is a temporary
loan of a resource, A.
And we have two types
of  borrow.
Shared burrows for
observing the resource
and Exclusive burrows are
for modifying the resource.
Here is an example of
a correct use of borrow.
We start by looking up,
two grades concurrently
so this is a read action so we use
a shared borrow for observing the data.
Since it's since it's shared,
we can look up two things at
the same time concurrently,
and in particular the kind
of this is unrestricted.
Once we are done with looking up
these two grades
and making their average,
we can write in the database
using an exclusive borrow
and exclusive are, as
I said, exclusive
and they are, in particular,
of kind affine.
So there are a few rules
to use this borrows.
The first rule is that
we, you cannot use
a borrow and the resource,
itself, at the same time.
Here, the f function is
called with the resource,
and a borrow, and that's not allowed
as a type checker will reject this.
A second rule is that
we can not use an
exclusive borrow and any
other borrow, so here,
I have an exclusive
borrow and another borrow,
and the type checker
will again reject this.
Finally, a borrow must not escape.
Here we have
a declaration of database
and then pair composed
which contains a borrow.
And then we try to leak the borrow
while the database is still
capture inside the function.
So this is not allowed
because the borrow
is escaping it's region.
And here is the region,
delimiting a borrow.
So the regions are
almost lexical scoping
with a few tweaks
and the way we check
for this kind of escape is
by using the indexed kinds
so before I said the kinds were
unrestricted affine and linear.
Actually there are a bit more
zero indexed by the nesting.
And here the grade, the borrow
of the database is in
a second nesting,
so it's annotated by un two.
Whereas, the region around it
is at the nesting level one.
And so we will simply check
two is bigger than one,
so the borrow cannot escape.
And the type checker will
again, rejects this.
Alright so we have borrow,
we have closure, we have functions,
we have linearity let's
put everything together.
Here is the API for the database
that they've used since
the beginning of this talk.
the type database is of linear kind,
we have defined functions,
that takes a borrow.
With its kind, and takes
the string and return an integer.
We have the add function that
takes an exclusive borrow.
a string, an integer
and returns units.
And since the functions
are currified,
you can, here the database borrow
is captured later on
and so the functions
are annotated with
the kind that is capture here.
Here is a simple use of this API,
as I said, which was
presented before.
So we have, two concurrent
Lookups,
grade Db, of the grade
DB of two grade that math and compsci.
And then we compute the average.
We can factorize a little bit the
lookup aspect
by creating a grade function
that captures a database,
and look up the topic
or the subjects of the grade.
And here we repeat
the argument subject and subject.
so we can simply partially
applies a function,
and it will compute the borrows
and the kinds accordingly.
And finally we can even go further
and use a function
attraction to pull
the function computing
the average outside
by taking a list of subjects
and applying a partially
applied function in list of map,
and so on and so forth,
and use any other functions
as we would want to
in a functional language
The type checker will
annotate the region
as we would expect, here we are
the disjoined region
for the shared borrow
and the exclusive borrow
and they are perfectly disjoined.
Finally, as we said before,
we have no type annotations,
so even if I used the average.
Even if I lifted
the average function, I
I still have no type annotation
here we have complete
type inference.
Alright so let's, look a little bit
under the hood at
inference and constraint.
The first step is to
elaborate the region.
By using the information provided
by the position of the borrow,
the scopes of the borrow
and the borrowing rules I presented,
which allow us to
completely determine
the biggest region
we could use.
Again second step is to
generate constraint,
which we encode, type
linearity and borrowing checks.
And to prove - check that
nothing escapes that shouldn't.
This constraint system
is custom to encode.
the rule we want
and based on HM(X).
Finally, we solve the constraints
using custom algorithms
that we provide,
and we obtain principal type schemes
for all the functions in our program.
So this principle type
scheme can sometimes still
be a little bit complicated,
and so we use subkinding rules
with positive and negative position
to simplify the type further down.
Alright, and so we obtain, finally,
the simple type schemes.
So to summarize, I presented
the Affe language,
a prototype is available
at this address online.
We've provided Linearity,
Closure, Borrows and Regions,
to provide good support
for both imperative
and functional programming,
we support managed
and unmanaged objects,
and principal and type inference,
which is something very noble,
for which type support borrows.
The downside is that so far we do
not support real flow sensitivity,
we can emulate this a bit,
but it has no proper support,
and we do not have yet
a concurrency story
so that's something
we're working on.
In the paper you can
find many many examples
to show that we can indeed support
many types of programming,
both functional imperative.
On the theory side, we provide
a syntax-directed type system for Affe,
how to encode into
an ML-style type-system,
we provide the formal account
semantics and proof of soundness,
and an inference algorithm for Affe,
which provide values, novel
contribution in particular
an extension to HM(X),
novel constraint system
and it's constraint algorithm
and proof of completeness.
That's all I have.
Thank you very much.
(AUDIENCE APPLAUSE)
ALAN JEFFREY: So, thank you Gabriel.
So, if you want to join
the authors for a live Q&A,
click on the link in
the Clowdr room for this paper.
Hello and welcome back to
the second session of ICFP 2020.
And our next paper is going to be
'Sealing Pointer-based Optimizations
behind Pure Functions',
and it's going to be
presented by Daniel Selsam.
DANIEL SELSAM: Everybody,
my name is Daniel Selsam
from Microsoft Research.
I'll be presenting joint work with
Simon Hudon from Carnegie Mellon,
and my colleague Leonardo de
Moura from Microsoft Research.
Our paper is titled,
'Sealing Pointer-based Optimizations
behind Pure Functions'.
Now, functional programming
really shines for
interactive theorem provers.
For many reasons.
It's easy to encode terms
with inductive types,
and this is actually
surprisingly cumbersome in C++.
It's easy to traverse terms
with higher-order combinators,
for example, it's easy to write
functions that replace sub-terms
of terms, or find sub-terms
matching patterns.
And it's easy to backtrack using
persistent data-structures.
So, we can just snapshot the world,
try tactic one in that
world and if it fails,
in constant time and no
extra programming effort,
we can just roll back
the world to the snapshot
before we started tac1 and then
try the second tactic in it.
And as we would expect, most
interactive thorem provers
are written in functional
programming languages.
So, Isabelle/HOL is written in
Poly/ML, Coq is written in OCaml,
Agda and Idris are
written in Haskell
and Lean3 was written in C++
at great spiritual cost,
but Lean4 is being
rewritten in Lean4 itself,
which is a functional
programming language.
But while functional programming
shines in this domain,
pure languages suffer
a critical limitation
that we call Purity's Achilles Heal.
Which is that, "Traversing
a term requires time proportional
to the tree size of the term,
as opposed to its graph size,
which causes exponential blowup
in theory and in practice."
And here's a little illustration.
On the left, there's a term
whose DAG representation
has only four nodes, and in fact,
has only four nodes in memory,
but when you view it as a tree, it
has two to the four minus one node.
So, exponentially more nodes
in its tree representation
than in its graph representation.
And perhaps a surprising
empirical finding
is that terms with
astronomic tree sizes
are actually extremely common in
interactive theorem provers.
So, it's well known that even
basic operations can produce them.
So unifying two terms, where
the function symbol has arity n,
can produce a term whose
tree size is two to the n.
But this is a somewhat
contrived example.
But in reality, terms are often
the result of long chains
of somewhat arbitrary user-written
meta programs or tactics.
And at least in Lean's
mathematical library - Mathlib,
it's not uncommon for a proof
that has only 20,000 nodes
in its DAG representation
to have over 2 billion nodes
in its tree representation.
And many performance issues in Coq
and Lean going back many years
have been the result of improper
handling of such terms
despite having the needed
impure tools at hand.
Basically, the exponential
blow up is so severe
that if a single module
ever traverses a term
with insufficiently precise caching
is very likely going
to be a bottleneck.
And now we can talk
about our contribution.
So, we present a new way to, quote,
'Seal' the needed optimizations -
the optimizations that you need to
traverse terms in linear time.
We show how to seal
these optimizations
behind pure functional interfaces.
And here's the main idea.
We start with a pure
reference implementation
of something that we want to optimize,
we find sufficient conditions
for a particular optimization
to respect the reference
implementation,
we then create a new primitive
that takes these conditions
as 'preconditions'
using dependent types
and otherwise is given the nominal
pure reference implementation.
And then we just compile this
primitive into the optimized version.
And a simple meta theoretic argument
establishes that
since it was proved -
since the preconditions were approved,
the optimization is settled.
And we show how to do
this for several common
low-level optimizations,
including pointer equality tests,
and even direct
pointer-address manipulations.
And we show how to use
these new primitives
to traverse terms in linear time,
which is the problem
we set out to solve.
So, perhaps the simplest
pointer optimization
is just short-circuiting equality
tests using pointer equality.
And the idea is simple:
If two terms x and y have
the same memory address,
they must be structurally equal.
So, you can skip the potentially
exponentially expensive
structural equality test
and just return true.
And the challenge here is
that this optimization
is only sound in general
for reflexive relations.
And the solution is somewhat simple:
Allow the optimization any relation
that you can prove is reflexive.
Which brings us to our
first new primitive
which we call, 'withPtrEq'.
And now, withPtrEq takes two
terms x and y of type alpha,
and a thunk, k, that takes
a unit type and returns Bool.
And the precondition, h,
is a proof that if x=y,
then this thunk, k, is
going to return true.
And then the overall primitive
withPtrEq returns Bool,
and it's pure reference implementation
just simply evaluates the thunk.
And now, the compiler will
treat this as opaque
until reaching the low-level IR.
At which point it will
expand a call to withPtrEq,
to the following
pseudo code snippet:
It first checks of the pointer
addresses are the same of x and y,
if they are it returns true,
otherwise it evaluates it up.
And the precondition, h,
guarantees that this version
respects the pure version
by a very simple argument.
Now, withPtrEq alone already
can yield exponential speedups
on pointer-equal terms trivially.
But small deviations from
pointer-equal from pointer-equality
remove the benefit entirely.
So, this is
an illustration of two terms
that share memory pointer
share an enormous tower,
but their heads are
actually different.
So, they are not themselves PtrEq,
even though their children are.
So, a single call to withPtrEq
will just see that they're
not pointer-equal,
and fall back on recursive
structural equality.
Obviously, what we want is to
call withPtrEq recursively
on the children, and we can do that.
The construction is
somewhat elaborate,
but it's entirely mechanizable,
requires no new primitives,
and the paper goes into
the details for those who are curious.
Now we're almost ready to
traverse terms in linear-time.
Consider the naive
exponential time algorithm
to evaluate a simple arithmetic
term into a natural number.
So, then here we have a term type
that has two constructors
one and add.
So, we can just evaluate
this into a map
by mapping one to the numeral one,
and by evaluating add t1,
t2, by first evaluating t1,
and evaluating t2, and adding
the results together.
Now, we're gonna show how to use
withPtrEq the recursive version,
to build a linear-time
version of this algorithm.
We need two additional components,
we need constant-time
intrusive hashing,
and we need something that we
call 'sharing the common data'
which I'll discuss shortly.
So, it's almost hard to believe
but even just computing the hash
of a tower requires
exponential time.
But hashing, unlike equality,
is a unary function.
So, in principal, we can compute it
once and just store it somewhere.
Which brings us to
this folklore trick,
which we call intrusive hashing,
which is to simply extend
the term type itself
to store the hashes of the terms
as extra arguments to
the constructors.
So, here the third argument
to add is an adder,
which is just our type that
represents hashes in this case,
and we can write a fast
constant-time hash function
that simply projects
out of this hash field.
And we can write a smart constructor
that internally calls
the built in constructor,
but will compute
the hash automatically
using the fast hash on the children.
Now, Lean4 has reference counting
and disruptive-updates,
so, we can actually use
imperative hash tables
and get the desired expected
O(1) lookup time.
But, if your language does
not have this feature,
then you can still use functional
or persistent hash tables,
and then all of the same
constructions applied,
but everytime we say linear really
means quasi-linear for you.
Now, the semi-naive traversal,
we call evalFastEqFastHash.
Which is to use the recursive
withPtrEq test for the equality,
and to also cache using
the constant-time
intrusive cache and a hash cache.
Now, this is already linear
time on this example,
strictly because of
the recursive withPtrEq.
And because of
the intrusive hash cache,
is also linear time on this
example, in expectation because,
with high probability the hashes
are going to be different,
and in the small chance
that they're the same,
they're very unlikely to be the same
again for the children and so on.
But this semi-naive algorithm
is still exponential
time on this example,
where we have two structurally equal
terms that are pointer disjoint.
And this brings us to
sharing the common data.
So, with low-level
pointer manipulations,
we can, quote, 'share
the common data' in linear-time.
And what we mean by that is
to take a term like this
that has multiple sub-terms
that are structurally equal,
but pointer disjoint,
and simply share the common
data or contact to the term
and produce the term such that
equality implies pointer-equality
of all sub-terms inside the term.
And now in the paper, we
introduce additional primitives
that allow writing pure
versions of this procedure
from first principles
in linear time.
But, as part of the Lean runtime,
we already have a high performance
version of this procedure
that applies to objects of any type.
So, there's no additional trust
required to simply expose it.
So, we present a new
primitive shareCommon
that is just the identity function
whose reference implementation
is just the identity function,
it actually takes no
additional preconditions.
But under the hood,
it's going to share the common
- use the runtime support
to share the common data inside x.
And finally, we have a robust
linear-time traversal,
which we are - to be
overly pedantic,
call evalFastEqFastHashShareCommon,
and the idea is simple,
we first share the common data
which takes linear-time,
and then we call evalFastEqFastHash,
which is linear-time as long as
the data is being maximally shared.
And our motto in general
is if terms are equal,
they should be pointer-equal,
and they will definitely be
pointer-equal after shareCommon.
And if terms are not equal,
their constant-time hashes
should not be equal
with high probability.
Now, the paper covers
many extensions
and alternatives to this approach.
I'll go through a couple
examples very briefly.
So, we can have
a pointer equality test
without requiring
reflexivity as follows.
Here's a primitive withPtrEqResult
that takes two terms x and y.
And instead of a thunk, k,
it's a continuation that gets
to see an optional proof
that x equals y.
But instead of returning a Bool in,
it returns an element
of any type beta.
And now the precondition we need
is that no matter what
proof we give it,
or what optional proof we give it,
this continuation is gonna
return the same value.
And the reference implementation
just calls it on none.
But at runtime, if x
and y are pointer-equal,
we call it with
the proof of reflexivity.
And we can also support direct
pointer address manipulation
with the new primitive withPtrAddr,
which takes a term x whose
address we wanna inspect
and it takes a continuation, k, that
is going to look at that address
and again, return an element
of an arbitrary type beta.
And the precondition we need here
is that no matter what address we
give k, k returns the same value.
And then the reference
implementation
just evaluates k at
an arbitrary value, zero,
whereas the optimized
version will evaluate k
on the actual memory address of x.
And the proof very
trivially implies that
the optimized version is
functionally indistinguishable
from the pure reference
implementation.
Perhaps the surprising
part of this is that
this precondition
isn't too restrictive.
And we show in the paper
that indeed we can do
many many sophisticated
constructions using withPtrAddr.
And in fact, combining
withPtrEqResult and withPtrAddr,
we can implement pointer
caches from first principals,
and we can implement shareCommon
from first principals, and so forth.
We recommend the
FastEqFastHashShareCommon approach
in general. It gives very good performance in
all our use cases in practice,
it's simple,
and the other constructions are
significantly more elaborate
for very little payoff.
And thank you, that's all
we have time for today.
(AUDIENCE APPLAUSE)
ALAN JEFFREY: Alright,
thank you, Daniel.
So, if you're interested in joining
the authors for a live Q&A,
and you're in the New York time zone,
then click on the link in
the Clowdr page for this paper.
Welcome back to ICFP 2020,
where the next paper is going to
be, "Effects for Efficiency:
Asymptotic Speedup with
First-Class Control,"
and it's going to be presented
by Daniel Hillerstrom.
DANIEL HILLERSTROM: Hi, my
name is Daniel Hillerstom,
and I'd like to tell you about
some recent work I've done
with Sam Lindley and John Longley,
on how the presence of
first-class control
your language can speed up
implementations of some programs.
I'll dive right in.
The purpose of this work is
really to explore space.
The space I have in mind here
is the design space of
programming languages.
When studying the expressiveness
of some language feature,
like first class control,
it is customary to consider
language with the said feature,
and then the fragment
modulo that feature.
Then we could pose questions along
different dimensions success,
computability...
complexity
and programmability.
However, any type of question
is really only interesting
if the setting involves
higher types,
because to a fair approximation,
we can regard all
reasonable languages,
with first-order types
as being equally expressive.
So in this work, we are in
the realm of higher types,
and we show that in this realm,
the presence of first
class control can improve
the asymptotic run time
of some programs.
To show this, we consider
this generic count problem
which is asked to implement
the third-order function
satisfying this type signature.
Let's unpack the type.
The first order function
parameter is called a point.
It is a functional representation
of a boolean value vector of size N.
The second order parameter
is a predicate function,
which operates on points.
It is an encoding of
some search problem,
and it yields true
or false depending on
where it is satisfied
by its provided point.
Finally, any faithful implementation
of this type signature
ultimately returns
the number of points
satisfying a given predicate,
or in other words,
it counts to number of times
a given predicate returns true.
We fix our base language
to be simple typed PCF
and extended with effect handlers.
Our concrete choice of control
operator is not essential.
Any first class control
operator will do,
however effect handlers
still provide a particular
structure form of
the limited control,
which makes them convenient
for the purpose of this work.
Then we first show that there
exists an implementation
of that generic count in PCF
for the effect handlers,
whose asymptotic worst
case runtime behavior
is two to the N.
Then we show that every
implementation of generic count
in pure PCF has at least
asymptotic runtime behavior
N two to the N.
That is to say there exist
a strict asymptotic efficiency gap
between PCF and PCF
with effect handlers,
due to the presence of first
class control in the latter.
In this talk, I will not provide you
with the actual proof of this.
Instead, I'll aim to
give you the intuition
for why this result is true.
I will elaborate a bit
on the methodology.
We impose one important rule,
namely that the type signature
of generic count is fixed.
That is no implementation in
PCF or PCF with effect handlers
is allowed to change the type
signature of generic count.
A consequence of this rule,
is that it's not possible
to translate PCF with effect
handlers into PCF,
say by way of an interpreter
or CPS translation.
This way we really get to
study the essence of the power
provided by effect
handlers. Moreover
this rule is also reminiscent
of the restriction
that programs are
faced by every day,
when programming
against an interface.
So we do consider this to
be a reasonable rule.
With this in mind, let's look
at the following example predicate
called EX and its
induced computation tree model.
The predicate takes a point as input
and applies this point to zero,
or queries to see if
component has the point.
This is reflected in the tree model,
by the first interior node,
which reads question mark zero.
I'm using the question
mark prefix here
to denote invocations
or queries of points.
And I'm using
exclamation mark prefix
to denote answers or return
values of predicates.
Now note how the structure
of the computation tree
coincides with all
the possible control flows
of the predicate.
Let's consider a concrete
evaluation of this predicate.
Supposed we apply to a point
whose zeroth component is true.
First component is false,
and second component is true.
Evaluation begins in the predicate,
and eventually queries the
zeroth component of the point,
which is true,
meaning that we'll take
the left branch down the tree
this corresponds to
continuing evaluation
of the then branch in the predicate.
Eventually, the predicate will
query the first component
of the point, which is false,
meaning we will take
the right branch down the tree,
and then, at some
point, the predicate
will query the second
component, which is true,
meaning we take the left
branch down at the tree,
and we now hit a leaf node
with the answer true,
meaning that for this
particular point,
the predicate will
yield the answer true.
Now, this particular predicate
belongs to a certain class
of predicates that admit
canonical models.
We call such predicates N-standard.
A tree model is N-standard
if it is a perfect binary tree
of height N, in addition
we also require that
the tree contains a query,
and that no sub tree
repeats any query.
We say that a predicate
is N standard
if its model is N standard.
For example, the predicate
EX is three standard.
For the initial analysis,
we restrict our attention
to N standard predicates.
This restriction serves to
simplify the analysis,
but it also provides us an instance
where the efficiency gap
between PCF and PCF
for the effect handles
manifests as clearly as possible.
This restriction will enable us
to give a crisp implementation
of generic count
with effect handles.
OK, let's consider how
one might go about
and implement generic
count with effect handles.
First, we need to take
the predicate as input.
And we have to apply this
predicate to a point.
We represent this point
as the invocation
of an abstract operation
called branch.
The only thing we know about branch
is that it's going to ultimately
return a Boolean value.
And also, given
the interpretation of branch,
we must wrap the entire
computation in a handler.
A handler consists of two parts,
a value clause that
tells it what to do
with the return value
or the answer of a predicate.
So if the answer is true, then
we're going to return one,
and if the answer is false,
we're going to return zero.
Then the second part is
an operation clause,
specifically a clause for
the branch operation,
which in addition to giving
access to the payload
also gives access to
the continuation
of the branch operation inside
the predicate computation.
This is a first class entity,
and what we do is we invoke
the continuation with true first,
and then we invoke it
with false subsequently,
and we sum up the result
of those two invocations.
Now, let's consider concrete
evaluation of effcount
applied to our example predicate.
The first thing that
happens is the predicate
queries the zeroth
component of the point.
This query causes an invocation
of the branch operation.
This invocation causes
control to transfer
into the branch clause
in the handler
where the first thing we do
is we resume
the continuation with true,
meaning that it is sent down to
the left branch in the tree.
Now, when the predicate
queries the first component
of the point, the very
same thing will happen.
Another invocation of
branch will occur
causing control to flow
into the branch clause
in the handler where we resume
the continuation with true,
so it is sent down
the left branch again.
We repeat this same argument
when the predicate
queries the second component,
so it is sent down the left branch.
Now, we find ourselves
ourselves at a leaf node,
meaning that we invoke
the value clause in the handler
with the answer false,
meaning that return a zero.
At this stage, the handler
is going to backtrack
to the most recent query
and apply the continuation to false,
taking us down the right
branch in the tree.
Now we find ourself
again at the leaf node,
so we're going to invoke
the value clause,
but this time with the answer true,
meaning that will return a one.
The handle is now going
to sum up the answers
that it got in the sub
tree, which is one.
And then it's going to backtrack
to the most recent query,
and then the pattern repeats.
So it's going to resume to
continuation with false,
and then subsequently with true.
So, backtracking here
ensures that every edge in the
computation tree model it's
been visited exactly once.
So if we generalize a bit.
This means that computation involves
Big O two to the N steps.
Now, in PCF, we dont have effect handles.
There's no mechanism
for backtracking
for sharing computation.
Therefore, every generic
counter function must restart
computation for every point.
Let me try to illustrate
what this means.
Let's consider some generic
comm function
applied to our example predicate,
and let's for simplicity,
assume that this
generic cunt function
visits the notes in
the computation tree
in depth first order.
The first thing that happens is that
the predicate queries the zeroth
component of the point,
which returns true,
meaning that'd be the sent down
the left branch in the tree.
The same thing happens
for the first component
and the second component.
And so we find ourselves
at the first leaf.
From here there is no
quick way to get to
the second leaf, because
there is no backtracking
on any means for sharing computation.
So the generic count function
has to go all the way back up
and construct a second point,
that represents the path
to the second leaf, meaning
that we will have to repeat
some work along the way,
in order to finally
the arrive at the second leaf.
And here the situation's the same.
In order to get to the third leaf,
we must go all the way back up,
construct the third point
that represents the path
to the third leaf, repeating
work along the way
in order to finally arrive
at the third leaf.
In general,
the generic count function
will have to construct points
in order to visit each of the leafs.
This means that computation
involves, at least,
two to the n steps.
Some might object to PCF as
a choice of base language,
because it lack characteristic
features found,
in say, industrial
strength languages.
However, as shown in the paper,
the efficiency gap remains
even under extensions to PCF.
Specifically, we consider
adding mutable static
and exceptions into the picture,
we consider them
separately and together,
and I will claim that once
we've put them together
our base language forms
a prototypical core,
of an industrial strength language,
like OCaml or Java.
Furthermore, in
the paper we also discuss
how to relax
the standard restriction.
That is so the predicate models
no longer needs to be
perfect binary trees,
and we can account
for repeat queries
and we don't even need to
query all the components
of a point.
We also consider how to extend
the problem to search,
that is, instead of returning
the number of times,
this predicate will
satisfy return to points
that satisfy the predicate.
We showed that the same
asymptotic bound applies
to the search problem.
We also conducted
empirical evaluation.
In summary, the takeaway is
that control operators admit,
asymptotically more
efficient implementations
of some programs,
and the intuition
for why that is true
is because control operators
enable computation
to be shared while backtracking.
And as for future work, we
would like to consider
how linear handles fits
into the picture.
So linear handles are
a special form of handlers
that only allow the continuation
to have been booked once.
It is not clear that our
current proof techniques
will adapt vertically
to the situation,
with the new handlers.
So, it would be interesting
to investigate.
Another thing that would be
interesting to investigate
would be a richer type system.
Say, one of the features
effect-typing,
and how that would
impact the result.
Thank you for tuning in to my talk,
and thank you for your attention.
(LIVELY PIANO MUSIC)
(AUDIENCE APPLAUDS)
ALAN JEFFREY: All right, so,
thank you, Daniel.
So, if you want to join
the authors for a live Q&A,
again, you can just
click on the link,
in the Clowdr room.
All right, and now, there is
going to be a short pause,
and when we come back,
we'll have the next paper,
in Session 2 of ICFP 2020.
(GENTLE LIGHT MUSIC)
Hello, and welcome
back to ICFP 2020.
And our next paper is going to
be "Computation Focusing,"
and it's going to be
presented by Nick Rioux.
NICK: My name is Nick Rioux,
and this talk is for the paper,
called "Computation Focusing,"
by myself, and my advisor,
Steve Zdancewic,
at the University of Pennsylvania.
Our paper is all about
proving program equivalents.
This is an important way
of reasoning about them.
So, whether you have a compiler
that performs CPS translations,
or just some optimizer that
does function inlining,
in order to justify them,
you're probably going to want
to be able to prove
programs equivalent.
The, sort of, gold
standard of equivalence,
the notion that we care most about,
is called contextual equivalence.
And two programs are
contextually equivalent
when they show the same
behavior in all contexts,
there's no way to
distinguish between them.
But proving this is difficult
because there's so many
different possible contexts
that programs could be used in
that we can't really just do
a case analysis on all of them.
So we need other techniques
to prove equivalences
and the CIU theorem does this.
It allows us to,
rather than consider all
possible general contexts,
only look at evaluation contexts
paired with closing substitutions,
but there are still
difficulties here.
And in particular in call by value,
there's still many possible
evaluation contexts.
So it's difficult to reason
about the interaction
between a term and its context
and call by name has this
very similar dual problem.
So another class of
syntactic proof techniques
includes logical relations
and bisimulations.
Logical relations in particular,
give you a really nice high
level reasoning principles
like relational parametricity,
but there are still
some limitations.
And one of those limitations
is that some equivalences
between existential types
have not been easy to prove
in the past using logical relations.
And the problem is essentially
that logical relations
are just more natural to use
to reason about how
a program produces an output,
than how it uses its input.
So let's look at a particular value
of this existential type.
And let's look at how these
values of this type are used.
Well, we used existential types
by pattern matching on them
to unpack them.
And here we unpack this
existential into a function Y
and this Y is a high order function.
So we pass another function
F as input into it.
And F has the type X arrow X,
but this X type is an abstract type.
And so F must be
the identity function.
So with that in mind, let's
look at these two values
of the same existential type.
They contain functions
that themselves
take another function as input F
and they both apply F to
many different values,
checking to see that it does indeed
behave as the identity function.
Since we've already
shown that this is true,
we can look at
the functions in these packages
and confirm that they both are
always going to return true,
no matter what.
So, in other words, this means
that they must be equivalent.
But logical relations
in bisimulations
struggle to prove this
because they force you
to come up with some relational
interpretation for X
that somehow relates
values of Boolean type
to values of Integer type.
But we have no such
relation in mind here.
There's not really a correspondence
between the values of X
in one of these packages
with values of X in
the other package.
So instead, what we want to do
is look at the possible context
these values may be used in
and exploit the fact that
they're constrained
by their types.
So throughout the rest of the talk,
we're going to look at
a proof theoretic technique
called focusing and show
that that's actually useful
for reasoning about programs.
In fact, we can use that to
prove this equivalence.
Lastly, we'll see why this
technique might be useful
in compositional
compiler correctness.
For this talk, we're
gonna deal with
a call by value language
with predicative polymorphism
in a pure setting,
but the paper goes beyond
some of these restrictions.
So what is focusing?
Well, focusing is
a proof search technique
that narrows down the search space
when you're trying to find
a proof of a certain proposition.
And viewed through
the lens of Curry Howard,
you can think of it as
making things easier
when you're trying to synthesize
a program of a given.
So how does focusing
narrow down the search space?
Well, it does that by visiting
fewer redundant terms
that are just equivalent to each
other via beta or eta laws.
We don't have time to go into
focusing in depth today
but I wanted to give you a flavor
of what focused terms look like.
So let's try and visit
all the focused programs
of Boolean to Boolean type.
The first thing that
focusing says we can do
is apply the lambda type constructor
anytime we have a function
on the right hand side.
So that just any term in our
language of function type
is going to be equivalent
to sum lambda.
And that's true by
eta in call by name
and in call by value we're
also using normalization.
But if you didn't have normalization
you could still use this technique
you would just have an extra non-terminating
term to consider.
So now we need to consider
what the body of
the lambda might be.
And when we're trying to build that
focusing says that
the first thing we can do
is eagerly pattern match.
Anytime there's
something in the context
that can be pattern matched on
focusing says we might as well
do that pattern matching right now,
there's no point
waiting until later.
So now we know that all
the terms we're interested in
have a lambda on the outside
and then immediately pattern
match on it's input.
And what we're left to
build are the two branches
of the if statement.
Both of these are closed
because focusing knows
that there's no point
in pattern matching on x twice
once we've already done it.
And so we just need to
build focused programs
of Boolean type.
And it turns out there
are only two of those,
true and false.
And so we can use those to build
our four candidate programs here
and turns out that every function
of Boolean to Boolean type
needs to be equivalent to
one of these four focused programs.
We've cut out many, many
non-focused programs
such as the identity
function lambda x.x
but this program is
still represented
in the second bullet point here.
So some properties of focused
terms to keep in mind
are that focused terms are
always beta eta normal.
There's no way to beta reduce them
and they can't be eta expanded
without introducing a redex.
And we characterize
them in our paper
as a restricted type system.
Basically, the usual type
rules that you're used to
but restricted to be
applied in a certain order
and this gives you strong
inversion principles
to do programmatic reasoning.
Lastly, for every focused term,
for every well typed term,
there's some equivalent
focused term.
This is called
computational completeness
and it's the key property we need
for reasoning about programs
and basically all it says is that
we may have eliminated many
redundant representations
of the same program but we
haven't lost anything of value,
there's still some
representative focus program
for any other program.
So why are we talking about
a proof search technique
in a talk about
contextual equivalence?
Well, it turns out that a proof
of contextual equivalence
is just a search through
all possible contexts
demonstrating the same
behavior for each context.
And so if you think
about it like this
and you apply
the completeness of focusing
then you can see that
there's no need
to search through all
possible contexts,
you only need to search
through focused contexts.
So that leads us to
a context dilemma
which looks a little hairy
but all this is saying is that
to prove two values equivalent
you only need to consider
focused contexts
which are represented
by a term, an f,
with a whole x represented
as a variable here.
And if v1 and v2 are open then
you need to close them off
with some closing substitutions
but you can assume
that all the values
in those substitutions are focused.
So let's return to the equivalence
that we wanted to prove earlier.
And now we'll apply
our focusing loma.
And this context loma says,
since these values are closed,
we just need to consider
some context NF
and show that they
both behave the same
when the values are filled in for X.
So what does the fact that
NF is focused tell us?
Well the whole in NF X
has existential type,
and we know that existential types
can be pattern matched on.
So focusing says let's
do that right away.
Now once we unpack the existential,
we get this function Y,
and the rest of the body
of the pattern
after each statement gets to
call Y potentially.
So there's really only two
things that we can do here,
either we call Y or we
don't, and if we don't,
then we can only return
a constant bullion value.
So there are three possible shapes
of programs here that
this context may take.
We need to show that the two values
behave the same in each of them.
This is easy in the case
of the constant bullion
because the context just
ignores its input.
The interesting case
is when we call Y.
And what happens here
is that V1
is going to get destructed
and substituted in for Y.
And it's gonna get passed in F,
which we've talked about before
must be the identity function.
So if you plug
the identity function into
the functions in V1
and V2, and you reduce,
you can see that both
of them return true.
So what's left in
the proof is to show that Z
is equal to true in both cases.
And that, combined with
a small detail
about the proof structure
that you can see
in the paper, let us
complete this proof.
Now that we've seen
program equivalence,
let's look at compiler correctness.
One property you might
want about your compiler
is that it preserves
all of the abstractions
in the source language.
So to say this more
precisely,
you can say that two terms in the source
language are equivalent
implies that after you compile them,
they should still be equivalent.
To prove this, you need to consider
an arbitrary source target
language context, C prime,
but we have a source language
equivalence to use.
So we need to back translate
the target context
C prime to a source
language equivalence.
And the key idea that
focusing helps us with here
is that we don't need
to back translate
every single possible
target context,
we only need the back
translate the focused ones.
There's a long history of using
focusing in proof theory,
but there's also a related
work here that uses
focusing in the context of
programming languages.
Especially as a guide to design
features of programming languages.
There's also work that uses focusing
as a normalization
procedure to decide the equivalence of terms
in the simply typed lambda calculus.
Lastly, normalization by evaluation
is pretty relevant
because it could be used
to prove our completeness
of focusing theorem.
There are many different
types system features
and effects that we might
study, and we expect
focusing to be a useful tool
along with all of these.
In particular,
the combination of linearity
and focusing is really
interesting to study
because that's where
focusing originated
and because linear
lambda calculus terms
have very nice normal forms
that make them easy to reason about.
To recap, our paper
contributes a few things.
First, we formulate focusing
in a call by value language
with predicative polymorphism.
And we provide a proof
of the computational
completeness there.
Then we prove a context lemma
and show that that's useful in turn
to prove various
programming equivalencies
like the one we saw today.
Finally, we showed that
focusing can be used
to prove compositional compiler
correctness properties,
like full obstruction.
And when we do this
for a simple compiler
from a language that's
pure into a language
with a simple divergence effect,
that's tracked by an effect system.
That's all for focusing for now.
Thank you.
(APPLAUSE)
ALAN JEFFREY: All right, so,
thank you, Nick.
If you're interested in joining
the authors of this paper
for a live Q&A and you're
in the New York timezone,
and then you can click on
the link in the Clowdr Room.
And now we're going to have
a short break,
please come back and join us
for the next paper in this session.
(UPBEAT JAZZY MUSIC)
(MUSIC FADES)
So, welcome back to
the second session of ICFP 2020,
and our next paper is going to be
"Retrofitting
Parallelism into OCaml."
And it's been presented
by KC Sivaramakrishnan.
KC: Hi, I'm KC and I'm going
to present our work on
retrofitting parallelism into OCaml.
So OCaml is a reasonably
popular programming language
that is used by several,
multiple industries,
but also widely in the academia.
Vocab and language has particularly
found favor for implementing
software verification
and static analysis tools
and also low-latency system services
and for all of its strengths
OCaml is one of the few
systems programming languages
that lacks support for multi-core.
To that end multi-core
OCaml is an ongoing project
which aims to add native support
for concurrency
and parallelism in OCaml.
Concurrency in multi-core
OCaml is added
with the help of effect handlers,
but the focus of this
particular talk is going to be
on parallelism and in
particular, we are going to
look at the details of
a multi-core capable
garbage collector that we have
in (INAUDIBLE) types of OCaml.
The design space for
multi-core OCaml,
multi-core garbage
collectors is quite wide.
And what makes our
work unique is that
our design is guided by
backwards compatibility concerns
before parallel scalability.
So adding parallelism to
OCaml has several challenges.
OCaml has millions of lines
of code in production
that have been written without
explicit parallelism in mind.
And this core tends to also
use advanced features
such as weak references,
ephemerons, lazy values
and finalizers, which
closely interact
with the current GC.
OCaml also exposes
a low level of C API
that allows the developers to
write very efficient code,
but also bakes in the GC ingredients
and the cost of refactoring
sequential code
in order to work on
a parallel run-time
is quite prohibitive.
So that is not something
that we would want to do.
OCaml is also a type-safe language.
The additional parallelism
should break type-safety.
For this, we directly
borrow the memory model
that was presented
in the PLD 2018 paper,
Bounding databases
in space and time,
which guarantees not
just type-safety,
but also other strong
properties under databases.
Developers using OCaml have
come to love and embrace
the low latency and predictable
performance of OCaml.
And this is thanks to the GC design.
Stock OCaml garbage collector
is a non-moving incremental
mark-and-sweep GC
where new objects are allocated
into a small minor heap
by bump pointer allocation
and survivors are copied
to the major heap.
The major heap is collected
with the incremental
non-moving
mark-and-sweep collector.
At the start of a major cycle
there is a small idle phase
after which the roots are
incrementally marked,
followed by incrementally
marking the rest of the heap.
And once the marking is done,
any unreachable objects
are incrementally swept.
And at the end of sweeping,
we come to the end
of our major cycle.
This design has several
nice properties.
The allocations into the minor heap,
which are majority of
allocations are quite fast,
and we do not have any read barriers
for reading OCaml object fields.
And this design being
incremental
also leads to enviable tail
latency performance.
And while we add parallelism
to this language,
we would like to keep some
of these nice properties
still going.
So we arrive at these
following requirements
for retrofitting
parallelism onto OCaml.
Firstly, we don't want
serial programs to break on
the parallel runtime.
A well typed serial program
remains well typed
on the parallel runtime.
And we also do not plan to
provide separate modes
for serial and parallel
execution
as Glasgow Haskell Compiler does.
This is because we want to reduce
the burden of maintenance
on the OCaml developers.
Secondly, we want the performance of
CDL programs to be the same,
wile running on the battle
runtime in terms of
the running time GC for
stains and memory usage.
And lastly, we want our battle programs
to remain responsive.
And then we want
the pilot programs to be able
to scale the traditional course.
We ordered the priorities this way
because getting responsiveness
is much harder
than making our programs go faster.
So with that, we
designed a multicolor
OCaml garbage collector.
And our multicolor red
allocator is based
on the screen Flow allocator,
which uses thread local
size segment of tree lists
for small objects
and resorts two system alleys
for large allocation.
And the performance of
this allocator is better
than OCaml first expert allocator
and is on par with the recent
best-fit allocator from OCaml.
And the major heap is
collected with the
mostly concurrent non-moving
mark and sweep collector,
based on the VCDC design.
One nice aspect of this
design is that we only need
a very short barrier at
the end of every major cycle.
And I should, at this point mention
that domains are our
units of adolescence.
And in particular, there
is no phase separation
between marking and sweeping
and marking and sweeping phases
between multiple
domains may overlap.
One of the major contributions
in this paper is
extending this design
to support a variety
of additional features such as
weak references, ephemeron,
two different kinds of
finalisers, fibers lazy values
and so on.
Ephemerons are particularly
tricky to get efficiently
implemented in
the concurrent multi-core GC.
Ephemerons themselves are
generalization of weak references,
and the property that
they bring in is,
they introduce conjunction in
the reachability property
of OCaml in for objects in the heap
And this requires multiple
rounds of ephemeron marking
and also marking the heap in
order to reach a fixed point.
And in this work,
what we've shown is
we can implement a cycle
delimited handshaking algorithm
in order to perform
the ephemeron marking,
without requiring a global barrier.
The two different kinds
of finaliser in Ocaml
also need two barriers,
one barrier each.
And in the worst case, we need
the three barriers per cycle,
a major cycle.
And because this design
is quite tricky,
we verify the model of
this design (INAUDIBLE)
Next, we come to the issue of
what to do about minor GCs.
Our initial design was based
on a knowledge of 93 collector,
which uses a minor heap domain,
but it's a lazier on the line,
serves the GC collector from
Marlow and Peyton Jones, 2011.
So this particular
design has an invariant
that there are no pointers
between two minor heaps.
And this allows each domain
to be independently
garbage collected.
And unlike the original
Dialogue lever design,
we are low pointers from
the major to the minor heap.
And the reason why we
allow this is two fold.
First, it prevents
eager promotion, right?
So early promotion is
a problem where you point
to an object, which is promoted,
which would
otherwise have not been.
If you hadn't
established this pointer
and this also mirrors
sequential behaviour
and unfortunately, what this does is
a particular domain
may follow a pointer
from the major to the minor heap
to remote minor heap.
And this will break
the invariant that we had.
So, what we need to do is
insert a read barrier
on reading OCaml object fields
which detects whether the result
of the read is going to be
a value and a remote minor heap
in which case, the domain
sensor interdomain entrap
requesting the target domain
to come out the object
which in turn might perform
a local minor garbage collection.
And then, the execution proceeds.
Recall that I had mentioned that
OCaml does not have read barriers
and now, this design has
interviews read barriers.
So, the first challenge is that we
need these read barriers to be
implemented efficiently for
performance backwards compatibility.
And in the paper, we showed
that we can do this
but the clever vector of
virtual memory mapping and
a series of bit-twiddling tricks,
using which, we have brought
down the read barrier to
three (INAUDIBLE) instructions.
And the proof of correctness of
this is available in the paper.
And the...
Because this
(INAUDIBLE) are going to be sorted.
The branch corrector correctly
predicts the branch
almost every read.
So, the performance impact of
these additional instructions is
minimal on sequential code.
Unfortunately though,
the introduction of the read barriers
breaks the C API.
And check out this example where
we have two domains, each
of which is reading
a major heap object which
points to the other domain.
So, at this point, this domain
sends a promotion request
to the other domain.
So, the two domains simultaneously
send promotion requests
and in order to prevent that
lock and make progress,
when the domain sends
a promotion request,
it has to keep servicing
other promotion requests
that it may receive.
So, the issue is that because
promotion may involve
a minor collection,
a mutable read is in fact a GC
safe point where GC may happen.
But this
breaks the (INAUDIBLE) that
we haven't stored OCaml well.
We don't have any
read barriers at all
and in particular, the C API
is often explicitly written
with the knowledge of
when the GC may happen.
And introducing
a read barrier, where the read
barrier is a GC safe point
will require manually
refactoring very tricky code.
And this is unfortunate.
So, in order to
get around this, we also implement
the parallel minor collector
which does stop-the-world
parallel minor collection
similar to GHCs minor collection.
So, this shows
a timeline of
the concurring minor collector
where we have two domains
and the minor collections
here can order
what are the activities being
done on the other domains.
And in particular, we read a barrier
once per major cycle
whereas in the parallel
minor collector, we read
barrier
two barriers for every
minor collection
in order to indicate
the start and end.
And these minor collections
are very frequent
and
in order to better utilize
idle time
while we are waiting for
the minor collections to complete
and when a particular domain has
completed its minor collection
but it's waiting for other domains
to complete the minor collections,
we fill this (INAUDIBLE)
space in the
in the barrier with major slices.
The advantage of this design is that
we don't read barriers anymore.
But our global barriers
are quite frequent now.
So, we need to be able to quickly
bring all of the domains to a stop.
So, we insert poll points in our
code for timely interrupt handling.
And this is based on
Feeley's paper from 93.
So, the big question is
how does this perform?
So, we perform evaluation on a
U circuit 14 quad Intel
Xeon on a Gold CPU
where we've isolated 24 cores
for performance evaluation.
And we observe that the sequential
throughput is comparable to OCaml.
The... Compared to stock Ocaml
Concurrent Minor was 4.9% slower
and Parallel Minor was 3.5% slower.
These overheads are quite reasonable
and the reason why Concurrent Minor
is slower then Parallel Minor is
that the additional instructions
for read barriers.
But we also observed that both
Concurrent Minor and Parallel Minor
used much lower peak memory
than stock OCaml.
This is because our
allocator is much more efficient
introducing fragmentation.
So, this gives us promise that
we can relax the memory bounds
in order to get better
running times.
And we also observed that our
sequential GC pause times
are on par with OCaml.
These results and more details
are available on the paper.
Next, we look at
parallel scalability.
The graphs here show
that the scalability...
The speed up of each
of the benchmarks
with respect to sequential baseline.
Overall, we see that the two
variants perform similarly
except a few notable differences.
On a few benchmarks,
Concurrent Minor really
suffers due to read faults
where just performing
a read requires
sending an (INAUDIBLE), requesting
the other domain to promote,
that domain promotes while
the domain with read folder is
idly waiting.
And we also see other cases
where the unbalanced allocation
leads to inopportune minor
GCs in Parallel Minor
which causes scalability issues.
We also observed that the parallel
GC latency was roughly similar
between Parallel Minor
and Concurrent Minor.
And (INAUDIBLE) means
Parallel Minor wins
over Concurrent Minor
because firstly, it
doesn't break the C API.
And it performs almost
similarly up to 24 cores.
And OCaml 5.00 which will
have multicore support
will use Parallel Minor.
We may reuse the Concurrent
Minor later for
a time when
commodity machines will have lot of
lot of codes than
they do now.
I'll stop here. Thank you.
(AUDIENCE CLAPS)
ALAN JEFFREY: So, thank you KC.
And if you wanna join the authors
for a live Q&A,
click on the link in Clowdr.
Hello and welcome back to
the second session for ICFP 2020.
And the last paper in this
session is going to be
liquid information flow control
and it's gonna be presented  by
Jean Yang and Nadia Polikarpova.
JEAN YANG: If you're
the director of the FBI,
you should be able to keep your
social media accounts on lockdown,
but this turned out
not to be the case
for former FBI Director James Comey.
Journalist Ashley
Feinberg discovered
Comey's secret Instagram and Twitter
simply by sending a follow request
to Comey's sons private Instagram.
The culprit,
a leak in Instagram's
suggestions algorithm.
This kind of thing affects many
more of us than just the Comeys
and it happens more
and more everyday.
NADIA POLIKARPOVA: Today's software
handles lot of sensitive information
subject to complex
security policies.
Traditionally, programmers
enforce these policies
by string policy enforcing
code or policy checks
throughout the application.
It is all too easy to
miss a chat by mistake
causing a potential
information leak.
A much better approach is to let
programmers specify policies
declaratively and separately
from the application code.
And then, let an information
flow control framework
ensure that the code
satisfies these policies.
IFC frameworks come in two
flavors - static and dynamic
which have complementary
strengths and weakenesses.
In this work, we will
focus on static techniques
which ensure absence of leaks
once and for all a compile time,
hence avoiding surprise failures
and performance overhead at runtime.
On the flipside, existing static
techniques are enabled to handle
rich policies that modern
applications need
or if they can, they require
programmers to provide proof hints
to verify absence of leaks.
In this work, we developed
a new IFC framework called Lifty
short for Liquid
Information Flow Types
which combines the best of
static and dynamic techniques.
Lifty is a static framework
but unlike existing static solutions,
it is able to verify rich security
policies completely automatically.
To enable this
automatic verification,
our first contribution
is an encoding of IFC
into a decidable type system
based on liquid types,
hence the name.
Moreover, when the application code
does not satisfy the policies,
Lifty can automatically
generate leak patches
that make the code provably secure.
Our second contribution is
a leak repair technique
based on type driven
program synthesis.
In the rest of this talk,
I will first introduce our encoding
of IFC into liquid types.
I will then give a demo of what
it's like to program in Lifty.
And finally, I will
give an overall review
of how Lifty's leak repair works.
In the liquid types system,
types are annotated with
logical predicates
called refinements.
For example, this is how
you would specify
the type of natural numbers.
By restricting refinements
to decidable logics,
liquid types provide fully
automatic type checking
of non-trivial program properties,
but can we use refinement types
to encode security policies?
To answer this question,
we draw inspiration
from another line of prior
work, security monads.
In this approach, computations
that manipulate sensitive data
live inside a special monad
which we will refer to as TIO.
For example, TIO Int is
the type of sensitive computations
that return an integer.
The purpose of the security monad
is to keep track of
the security level of the data
that the computation manipulates
and to disallow unsafe
information flows.
In Lifty, the security level is
recorded in the TIO type itself.
Apart from the return type,
TIO is parameterized by
two refinement predicate -
the input and the output label
which specify the security levels
of the input and output effects
of a TIO computation.
More precisely, the input labels
specifies the set of users
that are allowed to see
the data read by this computation.
The output label specifies
the set of users
who will see the data
written by this computation.
Both labels are predicates
from the refinement logic
and can refer to variables in scope
as well as a special
viewer variable.
Now, let's see how our Lifty
programmer builds TIO computations.
The building blocks
of a TIO computation
are atomic input and output
actions that the programmer writes
to model sources and sinks of
sensitive data in the system.
For example, if my program
can access a shared key
that belongs to Alice and Bob,
I can give this action
in the following type.
Here, the input label specifies
that the key's only
visible to Alice and Bob,
while the output label false
guarantees that this computation
will not perform any
user visible output.
On the other hand, I can
define an output action print
that outputs a string
to a given recipient.
The output label of
its type guarantees
that only the intended
recipient will see the string
while the input label true indicates
that the return value
unit is public.
Good luck trying to hide a unit.
Know that function types in
Lifty can be dependent,
so the label of the result can depend
on the value of the argument.
This allows Lifty programmers to
encode rich security policies
as types of TIO actions.
Atomic actions are combined into
computations using the TIO API
that Lifty provides.
The core of the API under
standard monadic primitives
return and bind.
Return simply wraps a pure value
into a sensitive computation.
And so, its labels are trivial.
The type of bind on the other hand
is key to correctly tracking
information flow in Lifty.
Bind sequences two
computations X and Y
such that the result
of X flows into Y.
The type of bind is polymorphic
in labels of these actions,
but not any four labels would do.
To avoid leaks, we need to ensure
that Y only outputs to those users
who are allowed to
see the result of X.
This is encoded by adding
the input label i of X
as a conjunct to
the output label of Y
essentially enforcing that Y's output
label is more restrictive than i.
Finally, the input label of
the sequence of X and Y
is the conjunction of
their input labels
and the output label is
the disjunction of their output labels.
The TIO API has a third
primitive operation
(INAUDIBLE) free downgrade
which plays an important role
in applications with rich policies
but I will skip this description
in the interest of time.
The TIO library also provides
a range of convenient
monadic combinators -
for example, mapM for mapping
a sensitive computation over a list.
Note that while
the primitive operations
are part of the trusted
computing base,
the derived operations are not.
They're implemented in terms
of the primitive operations
and the type check
using Lifty itself.
Now, let's see how I can use Lifty
to implement some simple functionality
of a conference manager.
Say I'm on the program
committee of IFCP 20
and I'm viewing the list
of all submissions,
but I'm also an author of one of
the submissions highlighted in grey.
As an author, I have a conflict
with this submsision.
The conference manager has
a policy that a conflicted reviewer
is not supposed to learn
the score or the decision for a paper
until the notifications are out.
Consider the following
hypothetical but insidious leak
that violates this policy.
As a reviewer, I can sort the list
of all submissions by their score.
If the programmer's not careful,
the sorting function might
use the true hidden value
of the score for my
paper for ordering.
In this case, even though
the score is still masked,
by looking at the position
of my paper in the list,
I can infer that the score is
somewhere between 1.8 and 2.0
and hence, the paper has
likely been accepted.
Yes!
Let's see how Lifty would
help us prevent this leak.
To implement a conference
manager in Lifty,
I'll start by encoding
the interface to the data store
as a set of atomic TIO actions.
For example, I'll add
an action that retrieves
the list of all submission
IDs from the data store
and action that retrieves
a paper title by its ID
and so on for each column
of my submissions table.
Now, it's time to add policies.
Recall that paper scores
are restricted to users
who are not conflicted
with the paper.
So, I would like to
change the input label
of getPaperScore to
reflect this policy.
Although the refinement
logic does not allow
mentioning program level functions
like getPaperConflict inside labels.
I can define an uninterpreted
logic level function conflicts
that denotes the set of user
conflicted with a given paper.
I can now use this function to
specify the desired policy on scores
that they are only visible to users
who are not in the set of conflicts.
To connect my logic level function
to the data ID from the store,
I will refine the result
type of getPaperConflicts
stating that it retrieves
exactly the same users
as those denoted by conflicts.
Finally, let's implement
the sorting functionality.
To this end, I will write
a function sortPapersByScore
that takes an input
at data store, ds
and the current user, client.
Lifty supports
a Haskell-like do notation
that desugars into invocatoins
of bind in a standard way.
Here, I first retrieved
the list of all submissions,
then sort them using
a custom comparator
that I will implement shortly
and finally project the paper titles
and output them to the current user.
Our custom comparator function
retrieves the scores of
the two papers from the store
and compares them.
I might not realize that
the functionality I just implemented
leaks information.
After all, I'm only printing
paper titles which are public.
Thankfully, Lifty is
watching my back.
If I ask to type check my program,
it reports two policy violations
for the two calls to getPaperScore.
Lifty is complaining that
they're not visible to client.
Instead of trying to
decipher that error message
and fix the leak myself
I can ask lifty to do it for me.
In this case, lifty
returns a modified program
where I call to get paper score
is wrapper in a power seacheck.
The check retrieves
the conflict list for this paper
and checks whether
the client is on that list.
If client is in fact conflicted
our generated patch returns
a default score of zero.
In the final part of the talk
let's see how lifty's leak
repair works under the hood.
Consider a stripdown version of
the leak I just showed you.
In this version we simply
read the paper score
and directly show it to the user
who of course might be conflicted.
How does lifty repair this leak?
The key insight is to
use the information
from the failed type
checking attempt
to localize the leak and infer
a local specification for the patch.
First, let's desugar the denotation
into invocations of bind.
While type checking the program
lifty infer the following
types for the two computations
sequenced by bind.
Now recall that our type
signature for bind
enforces that the output label
of the second computation
be more restrictive than
the input label of the first one
hence type checking in this case
reduces to the following
implication between the labels.
Lifty uses SMT software to
validate this implication.
In this case the check fails
and the program is deemed ill-typed.
Lifty keeps track of
which input action
generated the right-hand side
of the failed implication.
So it knows exactly
where the leak occurred.
In this case, the problem is
the call to get paper score
whose result is too
sensitive for its context.
To fix the leak lifty replaces
the offending input action
with a patch template
whose intention is to return
the original value whenever it's safe
and otherwise return a less
sensitive default or deducted value.
Crucially the lifty type checker
not only pinpoints the input
action that needs to be replaced
but also infers a local specification
that the patch needs to satisfy
in order for
the program to be secure.
In particular, the optimal
input label for the patch
is derived directly from the left-hand
side of the failed implication.
With the local specification at hand
we can use our prior work on
type-driven program synthesis
to fill the holes in the patch,
checking whether the client
is conflicted with the paper
and if so returning zero.
Thanks to the inferred
local specification
synthesis is performed completely
independently for each leak.
So leak repair scales reasonably well
to programs with multiple leaks
as we have seen in the demo.
In conclusion,
we have presented a new static
IFC framework called lifty.
Lifty is able to statically
and automatically verify applications
against rich security policies
and suggest leak patches
when the application does
not satisfy the policies.
You can play with lifty
through our web interface
available at this link.
ALAN JEFFREY: Thank you June and Nadia.
So there's going to be
live Q&A for this talk
as you are in the New York timezone
and you can get to it as
usual by going to the link.
So now if you would like to join us
for the virtual (INAUDIBLE) inside
the conference hall
chatting and drinking coffee.
That would be great.