JEREMY GIBBONS: Hello, my
name is Jeremy Gibbons,
together with Shriram Krishnamurthi,
I'm editor and chief of
The Journal of Functional Programming.
This year, we are trying out a new
interaction between JFP and ICFP.
Authors of JFP papers
published in the previous year
are offered the opportunity
to present their work
at that year's conference
provided that the paper
hasn't arisen out
of an earlier presentation.
This year authors of eight
papers took up the opportunity
and their presentations are
collected in this session.
Copies of those papers are freely
accessible on the JFP website
with links from the ICFP website.
The session is being streamed twice
one is at a convenient
time in New York
and again 11 hours later,
at a convenient time in Asia.
I remind you that registered
ICFP participants
will get the full
experience through Clowdr
including text chat during the talk.
Depending on the availability
of the authors,
there may also be a live video
Q&A session after the talk
in the New York stream and I will
announce that at the end of the talk
but there's no live Q&A
in the Asia stream.
The first talk is
a presentation of the paper,
A Theory of RPC Calculi
for Client-Server Model
which extends existing
stateless calculi
to cover stateful interactions.
The authors of the paper are
Kwanghoon Choi
and Byeong-Mo Chang
and Kwanghoon will be presenting.
KWANGHOON CHOI: Hello everyone.
I'd like to give a talk about
A Theory of RPC
Calculi for Client-Server Model.
My name is Kwanghoon Choi,
this is a joint work
with Byeong-Mo Chan.
Let me start with a background.
Developing distributed systems is
known as complex and error-prone.
For example, consider a web system.
You have to develop two
programmes, one for client
and the other for server in-
generally, in two
different form languages.
Also, the two programmes
need to be put together
for testing and maintenance.
tierless programme languages
also known also called
multitier programme languages
can address this problem.
You have only to develop
a single tierless programme.
Assuming a client-server model,
a slicing compiler will automatically
slice it into a client programme
and a server programme.
The communication between
the two sliced programmes
will be automatically supportive.
Particularly, we are
interested in a seamlessly
tierless programme language
for client-server model.
It is basically a programme language
designed for a single computer
but naturally extended
with a seamless RPC.
By the seamless remote
procedure call, RPC,
I mean the remote procedure
calls are language supported,
bi-directional
and fully transparent.
Links is a real world seamlessly
tierless programme language
for a client-server model.
One advantage of the seamlessly
tierless programme language is this.
If you look at this example
programme written in links,
you know that tierless programme can
be written exactly in the same way
as writing single computer programmes.
The only difference is specifying
the locational function.
Here, client means that
the main is a client function
that must run at client.
Here, server means that
the authenticate is a server function
that must run as server.
Firstly, it is language
supported not library-based.
Second, you can call a server
function from the client
and also you can call a client
function from the server,
so, it is bi-directional.
Third, the same syntax of
lambda application is used,
first, for local procedure call
and remote procedure call.
No extra RPC keyword is
used in the syntax.
So, links is the seamlessly
tierless programming language
for client-server model.
The RPC calculus is
a seamlessly tierless calculus
that extends the lambda
calculus with an RPC feature.
It was proposed as a foundation
of links by Cooper and Wadler.
In the calculus, c is
the client location,
s denote the server location.
Every lambda extraction has
a location annotation a
meaning that this must run
at a specified location a.
The RPC feature is described
by the big steps semantics.
When you evaluate a lambda
application at location a,
you evaluate the functional term L
at the same location a
into a lambda abstraction with
location and notation b.
You also evaluate an argument M
to our value W at the same location.
And then finally you do beta
reduction at the location b not a.
In the semantic rule for
lambda application,
the caller location a,
and the function location is b.
If a is different from b, then
the lambda application LM
is a remote procedure call.
If a is the same as b,
it is a local procedure call.
We use the same syntax for both
calls so it is fully transparent.
The seamless RPC is good for
tireless programming.
However, due to the transparency
of the seamless RPC
every lambda abstraction has to
check the function location
in runtime to decide
if it is RPC or not.
This happens even in the sliced
client and server programmes
after the slicing compilation.
Our solution is to have
located function types
to trap function
location statically.
Then we can statically decide
if given lambda application
is local procedure call
or remote procedure call.
As a result, programmemers can enjoy
the advantage of the seamless RPC
in the tierless programmes
but no more runtime location
checking is required
in the sliced client
and server programmes.
A key idea behind our
typed RPC calculus
is a location annotation
on a function type.
It is a reminiscent of a location
annotation on a lambda extraction.
The located function type means that
every lambda extraction
of these type
must run, is guaranteed to run
at a specified location a.
For example the argument f
has a client function type
because a client function is
going to be bounded to f.
In the second example, f has
neither a client function type
nor a server function type.
Because depending on
the value of if conditioner
was client function and server function
can be bounded to f.
In the typed RPC characters
only monomorphic
locations are allowed
so it is not well typed.
The other key idea is that
in the typed RPC calculus
you can identify all remote procedure
calls statically in compared time.
Let us see, it is typing rule.
This is a refinement of the conventional
lambda application typing rule
with respect to a caller location A
and a functional location B.
Once your tierless programme
is successfully type checked
in every lambda application LM
the caller location A
and the function location B
are fully analysed
and known in compared time.
Then caller location a is equal
to the function location b
then that lambda application
is local procedure call.
Otherwise a is different from b
then this is a remote
procedure call.
In this way, you can statically decide
if given lambda application
is local or remote procedure calls.
By the type soundness property
every remote procedure call
does analyse statically
will never be dynamically
changed into any local one.
Thanks to this property,
we can design a location information
directed slicing compilation
whose sliced clients and subprogrammes
will never do location checking,
dynamically in a long time.
This is an advantage over
the untyped RPC calculus
that always does location checking
in the sliced client
and several programmes.
The typed RPC calculus
is good so far
but it has a problem
because of using only
monomorphic locations
such as client and server
not something to report both.
For example you cannot write
a single polymorphically
located map function.
Instead you have to write
a client map function
and a server map
function separately.
A solution is to introduce
polymorphic locations
to the typed RPC calculus.
It is proposed by our sequel
research to the JFP paper
about a polymorphic RPC calculus.
This is joint work with James Cheney,
Simon Fowler and Sam Lindley.
In the polymorphic RPC calculus,
you can write a polymorphically
located function
with the location f traction
over location variable
and location application
as you see in the slide.
Then you have only to apply
to the client location
to get a client map function.
You can also apply to
the server location
to get a server map function.
This slide shows the comparison
among the RPC calculi
to support the slicing compilation
of the polymorphic RPC calculus
there are two approaches.
One is a study approach that is
described in the sequel paper
the other is a dynamic approach
that we are currently working on.
In this talk, I presented
theory of RPC calculi.
There are potential
application of location types
to other areas such as securities
and communication optimisation.
Also, we want to develop
a fully fledged seamless
tierless functional from
the language based on the series.
Thank you for your attention.
(APPLAUSE)
JEREMY GIBBONS: Thanks Kwanghoon.
If you are watching
the New York stream in Clowdr
you should now see a Q&A link,
where I hope you can ask
Kwanghoon question by video chat.
The next talk is
the presentation of the paper
The Full Reducing Krivine
Abstract Machine KN
simulates pure normal-order reduction
in lockstep
which adds to the framework
for environment machines
developed by Małgorzata Biernacka
and Olivier Danvy.
The authors of the paper are
Alvaro Garcia-Perez and Pablo Nogueira
And Alvaro will be presenting it.
ALVARO GARCIA-PEREZ: In this talk,
we prove properties of
an abstract machine.
In particular that the machine
defines the same strategy
than the normal other strategy
of the lambda calculus.
We prove this result by
introducing a semantic artefact
that corresponds to the machine
and it is retrofitted for
the proof of the property.
The corresponding artefact is
a reduction of strategy in a calculus
of closures.
As this quote by Cregut shows,
the importance of full reduction
is widely recognised
in the full implementation of programming
languages and (INAUDIBLE).
Full reduction refers to reducing
the term up to a normal form.
That is a term without (INAUDIBLE)
For instance, this is especially
important with nowadays
proven systems with
the (INAUDIBLE) types
which needs to reach
the normal form of a type
in order to implement
type conversion rules.
The machine we study is Cregut's
full reducing version of
the Krivine abstract machine
which we abbreviate to KN.
In a nutshell, KN takes
as input a lambda term
that it embeds in closure in
an environment that disturbs bindings
and uses a continuation of stack
and tracks the lambda nesting
level of the term being evaluated.
The machine looks up in environment
the binding of a variable
represented by a De Bruijn index
pushes the operant of
an application onto the stack
retrieves such an operant when
the operator is an abstraction
and place it as a binding
in the environment.
Reduces the body of
an applied abstraction
by pushing a special
symbol on the stack
and placing in the environment
the lambda nesting level
of the formal parameter
of the abstraction.
Calculates the De Bruijn index
of such a formal parameter
retrieved from the environment,
reduces the operant
of a normal form
which is embedded in
a special kind of closure
that disturbs (INAUDIBLE) theorems.
And finally flattens
the stack into a normal form
that is returned when all
the symbols in the stack are consumed.
KN has been proven to find
the normal form of a term
when it has some.
However the machine is
the first order transition system
that manipulates environments
and (INAUDIBLE) stacks at the low level.
And this format is not ready
to the deploy proofs by
structural induction.
Our approach is to introduce a
higher order calculus of closures
with a reduction strategy
that mimics the machine
and that is suited for deployment
proofs by structural induction.
And later to prove that the set
calculus realises the normal order
of the strategy of
the pure lambda calculus.
We arrived at such
calculus of closures
from the ones in the tradition of
Curien's calculus of closures
lambda rho.
Curien's calculus
contains proper closures
made up of a term
and an environment.
The term uses the De Bruijn
indices representation,
the environment stores closures
and the indices are used to access
the bindings in the environment
where positions in
the environment start at 0.
In the example here,
reduction starts with a closure
with empty environment.
When an application is reached
it's operant is embedded
into a closure
and prepended to
the current environment.
Then the binding at position
0 is looked up and retrieved
from the environment.
And then reduction
resumes on such bindings.
In the better rule of this calculus
the operator in an application
is reduced multiple step fashion
to a weakened normal form.
This poses some problems when
definding a reduction relation
which is purely single step.
This issue whilst
observed and fixed
in the Biernacka and Danvy's
Lambda hat Rho calculus.
This variant of Curien's
calculus considers a constructor
for closure application
that enables the reduction
relations to be lift
to the scope of the operator.
The calculus also includes
an expansion rule
that expands applications
to closure applications.
This mechanism is reminiscent
of the applied stage
in the (INAUDIBLE) evaluators
in the classical literature
in higher order
functional programming.
Now reduction expanse applications.
Reduces the operator if needed,
performs better with action
and then continues to
reduce as before.
The Biernacka and Danvy's
lambda hat rho
is enough for weak reduction.
They give account of
both call by name and call by value
weak reducing strategies
in this calculus.
However it cannot accommodate
full reducing strategies.
We remedy this by further
extending the calculus
with a constructure for
closure abstraction.
We also provide a new expansion rule
that expands abstractions
into closure abstractions.
But before presenting
this rule in detail
we discuss how to represent
the formal parameter
of the abstraction
in the environment.
In calculus, a variable is
represented by a De Bruijn index
which stands for
the relative distance
between the applied
occurance of the variable
and it's binding occurrence
in the abstracts index tree.
If the binding lambda is
immediately above the variable,
then the index is 0.
Otherwise the index gets
incremented as the distance
to its binding lambda increases.
However if we place the De Bruijn
index of the formal parameter
in a scope which is nested
under more lambdas
than it's binding occurrence,
then we have to adjust that
index by adding to it
the number of lambdas going down.
Inspired by KN, we used
instead De Bruijn level
of the formal parameter
here over lined
which stands for the absolute
lambda nesting level
of the binding lambda in
the abstract index tree.
One stands for the first lambda.
And the level increases if
the binding lambda is further down.
The advantage of
the De Bruijn levels
is that they need not be a adjusted
when placed in scopes of the term
that are nested under more lambdas.
In order to use the De Bruijn level
we first decorate our
reduction relation
with the current
lambda nesting level.
And then the expansion rule
pushes into the environment
the current level increment by one.
Since the formal parameter
has crossed the lambda.
We also add to the calculus
a construction for such levels
and we restrict the environments
to either contain proper closures
or levels since this would be
enough for the reduction strategy
that mimics KN.
When the level is retrieved
from the environment
the index corresponding
to it can be calculated
by subtracting the level from
the current lambda nesting level.
A new rule takes care
of this calculation
and embeds the calculated
index into a new construction
for absolute indices.
Absolute indices are formal parameters
of an applied abstractions
that are not relative
to any environment.
We show an example of a reduction
sequence in our calculus.
The sequence starts with
a term within the environment
and expands the application
into a closure application.
But now it also expands
the operator to a closure abstraction
before performing the beta step
which replaces the formal
parameter by the operand
then the sequel goes on as before.
We also show how reduction acts
on any applied abstraction.
The abstraction is expanded
to a closure abstraction
and later the level of
the formal parameter
is retrieved from the environment.
No reduction moves the scope to
the body of the closure abstraction
by the means of a compatibility rule
that increments the level decoration
of the reduction relation.
Combine with the rule
for index calculation
this results in the level
one of the formal parameter
being subtracted from
the current lambda nesting level.
Which is embedded as
the absolute index 0.
Notice that the input term
was already a normal form
and that reduction has only
performed administrative steps
which amount to flattening
the (INAUDIBLE) substitution in the closure
into a term.
Our main result is a one
to one correspondence
between the non-administrative
steps in our calculus
and the steps of normal
order in lambda.
This correspondence is captured
by the commuting diagram here.
On the top, C or more
administrative steps
followed by one beta step
correspond to the one
beta step on the bottom.
A substitution function sigma
mediates between the closures above
and the terms below.
The substitution function
flattens the closure
by performing only
administrative reduction.
The main technique used in
the proof of this result
is a structural induction
on the derivation (INAUDIBLE)
of reduction judgements
which has been possible
thanks to the features of
our calculus of closures.
In a previous work, we used
programme transformation techniques
to interderive KN
..and the reduction in
strategy in our calculus.
Together with this previous
work, our main result entails
that KN and normal order,
perform the same beta reduction
steps, and in the same order.
To conclude, our contribution
has been possible
thanks to the
integration techniques,
and to our judicious use
of scopes and levels
in our calculus of closures.
We have proven our result, which is
stronger than the known result,
that KN finds the normal form
of a term, if it exists.
Our contribution adds
to the increasing corpus of
knowledge of full reduction.
We conjecture that
variance of our calculus
could be used to
prove similar results
for other full reducing strategies.
In particular for the eager strategies
in the call by value family.
(APPLAUSE)
JEREMY GIBBONS: Thanks, Alvaro.
If you're watching the New
York stream in Clowdr,
you should now see a Q&A link,
where you can ask Alvaro
questions by video chat.
The next talk is
a presentation of the paper
Local Algebraic Effects Theories,
which extends the algebraic
effects and handlers approach
to track which equational theory
the effects are required to satisfy
in which sub-parts of a programme.
The authors of the paper are
Ziga Luksic and Matija Pretnar,
and Ziga will be presenting.
ZIGA LUKSIC: Hi, I'm Ziga Luksic,
and I will present joint
work with Matija Pretnar,
on local algebraic effect
theories, which was developed
to aid with reasoning in
languages with effect handlers.
In reasoning about programmes, we
often rely on certain equivalences
such as the ones stemming from
mathematical properties.
For instance, the functions f1
and f2 can be considered equal,
since x+x = 2*x.
Programme equivalents gets much harder
when we start using
computational effects.
For instance, when using print,
it's not entirely clear why they're
printing the same string twice,
is the same as printing
a double string.
We do not know whether the language
adds a new line separator
at the end of each output,
or perhaps the prints are
counted for a message log.
We must therefore know the specifics
of the language implementation.
So just imagine how much
more difficult it becomes
if effect behaviour is user defined.
This is precisely the case
in languages with
algebraic effect handlers.
In such a language, effects
are modelled by operations
which are assigned types in
the so called effect signature.
For instance, here we have
an operation Choose,
that represents a binary choice.
It accepts a unit argument
and returns a boolean value.
The operation itself is only a construct,
and its behaviour is specified
by the handler that intercepts
the operation call.
The true handler has
an effect case for Choose,
and here we have the unit
argument of the operation call,
and the programme continuation k,
which is captured at
the time of the operation call.
The effect case states that
whenever Choose is invoked,
the continuation is resumed
with the value true.
This causes every call of Choose
to simply return the value of true.
Now when using this handler,
the behaviour is crystal clear.
The code always returns one,
because Choose always returns true.
And for a slightly more
interesting example,
if we build a function choice, that
returns one of its two arguments,
where the selection is,
again done with Choose,
we can again use the handler
that always returns true.
And in that case, choice always
chooses the last argument.
So the functions f1
and f2 are equal,
since... well, they both
always return zero.
They're also equivalent
in a broader sense.
Every handler that results in
an associative implementation of choice
results in f1 being
equivalent to f2.
So another instance of
a suitable handler
is one that collects
all possible results.
And on the other hand,
if we randomly select one of
the options with a 50% chance,
that is not a suitable
implementation.
The main issue here is how
exactly to state such a property.
One way to do that is to use
equations. In the original approach,
the effect handlers, the theory
consisted of an effect signature
and equations between operations.
For instance,
associativity of choice,
which is what we wanted
in the previous example,
can easily be expressed
with an equation.
Using equations allows
us to abstract away
from concrete implementations.
We can focus on effect
implementations that satisfy
certain requirements that are
set by the equational theory.
The original approach assumes
a single global effect theory,
but this turned out to
be very restricting.
There are many useful handlers
that work with entirely
different theories, and
by fixing the global theory,
we are unable to solve them.
This is where our work comes in.
We transition to local theories
by packing equations into
computation types instead.
A computation type now state
the type of return values,
the names and types of
operations that may be called,
and the equational theory.
Of this type, all computations
are considered equivalent,
modulo the equations ε.
Let's take a look at
a small example.
In this signature, we
define operation signal
that accepts a unit
and returns a unit.
It truly does nothing
more than just signal
to the handler that it was called.
And in the effect theory we
can be a bit more expressive.
The equation states that
if we signal twice,
and then proceed with
an arbitrary computation, that
it's no different than
if we signal only once
and then continue with that.
Now an example of a handler
that fits the equation
is one that returns true as
soon as a signal occurs,
and false if the computation is
evaluated without a single signal.
And an example of handler that
does not respect the equation
would be a handler that instead
returns the number of
signals received.
We can now use this equation
to restrict possible
effect implementations.
Here we have two
functions f1 and f2,
and f1 has no equations, while
f2 uses the above equation.
This means that f1 can be handled
by any handler for signal,
while f2 requires
the handler to now differentiate
between one and many signals.
We can of course use such handlers
for f1 as well, but not vice versa.
This already shows the difference
between global and local theories,
since in the global
setting, we either require
all handlers to respect
the equation, or none of them.
In the first case, we can't use
such a wide variety of handlers
for handling f1,
and in the second case,
we can't use the equation as
a reasoning tool in the body of the f2.
And when implementing effective
behaviour with handlers,
we of course need to be mindful of
the fact theory that
we're working in.
Handler type informs us about
the kind of computations
that the handler is used for,
and what the resulting
computation type is.
Since two computation
types are involved,
equations occur in two spots.
The ε on the left sets
the requirements for the implementation,
and ε′ on the right states
the theory of the (INAUDIBLE)
We have to check that
for every equation in ε,
if we handle both sides, we end
up with equivalent computations.
The equivalence is considered
in the theory of ε′,
so we may be aided by
the equations that are acting ε′.
Handler correctness is undecidable.
So the proofs are
constructed in a logic
that is coupled with
the type system.
Using equations comes with extra
work when typing handlers,
but provides a strong
tool for reasoning
and it's a very natural
fit for algebraic effects.
Local effect theories impose less
restrictions than global ones
and we consider them an all around
improvement over global theories.
Equations are vital for
reasoning about effect behaviour.
And the type system can also be
coupled with different kinds of logic.
So we can use a system that
fits the problem at hand.
Or if we use local effect theories,
the changes to the language
are rather minor,
and the resulting system
is also easy to use.
We do not need to switch to
denotational semantics,
or to a full-fledged
dependently type checking.
The drawback is clearly the need for
user input when typing handlers,
but handler definitions are
the only point where this is required,
so most of the work
is still automated.
Since the paper was published,
we have done some
considerable advancements.
We have extended
the language with recursion
and some basic data types,
products or lists.
We also included the non-trivial
extension of subtyping,
which greatly improves
the usefulness of the language.
All of this has been formalised
in the Coq proof assistant,
alongside some smaller examples.
And we also constructed a
sound and eloquent
denotational semantics,
which takes into account all
the formation (INAUDIBLE).
The approach was also implemented
on top of the f framework.
We decided to use
a bi-directional type inference
as it's more suited for
working with effect theories.
But the system does not
automate correctness proofs,
which are left to the user.
The proofs can be done
by pen and paper,
or they can also be constructed
in the Coq formalisation
of the language.
We also considered
a few future goals.
The important extension that has
not yet been done is polymorphism.
We wish to have times that are
polymorphic in the value component,
as well as polymorphic in
the signature and equations.
The extension could
be far from trivial
but it's ultimately important
if you want the language,
it can be used in practice.
Another key aspect that we're
not yet entirely satisfied with,
is proving handler correctness.
Automation would be great,
but even just easing the burden
by providing better tools for user
proofs would be a great start.
Perhaps also very important is
finding good use cases for
local effect theories.
We feel that we are now at the point
where future work should
be guided by shortcomings
when trying to apply it
to actual problems.
Anyone interested is
welcome to read our paper,
and thank you for your time.
(APPLAUSE)
JEREMY: Thanks, Ziga.
If you're watching the New
York stream in Clowdr,
you should now see a Q&A link,
where you can get
questions by video chat.
The next talk is a presentation
of the functional pearl,
heterogeneous binary
random-access lists.
Which you can use for example,
to implement efficient
typed environments for
a well typed interpreter.
The paper's by Wouter Swierstra.
WOUTER SWIERSTRA: Thank you
for that introduction, Jeremy.
So my name is Wouter Swierstra,
and I'm here to say a little bit about
the functional pearl that
I published in JFP last year.
So let's start by
talking about lists.
So lists are one of
the very first data types
that we teach our
undergrad students.
And they're a great vehicle
for explaining concepts
such as higher order function
with maps and folds,
recursion, or polymorphism.
But as our students mature,
they typically take one
of two career paths
if they're interested in
functional programming.
On the one hand, if they
choose to go into industry,
they quickly realise that
if they need to store
any serious amount of data, you
need better data structures,
such as finite maps or some
form of balanced binary tree.
Other students might pursue
a career in academia.
And in that case, they
spend their time writing
intrinsically typed evaluators
for a lambda calculi,
or any kind of fancy
thing like that,
which requires a list, where
the values stored in the list
might actually have different types.
And to do this in
a typesafe fashion,
you typically use something called
a heterogeneous list or a H list.
So this paper asked the question,
can we have our cake and eat it?
Can we define a data structure
that's both heterogeneous
and efficient?
And this isn't just
a theoretical probe.
So people who work in
industry and academia,
such as David Christian, who
has co-authored (INAUDIBLE),
they wrote an experience report
on Dependently Typed Haskell
in Industry last year,
that they have this experience of
profiling crucible that showed
that linear axis imposed an unacceptable
overhead on the simulator.
As a result, they actually
abandoned the typesafe
dependently typed approach
that they were taking,
in favour of data dot map
and an unsafe course.
So what's in the paper? So
I show how to implement
an heterogeneous binary
random access list and act.
And this has the same API as just
regular heterogeneous list.
So there's an empty structure, nil,
and there's an operation
to add new elements
to the front of the list
and operation to access elements
within those two lookup,
or a bang, bang.
And all of these operations
are both total and typesafe.
And furthermore, there are no
coercions or lemmas necessary
for everything to type check. It's
intrinsically typed by design.
So in this talk, I won't try
to cover the whole paper.
But instead, I'll just focus
on the homogeneous case,
where we have binary
random access list
originally proposed
by Chris Okasaki,
in his book on purely
functional data structures,
and show how to
implement that in Agda,
in a kind of total and typesafe way.
And then the heterogeneous version
follows quite naturally from this.
So if we need better than
linear access times,
we need to shift from
lists to trees.
And for the moment, let's
just make the assumption
that we only ever have to store
two to the power of n elements.
And that's very easy to do
because we can store two to
the power of n elements
in a perfectly balanced
binary tree of depth n.
So here are a few examples of
perfectly balanced binary trees,
where I'm going to draw black dots
for the leaf storing data,
and white dots for
the nodes which store no data.
If I want to write this in Agda,
I can define a little
datatype for my trees
indexed by natural number corresponding
to the depth of the tree.
So I can have a leaf which
stores an element of type a
and has depth zero,
or I can have a node which has
two sub trees of equal length,
and then return to tree
which is one deeper.
Now if I want to kind of denote any
particular value in such a tree,
I typically use a path
through that tree.
The data type path here is just
isomorphic to a vector of (INAUDIBLE)
but it's nice to have
this separate data type.
The idea is that this path
tells me for every node
whether I should go left or right.
And then I can define
a lookup operation
which just follows that
path with the tree.
going to the left subtree
if the path starts with
the left constructor
and the right subtree if it starts
with the right constructor.
At the end of the path I know
that I've hit a leaf and turn
the value stored there.
The important thing to notice here
is that the type in the C ensure
that the depth of the tree
and the length of the path coincide.
So I can always return
the value of type (INAUDIBLE)
Now if I only have to store
2 to the power of n elements
this would be the end of the talk.
But you'd be very
right to complain that
I can't just assume that
everything is a power of 2.
But there is one
observation I can make
which is that any number
can be written as a sum
of powers of two using it's
binary representation.
And that's the key idea behind
this binary random access list.
So binary random
access list consists
of the list of perfectly
balanced binary trees
of increasing depths.
And the ith position in this list
there may or there may not be
a perfect binary tree of depth i.
So let's look at some examples.
So if I need to store three elements
in a binary random access list.
I can do this with a leaf followed
by a binary tree of depth one.
If I need four elements,
I omit the first two tree
but I have a tree of depth two.
If I need five elements
I have a leaf,
I have no tree in position two
and I have a tree of depth two in
the second position in the list.
I guess if you are familiar
with binary numbers
you can see how this one works.
So the numbers
representation in binary
determines the shape of
the binary random access list
storing that many elements.
So it'll need some binary numbers.
Let's right that anecdote.
So we can have a simple
type for binary numbers,
0s and 1s are the end of the binary.
We can define a successful operation
which increments the binary number.
The important thing here is that
we have the least significant bit
at the beginning of
the binary number.
So if we see a 0
we can flip it to one,
if we see a one we flip
it to a 0 of course.
So now we can finally define
our random access list.
There are three type arguments
that you can see here.
The type A corresponding
to the type of the values
stored in the random access list.
The number N which is
the depth of the list
as we are going down
and a binary number
which kind of represents
the shape of the list
of the random access list
but it also kind of counts
the number of elements in this list.
So there are three constructors.
So nil is the end of the list
and the kind of, corresponds
the empty binary word.
If we are kind of using a one
if the binary number
starts with a one
we have a tree of depth n and a tail
which kind of, it has
a shape of kind of binary
of the remainder of
the tail of the binary word.
And if the binary word
starts with a zero
then we have no tree
but we have kind of a tail
of the random access list
that we might still have.
So the binary number, counts
the number of elements
and determines the shape of
our random access list.
And one thing which you can see here
is that the number n grows
as we go down the list.
And this is not what you
might be familiar with
if you reduce
the things like vectors
or the vector, a little
number kind of counts down
to the end of the list.
Here n counts up as
we go down the list
because they are kind of
increasingly deeper trees
as we go down the list.
And typically we consider
random access lists
starting with the n zero
but it's good to be a little
bit more general sometimes.
So now we can define
a data for positions
in a look up function.
And these positions they are
kind of take a natural number
in a binary number.
And these positions kind of
they essentially combine the usual
kind of linear position in a list
and the path in a tree.
So if we know that the binary number
corresponds to the shape
of their own access list
that we are accessing,
starts with a one,
then we can choose to have
a path of length n in the tree
at the head of the list.
That's what the here
constructor does.
The other two constructors there,
they basically jump
over any kind of tree
which may or may not be there
and the kind of out most
list in the structure
until we find the tree
that we are looking for
and then we have the path
in that tree to one of
the individual elements.
And then we can define
a look up
function in kind of
quite a straightforward now.
If we want to add new
elements to this,
this is a little bit tricky.
The first thing you might try
would be to define a cons function
which takes an A,
which takes a random access list
starting with depth zero
and then produces
a new random access list
where we have one more element.
So we kind of implemented
the number of elements
which is represented by
the binary number B.
But if we try this we
get stuck quite quickly.
As we kind of need to
make a recursive call,
the tail of the binary random
access list actually list
actually has larger access tree in
which we are trying to add an A
which kind of no longer
lines up some how.
So the solution is to define kind
of a more general operation,
a cons tree operations
which adds a tree of depths
and to a random access list
starting with n and then increments
the number of elements stored.
And then we have the degenerate case
where n equals 0 then it
corresponds to the cons operation
that we have there.
If you want to know a little bit more
about, the details are in the paper
but the cons tree
operation closely mimics
the kind of successful
operations on binary numbers.
So to wrap up a little bit,
we can extend this to
the heterogenous case
by writing a heterogeneous
binary random access list
index by a random access list
which stores some type information
first time universe u.
And despite like
the apparent complexity,
there is an example in the paper
where I write an efficient
lambda calculus evaluator
using heterogeneous binary
random access lists.
And this turns out to be
no harder than just using
kind of heterogeneous list
that you would use in the situation.
Furthermore it's fairly easy
to port this code to Haskell.
It turns out that you only
need about 130 lines
to define the data
structure of the nill,
the cons and the look up operations
of which I should point
out that maybe ten percent
is language extension pragmas
but there is nothing too
fancy going on there.
So in conclusion if you can
choose the right data structure,
one very nice things about
these binary random access list
is that there is no
rotation involved.
Everything kind of
stays in the same order
regardless of when we add things
that kind of stays well formed.
And if we choose our type
indices in such a way
that we can enforce the key variance
that we are interested in
this ensures that all of our definitions
can go through quite cleanly
and we really can have
our cake and eat it.
(APPLAUSE)
JEREMY: Thanks, Wouter.
If you are watching the New
York streaming Clowdr,
you should now see a Q&A link
where you can ask Walter
questions by video chat.
The next talk is
the presentation of the paper
POPLMark reloaded; Mechanising
proofs by logical relations
which presents a new collection
of benchmark problems
in mechanising the matters area
of programming languages.
The authors of
the papers are Andres Abel,
Gias Allais, Alia Hameer, Brigitte
Pientka, Alberto Moenigliano
Steven Schafer and Kathrine Stark.
And Brigitte will be presenting.
BRIGITTE PIENTKA: Hello
and welcome, thanks for coming.
This talk is going to summarise
our POPLMark reloaded
mechanising proofs by
logical relations.
My name is Brigitte Pientka
and this is joined work by
Andreas Andreas Abel, G. Allais,
Alia Hameer, Alberto Moenigiliano,
Steven Schafer and Katherine Stark.
So today mechanisation are common
place in programming languages.
However they are also time consuming
and there are few design guidelines.
So what's the problem?
The problem is that proofs
are tricky to write.
Both on paper as well as
in proof assistancts.
There are a lot of challenging
details to keep track of.
On paper it's hard to keep
track of dependencies
among different theorems
and the definitions
and you might think that proof
is in a sense are the answer.
But in proof assistants there
is sort of another overhead
we have to deal with.
We have to build up the infrastructure
for modelling for example
bindings and context and so on.
So there is quite
a lot of time that gets
into the building this
particular infrastructure.
It's often hard to understand
how different features interact,
difficulties increase with
the size of the mechanisation
and it can be really
quite time consuming.
It's through this that often
a whole team of students
is actually tacking some of
this mechanisation efforts.
Now experience very much matters.
Now the goal of this paper was
to develop a benchmark problem
that would allow us to gain a deeper
understanding of the similarities
and differences in how we mechanise
problems in programming languages
Now we as developers of proof
assistance and libraries
wanted to make our
approaches more robust
and identify parameters
and abstractions
to better structure
proofs and bring down
the cost of verification overall.
So it's worthwhile to take
a look back at POPLMark in 2005.
Back in 2005 POPLMark challenge
was to mechanise system FSAP
And that is a problem that can
be fairly easily understood.
It's described in types of
programming languages,
it can be mechanised in
a couple of hours.
It focuses really on
representing and reasoning
about structures with binders
in particular RV model
of the polymorphic functions base.
All proofs for syntactic
structural induction.
And it was a great way of
exploring different encoding
techniques for
representing bindings.
In fact people used strings,
De Bruijn, nominal encodings,
(INAUDIBLE) as well
as high (INAUDIBLE)
But on the flip side it did not
really identify any bugs or flaws
in existing sytems.
It did not inspire the development
of new theoretical foundations
nor did it push any existing
systems to their limit.
All systems were in some
sense, equally suitable.
So we want to go beyond
the POPLMark challenge.
And in fact one doesn't
need to go very far,
one just needs to look in
the conclusion of this paper
and one sees that
one of the problems
one challenges in (INAUDIBLE)
is Proof by Logical Relations.
So our contribution here in this
paper is to describe a tutorial
for a stronger normalisation
proofs for a valid type terms
using Kripke-style
logical relations.
The really few standard
textbook chapters out there
that focus on strong
normalisation proofs.
And although it has been really
a good standard in some sense
to evaluate proof assistance
using a strong normalisation proof
by logical operations.
See for example there is
Altenkirch work in 1993
where he used lego to
give mechanisation
of a strong normalisation proof
for (INAUDIBLE) calculus.
Now one difference between
all this work and ours is that
we are really focusing on
well-typed term represantations
and that leads us to
a Kripke-style of logical relation
where we talk about extentions
of typing context.
And this also brings
me to the challenges
which really go beyond
the original POPLMark challenge
because we need to model
the simultaneous substitutions
and renamings, context extensions,
obstruction properties
such as weakening and extension
strengthening play much more,
central role and in order to
describe the reducibility definition
we need to have a way
of distinguishing
between inductive
and stratified definitions.
And last we implemented
our solutions
in three different proof assistance.
Beluga, Coq and Agda.
Now I also want to mention
some considerations
that went into choosing this
particular bench marks
because there are of course
many different kinds
of logic relations proofs
and Kripke-style logical relational proof.
In particular, there have been
very proper for reasoning
about concurrent
and imperative programmes
where we reasoned about
memory extension
rather than typing
context extensions.
Nevertheless we focus here
on logical relations proofs
for typed terms.
(INAUDIBLE) no state.
But we believe that this
is a good spring board
for richer theories in particular
dependent type theories.
One problem in particular
that often comes up
when you think about
dependant theories is
the notion of equality.
And we need to sort of reason
about some as in completeness
of algorithmic type
directed equality.
And the proof of soundness completeness
of typed directed equality
exhibits many of the same
ideas and challenges
that we have in the proof
of strong analyzations
towards simple lambda calculus.
And last our guiding principle
was really to design a benchmark
that is reasonable so grad
students would be able to do it
after reading the tutorial.
So how do we define
strong normalisation.
So traditionally, we define it by
saying M is strongly normalising
if all rewrite sequences starting
in M end in a normal form.
And this often characterised using
what is called
an accessibility relation.
But in fact the proof become
increasingly annoying
when we need to reason about all
these different rewrite sequences
and analyse different reducts.
So the alternative was
proposed by a F van Raamsdonk
and Paula Severi going
back also (IANUDIBLE)
this kind of modular approach
for strongly normalising
where we have inductive
characterisations in normal forms.
And this leads to modular proofs
both on paper
and mechanisations and the proofs
essentially becomes much similar.
So the first child problem
is to prove the equivalence
between the accessibility relation
and inductive definition
of strong normalising terms.
And the second one is actually
proving strong normalisation
for simply typed lambda calculus
using the inductive definition.
And that will have
certain set problems
that will also be
described in the paper
and outlined the proofs.
So in the remaining few minutes
I want to talk about our solutions
of one Beluga which is this
contextual High order of syntax
and then Adga and Coq where we
use the De Bruijn codings.
So Beluga is probably
the youngest system
on this three proof assistance.
The proof tiered syntax based on
the logic of (INAUDIBLE)
and therefore is of course
great to model by instructors.
Beluga also has build in
support for substitutions
and renamings and in that sense
it's kind of ideally suited
for that particular problem.
But it was also a great case
study for finding bugs
and making the system more robust.
In particular it allowed us to
find bugs in coverage checking
and in extend termination checking.
In over the last year,
we also implemented
an interactive proof
development mode Harpoon
to make it easier to develop
such proofs in general.
But there is no proof automation.
Now Coq on the other hand we used
de Bruijn encodings
for modelling findings.
We have in fact two solutions
developed by Katherine
Stark and Stephen Schafer.
The first one was on
well-scoped syntax
and the boilerplate was
generated by Autosubst 2.
And the second solution focus on
well-typed de Bruijn encodings
and the boilerplate sort
of proven manually.
Both proofs were a sort
of very much developed
and close collaboration with
our proofs and Beluga.
So they have a very
similar structure.
So everything can be
proven as expected.
It's very worthwhile nothing that
substitutions and beginnings
are functions mapping
from positions to terms
or positions to other positions.
And repetitive proofs
are kind of factored out
using proofs, scripts
and Coq tactics.
It also led to a way of
maybe rethinking Autosubst.
Maybe one should have an Autosubst 3
where we actually can
generate boilerplate codes
for valid types
and tax automatically.
And last Agda, we used to
generate syntax library
from (INAUDIBLE)
It worked very well as
an expert user to test
and stress test his
library,
it led for example
to implementing additional
generic results
as part of the generic-syntax
library because they were missing.
And the abstractions
provided by the library
led to very compact proofs.
Now, the theory of
renaming and substitution
is however not internalised
and there is no automation.
So overall, I think all of us
felt it was a success.
These benchmarks did expose
bugs and shortcomings
in existing systems.
It made libraries
and systems more robust.
It helped us restructure
our approves,
and it helped us to gain a deeper
understanding of each approach
and how they're actually related.
So benchmarks can be great.
We would encourage
you to explore them.
Hopefully we'll see
a solution from you.
We already saw a solution developed
in F star, which is wonderful.
But we also hope that some of
the considerations and discussions
that led to the choice of
our benchmark problem
helps you to formulate
other challenge problems.
Of course, this isn't the end.
So thanks for listening.
(APPLAUSE)
JEREMY: Thanks Brigitte.
If you're watching the
New York streaming Clowdr,
you should not see a Q&A link
where you can ask Brigitte
questions by video chat.
The next talk is
a presentation of the paper,
perturbation confusion in forward
automatic differentiation
of higher-order functions,
which describes a longstanding bug
and the implementations of these
and two potential solutions.
The authors of the paper are
Oleksandr Manzyuk, Barak Pearlmutter,
Alexey Radul, David Rush,
and Jeﬀrey Mark Siskind.
And Barak will be presenting.
BARAK PEARLMUTTER: My name
is Barak Pearlmutter,
and I'd like to tell you about
a bug that we encountered
in allowing derivatives of
higher-order functions.
This work is part of
a sustained effort
to make automatic differentiation
robust, performance general,
and ultimately ubiquitous,
and of course, correct.
It should be easy to
take a derivative
as it is to take a square
root or write a loop.
That means programmemers should
be able to take derivatives
of anything who's
derivative make sense.
So derivatives of functions,
which themselves take
or return functions,
like solving an ODE
or the derivative of map.
And of course, we want to take
derivatives of functions
which internally take derivatives.
So we want to allow nesting.
Let me set up what we need
to explore this issue.
I'll review our notation
and terminology
for forward automatic
differentiation.
Although the same issue
crops up in all other modes,
we'll use forward for clarity.
Then I'll talk about classic
perturbation confusion
and how it's avoided using tags.
We'll think about derivatives
of higher-order functions
and see how allowing them breaks
the one-to-one correspondence
between invoking derivative
operators and taking derivatives,
thus allowing this bug.
After that's all unpacked,
look at ways to address the problem.
In forward automatic
differentiation,
derivatives are piggybacked
on primal values.
So we have x plus x prime epsilon,
x is the primal, x prime is
the derivative value called a tangent.
This is like a dual number,
like a complex number inside the computer,
it's represented as
a two element pair.
These are propagated according
to the rules of calculus,
and we have an operator for
extracting the epsilon coefficient,
the tangent of an output.
I'll show how his is used to perform
forward automatic differentiation
on a simple but topical function.
Let's say f of t is one over one
plus e to the minus t.
We define the operator D to take
the derivative of f at a point x
by fiting x plus epsilon into f
extracting the tangent of the output.
We can take f of two
to get 0.881,
and take the derivative of f at two,
take f of two plus epsilon,
crank that through,
we get 0.881 plus 0.105 epsilon.
We extract the tangent to
get the derivative of 0.105.
This function is also the solution
to Verhulst epidemic equation.
The derivative is
the rate of infection.
So did you really think you could
go whole talk without Coronavirus?
It used to be that
nesting was initial idea,
but many applications
demand nesting.
When done in frameworks
that don't support it
programmeers end up going through
all kinds of crazy hoops
to get nesting working.
Said scripts depatch source code
between multiple passes
through preprocessors,
manual closure conversion,
all kinds of heroic technical
debt creating shenanigans.
We want it to be natural.
Here's some simple nesting.
D takes a derivative at a point.
On the left here is conventional
mathematical notation
for nesting derivative.
Notice how much nicer the functional
notation on the right is.
Regular calculus is better
with lambda calculus, right?
Look at the definition of D.
Now there's this fresh thing
that there wasn't before.
That means we get a fresh
epsilon every time we invoke D.
So that nested invocations
have different epsilon tags.
And so their tangents don't collide.
That's critical to
getting the right answer.
When I say epsilon i
or a different tag,
these might be implemented
in lots of different ways,
like by nested structures with
existential types for safety
or a variety of other techniques.
We're abstracting all that away
and just saying tag, different
epsilon tags, different indices.
Recent formulations often
still get this wrong.
For some of them it's out of scope,
you can't even express nesting.
For others they crash,
you get the wrong answer.
The phrase higher-order
automatic differentiation
is used in a bunch of different
senses in the literature.
When we use it here
we mean the hard one.
This first definition, taking
derivatives of higher-order functions,
not plain or higher-order
derivatives,
and not derivatives of
first order functions
defined using
higher-order operators.
What is meant by the derivative
of a higher-order function?
Well, in part there
was the motivation
for the development of the whole
field of differential geometry
100s of years ago.
But let's give a simple example
of binary curried function.
So f of xy equals x squared
plus blah, blah, blah.
We can take F at the 0.5
and get a function from y,
225 plus yq, blah, blah, blah.
We take the derivative of f at five,
and we'll get
the partial derivative of f
with respect to its first argument.
So map from y to the derivative
of that expression,
with respect to x at
the point x equals five and y.
I'm ignoring derivatives of function
whose domain is a function.
Read the paper for that.
In order for this to go through,
we're going to have to extend
the derivative operator.
Well, not the derivative
operator itself
whose definition remains
the same, but it's type.
And also we have to extend
the tangent operator.
The tangent operator operates
on numbers the same way,
but on functions by
post-composition.
OK. Now we're in a position to
do something very disturbing
or quite amazing,
depending on whether you like to
build large correct artefacts
or enjoy watching slow
motion train wrecks.
So I'm going to define
an offset operator s,
it takes an offset u
and a function f
and returns f offset by u.
And I'm going to define D hat
to be the derivative of s
at the point zero.
If we look at D of f at x,
we expand things out, turn the crank,
and we get f prime of x.
Similarly, if we take
D hat of f at x,
we expand out the definition
of D hat, turn the crank,
and we get f prime of x.
So we should have D hat equals D.
But if we use them in
a nested fashion,
D is operating correctly
on a scalar function h
takes a second derivative,
but D hat gives us
a constant function zero
when used in this nested fashion.
What happened?
Well, the fresh triggered
when D was invoked,
the thing is Ds of
zero returned a value
which has a single tag in it,
a single concrete tag.
So when it's nested,
we can get a collision.
That's really bad.
OK, I'll unpack.
That's the dirty laundry of higher-order
automatic differentiation.
Now, let's get to
the bottom of this mess.
What's the root cause?
Note D was invoked once in
the definition of D hat,
but we can still get
nested derivatives.
And that's cause derivatives
of higher-order functions
breaks the one-to-one relationship
between invoking a derivative
operator and taking a derivative.
It's like those corny jokes
about engineers and accountants
travelling with fewer tickets
then people are hiding in the loo
and the conductor comes
to check tickets.
There's a disconnect between allocating
the tags and using the tags.
And we have poor enforcement of
the one tag per nested derivative
calculation policy.
The key issue is, that we need
to distinguish the tangents,
the tags for different derivatives,
even though the different derivative
operator is called only once.
If we don't, we get
perturbation confusion.
Here's an idea for a workaround.
We would have gotten
the correct result
if D hat had been left un-reduced.
So, instead of writing that
expression at the bottom
where we use D hat twice,
we could define D hat twice
and use the two different definitions.
That would be OK,
except it's manual and horrible.
We want programmeists to just take
derivatives and get the right answer
and not have to worry about
what's under the hood.
So here's an idea for accomplishing
this more transparently.
We could use eta expansion.
We would delay the fresh
until all the arguments needed
for post-composition of tangent
are available.
So immediately beta reduces to
a non-function containing value.
So we'd have separate versions of D,
for scalar functions,
binary curried functions, etc.
This could also be accomplished
using polymorphic recursion.
Although that gets hairy when
the underlying language
gets more complicated.
Here's another idea.
What's going wrong is that
the value passed into the function
whose tangent is being taken,
might have the same tag that's
in play in that function.
So we could augment it with a rapper
to guard the tag in the function
so that if it occurs externally,
the external one gets renamed
away and then renamed back
after being passed through.
OK, take home message.
We can import
the standard definitions
of derivatives of
higher-order functions
into automatic differentiation,
but allowing them breaks
the automatic differentiation machinery.
Now, it might be a stretch to
call this the amazing bug.
It's a pretty crowded field,
but I hope you'll agree
that it's an amazing bug.
We have some ideas for solving this.
And I propose two
solution frameworks.
One is based on eta expansion,
and the other is on renaming tags away
and then renaming them back
when they're passing through
the tangents of closures.
Recent formulations of forward
of automatic differentiation
still often get this wrong.
For some it's out of scope,
others get the wrong answer.
The two solutions that I proposed,
they solve the correctness issue
but they do have some issues
with complexity.
So we would like to
work on this some more
to get the efficiency right,
those constant factor efficiency,
and these solutions
implemented naively at least
would seem to break some of
the complexity guarantees
that we'd like to make
an automatic differentiation.
Thank you for listening.
I hope this story has
been of interest.
And I'd like to thank the organisers
for arranging this
fantastic virtual gathering
under very difficult circumstances.
I'd be happy to answer
any questions.
(APPLAUSE)
JEREMY: Thanks Barak.
If you're watching the
New York streaming Clowdr,
you can now see a Q&A link
where you can ask Barak
and Jeffrey questions by video chat.
The next talk is
a presentation in the paper
elastic sheet defined functions,
generalising spreadsheet functions
to variable size input arrays,
which is about helping end users
spreadsheet programmemers
to write more flexible functions
that work over inputs
of arbitrary size.
The authors of the paper are
Matt McCutchen, Judith Borghouts,
Andy Gordon, Simon Peyton Jones
and Advait Sarkar.
And Matt will be presenting.
MATT MCCUTCHEN:
Hi, I'm Matt McCutchen
and I'm going to talk
about a method of
automatically generalising
spreadsheet functions
through variable-size input arrays,
which we've nicknamed elastic
sheet-defined functions.
The spreadsheet is by far
the most widely used
functional programming environment
because it's so easy to use
even for people unfamiliar with
conventional programming.
For instance, suppose we're
shopping for a set of foods
and the prices are
given without tax.
We want to compute the total amount
we'll pay including the tax.
We just type our starting
data into the cells
and enter the formulas we want
to calculate into other cells.
If it's too mind-bending
to calculate the tax
on all the foods at once,
we can do it for the apple
and then copy the formula.
We have to be a little careful with
relative and absolute referencing
but if we make a mistake,
it's easy to spot and fix.
We can work one step at a time
and always see all the data at once.
So for a simple problem like this
we never have to think very hard.
Now suppose we want to total
a lot of shopping lists.
Of course, rather than make many
independent copies of the formulas,
we'd like to reuse them so that
if we have to fix the bug
in the original formulas,
the fix takes effect on
all the shopping lists.
Since we're familiar with calling
built in functions like sum,
can we define our own function
for the shopping list
that we could call?
In current mainstream
spreadsheet tools we can,
but we have to rewrite the logic in
a separate programming language
such as visual basic,
which sacrifices all the usability
advantages of spreadsheets.
Fortunately, there's
an easier approach
that has appeared in
many research systems.
And we think it's only a matter of
time before it becomes mainstream,
the sheet defined function or SDF.
To make our original
formulas into an SDF,
we just mark
the cells that represent
the inputs and output of
the function and give it a name.
Now we can call shop
on the second list,
just like a built in function.
Semantically, the tool makes
a temporary copy of the function body
with our new input substituted in
and returns to new output.
But of course the tool can
optimise this process.
The user can open the temporary
sheet to see what happened.
This requires users to
think a little harder,
but we think many of them will
be comfortable defining SDFs
and the rest will at least be
comfortable calling them.
However, we quickly
run into a problem
if we call shop on a shopping list
of a different length
than the original,
when we try to put the pretax
prices in the input range
they'll get cut off
and we'll get the wrong answer.
The result we like is
if the body of shop
are resized to fit the input,
how can we make shop
behave this way?
One approach is to let
the entire array of prices
be stored in a single cell.
If we apply an operator
like plus to two arrays,
we're implicitly adding
the corresponding elements.
This will work regardless of
the sizes of the arrays.
This is a little more
for users to learn,
but it's a plausible
solution for shop.
However, for more complex SDFs,
the array programming approach
becomes unmanageable.
Here's the sheet containing
the transaction history
for a bank account with
interest compounded daily.
To compute the balance
after a transaction,
first we apply the interest
of the previous balance
based on the number of days
since the previous transaction,
then we add the amount of
the current transaction.
This example presents
two new problems
for the array programming approach.
To line up the previous dates
with the current dates,
we need to shift the array
in A4 down one element
and add A3 at the top.
Let's assume that a spreadsheet tool
designed for array programming
will have a shift down
function to do that.
But for the reference to
the previous balance,
if we tried to do the same thing,
we'd ended up with the whole
array in C4 depending on itself
which won't work.
To handle the iteration,
we need to use this special
function called VSCAN2
and pass the lambda function
that computes each element
from the previous one.
Most users won't be able
to come up with this
unless they find an example on
the web that's similar enough
that they can adapt
to their problem.
If that isn't bad enough,
here's another SDF
with a naive model
of cascading delays in
the bus transit system.
The idea is that
a departure from a station
will be delayed if
the bus that was supposed
to make the trip hasn't arrived yet.
We want this SDF to re
size in three different
ways, the of time
steps in the simulation
and the vertical direction,
and the numbers of stations
and routes both in
the horizontal direction,
this mutual recursion
among four of the arrays.
While we think this
is possible to write
using array programming
it's going to be such a mess
that I won't even try.
So it seems we really do want
to resize an SDF at the cell level,
effectively generalising
it to handle input
of variable size,
we call the result in elastic SDF.
Maybe the user can somehow
specify how
the resizing should work.
But it turns out that for many SPF's
including all three
we've seen so far,
the user doesn't need to do anything
because we can figure out
the resizing automatically.
That's the topic of our paper.
Let's see how
the generalisation process works
in the simplest shop example
for the purpose of
describing our work,
we use a textual
notation for SDF's.
Users don't need to know anything
about this notation
though we have evidence that
some users may find it helpful.
Here we have the function name
and the input and output ranges.
Each line of the body
describes the rectangular tile
of one or more cells with
the copied formula.
For example, the first line
describes these three cells,
the given formula is placed
in the top left cell
and copied to the others
with the usual adjustment
of relative references.
We can now write the elastic SDF
that we want in this notation
by introducing a length
variable alpha,
that can take any non
negative integer value.
Of course, if we set off in three
we get the original shot back,
we'll call this elastic SDF shop
one for reference in this talk,
Though the user would invoke it
using the original name shop.
When an elastic SDF is called,
We set the length variables
to match the argument sizes
in this case setting off with a six
and substitute them
into the definition
giving an ordinary SDF that
we can evaluate as before.
Now if the tiles may
colllide when they expand,
we address this by
labelling each reference
with the tile or tiles that
originally pointed to
and having it read only
from those tiles,
even if others overlap them.
Here the reference, in the sum
reached the age seven of tile four,
while the output reference reached
the age seven and tile five.
We do this for all SDF's but
to reduce clutter we won't show
the labels for the rest of the talk.
The question immediately comes up
Is the best generalisation of
the given SDF always clear?
for one thing we want
a generalisation that's well defined,
meaning that its
references stay in bounds
for all values of length variables.
For example, if we set the height
of the column H tile to alpha,
but the height of
the column G tile the three.
Then when alpha increases the H tile
will be referring to undefined
cells below the G tile
so this generalisation
is not well defined.
From now on we'll consider only
well defined generalisations.
To illustrate the next point
consider this contrived sum two SPF
that sums two arrays
and adds the totals.
Here are two well
defined generalisations
sum 2 D allows the arrays to be
different lengths alpha and beta,
while some to S requires them
to be the same length alpha.
We say that sum two D is more
general than a sum two S
since it can be
converted to sum two S
by substituting for
the length variables,
we prefer sum two D to make sure
we generalise as many
degrees of freedom
in the original SDF as possible.
So given an SDF like shop.
If there's a well
defined generalisation
that is more general
than all the others,
which we call principle.
That's the one we want.
Unfortunately there
are several problems
that can cause them to be no
principle generalisation,
we'll look at one of them.
In addition to shop one
that we saw earlier shop
has two other contrived,
but well defined generalisations
one that uses only
the first three items
of the input and one
is the last three.
None of these generalisations
can be converted
to any of the others by
substituting for alpha.
And since they can all give
different answers on the same input,
it should be intuitively clear
there isn't a principle
generalisation
that's more general than all three.
The user probably want shop one,
But we have to
formalise that somehow.
So we introduced the concept
of irregular generalisation
which satisfies several conditions
on top as well defined S,
one of which is that
a cell reference
can pick three elements
out of a larger tile,
so sharp one is regular
and the other two
generalisations are not.
Now out of all the well
defined generalisations
of an SDF, if we keep only
the regular generalisations,
we can prove that there's
always a principle
regular generalisation.
And that's the elastic SDF we use.
This can be seen as the analogue
of the principal type of terminal
functional programming language
or algorithm defined the principle
regular generalisation
introduces all the variables
that could possibly need
generate constraints on them
based on the definition
of regularity.
And then solves the constraints.
For example, because of
the relative reference
between the files in
columns G and H,
we generate a constraint that
the heights of those tiles are equal.
Again this is analogous to
the type inference algorithm
in a functional
programming language.
We've seen that in order to have
a principle generalisation
we needed to introduce
a concept of regularity
that excludes some well
defined generalisations.
We try to make
and capture user intent,
which inevitably involves
judgement calls or goals,
aside from having a principle
of regular generalisation,
or to support as many realistic
STF design patterns as we can,
and keep the process
predictable for users,
even if they don't know
the detailed rules.
Our work represents the first draft
of the definition,
we expect future work will refine it.
This is all technically elegant
but we need to make
sure we're actually
making things easier for users.
So we did a user's study
to compare elastic SDF
to the best existing alternative,
namely array programming
on a set of tasks
based on real world spreadsheets
we previously collected.
I'd like to highlight
a few findings.
First users experience
lower cognitive
workload using elastic SDF
compared to array programming,
based on the standard survey
called the NASA task load index.
Second, we have partial
data suggesting
that users solve tasks
faster on average
using elastic SDF compared
to array programming.
And finally, while users
stated a preference
for array programming
for simple tasks
they preferred elastic SDF
for more complex tasks.
This is no surprise
given the complex tasks
are much harder to solve
with array programming.
These results are
really promising them,
more work is needed to further
optimise the user experience.
So, we've seen briefly
how we can use ideas
from programming language
theory to offer spreadsheets
uses an easier way to reuse logic
on inputs of different sizes.
You can find the full definitions
algorithms and proofs in the paper.
We look forward to making
this functionality
widely available to improve
these to productivity.
Thanks for listening,
and we look forward to your
questions and feedback.
(CLAPPING BACKGROUND)
JEREMY: Thanks Matt, if you're watching
the New York streaming Clowdr.
You should now see a Q&A link,
where you can ask Matt
questions by video chat.
The next and final
talk in this session
is a presentation of
the paper,
Emerging Languages and Alternative
Approach to Teaching Programme
by Saverio Perugini, which argues that a
course on
The principles of programming
languages should not be structured
according to those principles,
but around emerging languages
such as Lula and Elixir instead.
SAVERIO PERUGINI: Hello, my name
is Saverio Perugini.
And today I'm going to be presenting
our journal of functional programming
paper emerging languages.
An alternative approach to
teaching programming languages.
I'm in the Department of Computer
Science at the University of Dayton.
So, while the learning outcomes
of a course in programming
languages are well established
the most effective approach
to teach a languages course,
is not a settled matter.
There is, there are
a myriad of approaches
there the two predominant approaches
are the principles slash
concepts based approach
and the interpreter based approach.
There's also a paradigm
survey based approach,
there are hybrids of these.
Each involve challenges
In this work we challenged the idea
that of course intended
to convey the concepts of languages
should therefore be structured,
according to those concepts.
We saw that each programming languages
from a different perspective,
the approach we developed involves
using emerging languages
as a conduit through
which students incidentally bump
into the concepts of languages,
the implementation options
available for them,
and the compelling consequences
of those options on programming,
which are the student learning
outcomes the SLO's,
of course in programming languages.
Now, when we say emerging languages
what we mean here is languages
that have adopted functional
features to some extent or another.
In the last 20 years or so
so languages like lula
elixir, go, python, and so on.
And despite the moniker
for this approach.
The goal here is not
to teach students,
emerging languages, and thus
the course must not involve,
or perhaps I should say
devolved into an isolated row
investigation of a sequence
of emerging languages.
Rather, the goal here
is to teach students
the principles concepts
of languages.
As an intended, though, on
advertised side effect
of covering these
emerging languages,
under the guise of a survey course
on a variety of ha new languages.
The central thesis of this work is
that this alternative approach,
results in a variety of
course deezer durata
scope for an instructor
customisation alignment
with current trends and language
evolution practice and research,
and probably better aligned
with industrial needs.
What I'm going to discuss
here is the rationale for.
the course mechanics supporting
and the consequences of this approach.
So, the rational for
the emerging languages approach
is based on some simple ideas.
First, let's recognise that
students think in terms of
languages, not concepts.
I call that the the students
language centric perspective,
learning concepts of
programming language itself
sounds dull and academic
learning languages,
especially new and emerging ones,
and how those languages
apply in domains
in which students have passion.
Like game programming,
Internet of Things,
web frameworks, sounds like fun.
So why not take advantage of
the junxtaposition of the circumstances.
If we tell students we're going to,
they're going to to learn the lula.
Python, Ruby, that's something
they can get excited about.
Let's get students excited
about what they're studying
and then most effectively
harness that motivating
spirit to meet the learning
outcomes of the course.
Exploring the concepts,
implementation options,
and then the implications of
those options on programme.
So, step one, student thing concepts,
stinks languages is not concepts.
Let's further recognise,
that students are motivated
to learn emerging technologies
they perceive as relevant
to the software industry,
even if the only
ephemerally relevant.
That's what I would call the student
relevance centric perspective.
Most average students are
typically not going to get excited
about a required concepts of
programming languages course,
whose description indicates the use
of Lisp as
an implementation language,
which the students perceive as
not being used in industry,
not building the resume
and not helping them get a job.
Students, however, are motivated
to learn new hot languages
and novel emerging technologies.
Students perceive emerging languages
like Python and Ruby
as less academic,
more fun and more practically
applicable to real world problems
than languages like Lisp, which they
perceive as archaic and arcane.
I think the reason
for this perception
is that this perception is formed
and influenced by the culture
of the online ecosystem
in which students explore
probe experiences,
new languages and new
technologies on their own.
Things like vlogs, YouTube videos,
StackOverflow, GitHub, and so on.
So why can't we teach
students first class
in high order functions and closures
in Python rather than Lisp?
I mean, ultimately, nobody cares
if a student can programme less
rather, they care
if a student can think
like a Lisp programmemer in
higher order abstractions.
metaprogramming and
a variety of other languages.
So let's harness that process
of programming language
acculturation incubation in which
students participate,
perhaps unconsciously.
Given those circumstances,
we think it's reasonable
to use emerging
languages as a method
or conduit by which to dispel
Distil concepts of
languages to students.
And then of course, let's build
a course framework around that idea.
And let's use course
mechanics that leverage
how students learn languages on
their own, to teach them concepts.
So that's what we did. We
designed a course framer
to support that approach
or to order operate
operationalise that approach.
And the model we came
up with involves three
it's a module based approach.
It involves three modules.
It's a modular based
design, I should say,
involves three modules.
Students were given a foundation
and a vocabulary in language,
a brief foundation of vocabulary
in language concepts
through sort of a functional
programming tutorial
in module one which which was formed
the background from
which they deconstructed
the emerging languages
presented in module two
deconstruct those languages
into the concepts
and then probe those
concepts for subsequent
comparisons synthesis
use application
of those concepts in final
culminating projects in module three,
so, Module one, Brief Introduction
Identification of Language Concepts,
Module two Deconstructing the Emerging
Languages Presented to Prove those
Concepts
in Module three Reconstruct,
Reconstruct, Synthesise,
Apply those Concepts in,
in, in Projects.
now, that that third
module also helps
connect those languages back to
the concepts in module one.
Module two is really the
the heart and soul of the course
that the most number of
weeks, six to eight weeks,
it's really the the body of
the course the meat of the course.
Now, I do want to
mention in module two
module two is really
where the instructor
has the opportunity to
emulate as much as possible
the process by which students
learn languages on their own
through those those online
for I was discussing earlier.
So this is the module where we,
we, we did YouTube videos, we did.
Language cheat sheets or
quick reference sheets.
We did online style, blog webpages,
we did language Synopsys.
A lot of active learning going on.
Students presented each language
over the course of two
consecutive 75 minute periods
really trying to emulate the process
by white, by which students
learn, learn languages.
This also provide a graded
preparation for their final,
the same sort of mechanics that
we're using their final
culminating project.
We've offered this
course three times
three offerings using this approach.
And these are some of the languages
that we use, across some
of those offerings.
This is a subset of them.
And this is are
the student artefacts
and final projects and cheat sheets
and YouTube videos are all
posted in this GitHub site,
which I probably won't be able
to demonstrate or at
least illustrate later.
Module three is really the module
where where students are
given the opportunity
to demonstrate a mastery of
those concepts distil
during the emerging
languages presentations.
and really demonstrate
how they can use
their intuition to
independently discern
how and when and creatively harness
an integration of a subset
of those concept
that they absorbed
in that module to craft a
solution to a practical computing
problem in module three.
The project involved the software
system, a formal term paper
using the ACM conference
style and law tech and
an in class presentation
to classmates.
Now without a formal research
experiment, it's challenging to
ascertain the merit
of this approach and
helping students understand,
understand the core
language concepts.
We can, however, offer some
anecdotal and formal evidence.
This table I'm showing you here
presents the observed frequency
of the use of language concepts
of the language concepts
in the source code of
the final projects.
Now, again, while the observation
of an application and
integration and a use of these
concepts in the final and
the final projects can on its
own serve as formal evidence
that they understood the concepts.
It does provide some
anecdotal evidence,
particularly because many
of these projects were
of high quality and some
were even published.
OK. wrapping up here,
what are the what can you
expect from this approach?
What are the consequences.
It's customizable. The
instructors picking
different languages every semester.
The mechanics are
somewhat customizable,
although to a lesser extent, because
we're trying to use mechanics,
which, which one of the main
ideas here is using mechanics,
which would dovetail
nicely with how students
learn languages on their own.
It gets students away from
their Java-centric worldview.
We're covering a wide
spectrum of languages
in a relatively short
period of time,
which really radically shatters
students, Java-centric, a worldview,
promoting the idea that
students should use languages
for the particular problem
domain we're covering things
like you know, a new
concurrency models.
CSP actor Julia scientific
computing law game
programming MapReduce. So on
promotes academic integrity.
You're rotating the languages
out every semester.
Doesn't require a big inordinate,
an excess of work on the
instructors part because the students
are producing the artefacts.
It doesn't compromise
learning outcomes.
The outcomes are the same,
the mechanisms different.
Aligns well with industrial
needs, promotes professional
preparation
and academic preparation.
Of course, there are challenges.
Scaling the approach
is certainly a challenge,
especially in sections with large
number of students, 50
to a hundred students.
There's an entire section of
the paper dedicated to some
sort of rough calculations
on how you might adapt
the approach to large sections.
There are some other
challenges as well,
which are mentioned in the paper.
Concluding the idea presented
here, the approach presented
here is based on the idea that
we should teach programming
languages to students in
a mode that meshes well and
leverages both how students
think languages, not concepts.
They put languages before
concepts and how they learn
languages and new technologies
on their own online for
YouTube videos, stack overflow
and things like that.
I hope my goal with this
presentation in this paper is that
get the discussion going,
challenge the idea,
how we teach programming languages.
I hope it encouraged people to
think this folks that think
differently and to bring this
back to their institutions.
I encourage you to explore our
webpages, especially our get hub site,
which involves all the the language
Synopsys, YouTube videos,
presentations, and then some of
the projects are posted as well.
At this point, I'd like to
thank you for your attention.
And I certainly welcome
you to contact me
with questions
and comments. Thank you.
(CLAPS)
RICHARD: Thanks. I'm afraid that
Saverio is not available for
live Q&A So that
ends this session.
Please do, let me know what
you think of this scheme. Bye.
(UPLIFTING ORCHESTRAL MUSIC)